<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fieldwork | Benjamin Hills</title>
    <link>https://benhills.github.io/category/fieldwork/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://benhills.github.io/category/fieldwork/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Fieldwork</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://benhills.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Fieldwork</title>
      <link>https://benhills.github.io/category/fieldwork/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combatant Col</title>
      <link>https://benhills.github.io/blog/waddington/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://benhills.github.io/blog/waddington/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We typically think of ice cores in the context of global climate.
For instance, Antarctic ice cores demonstrate the link between greenhouse gases and temperature, both through glacial cycles (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature02599&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dome C&lt;/a&gt;) and into the human era (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1029/95JD03410&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Law Dome&lt;/a&gt;).
What many don’t know is that some of the most powerful ice-core interpretation has been for regional climate rather than global. Take &lt;a href=&#34;https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1029/95JD03410&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Richard Alley’s interpretation&lt;/a&gt; of the Younger Dryas from a Greenland ice core, GISP2.
Noticing substantial precipitation changes in Greenland over very short timescales (~decades), he argued for changes in both atmospheric and ocean circulation in the North Atlantic as the Earth was coming out of the last glacial period.
Ultimately, these changes led to a global climate event in the Younger Dryas, but the critical measurement for this inference was local to the North Atlantic around Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, we are focused on climate in the North Pacific and how that can be sampled using alpine ice cores from Southeast Alaska and, in this case specifically, coastal British Columbia.
The North Pacific is dominated by two pressure systems, the Aleutian Low and the North Pacific High.
Seattle-ites will be very familiar with the effects of these pressure systems.
During winter, cold temperatures move the high pressure system to lower latitude and allow the Aleutian Low to grow which brings wet weather to Seattle and the broader Pacific Northwest.
Alpine ice cores preserve the dynamics of this system and how it may have changed over the last ~few hundred years.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-atmospheric-circulation-in-the-north-pacific&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Atmospheric circulation in the North Pacific.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/waddington/aleutian_low_hu8dc042ba89a8cea4a010c46d7b18f6b8_3544519_49765eef5c27a0911645bdc707f9eacc.webp 400w,
               /blog/waddington/aleutian_low_hu8dc042ba89a8cea4a010c46d7b18f6b8_3544519_8930348f6ff4488ce1c722a0dc31b84f.webp 760w,
               /blog/waddington/aleutian_low_hu8dc042ba89a8cea4a010c46d7b18f6b8_3544519_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/waddington/aleutian_low_hu8dc042ba89a8cea4a010c46d7b18f6b8_3544519_49765eef5c27a0911645bdc707f9eacc.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;443&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Atmospheric circulation in the North Pacific.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mt. Waddington is the highest mountain in British Columbia.
As may be expected for such a prominent piece of earth, it obstructs the wet air masses coming in from the Pacific and can get hammered with snow in the winter months.
Our estimates were for ~12 meters of snow to the previous summer&amp;rsquo;s surface or ~7.5 meters water equivalent! Compare this to Seattle where it rains about 1 meter per year.
Combatant Col, where we are looking to drill an ice core, rests between Waddington and its neighbor to the north, Mt. Combatant.
Enough ice accumulates in this mountain saddle to make it a flat and relatively safe space to camp away from the avalanches and mountain debris coming off both peaks.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-mt-waddington-summit-and-combatant-col-indicated-by-the-arrow-photo-from-summitpostorghttpswwwsummitpostorgmount-waddington153091&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Mt. Waddington summit and Combatant Col indicated by the arrow. Photo from [summitpost.org](https://www.summitpost.org/mount-waddington/153091).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/waddington/waddington_summit_hu69822adf3778783218d5352367cfe673_5919218_cc635e196097489ab7d7fda081699571.webp 400w,
               /blog/waddington/waddington_summit_hu69822adf3778783218d5352367cfe673_5919218_95b6c2268b9cbd751eb6450fb64c4e29.webp 760w,
               /blog/waddington/waddington_summit_hu69822adf3778783218d5352367cfe673_5919218_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/waddington/waddington_summit_hu69822adf3778783218d5352367cfe673_5919218_cc635e196097489ab7d7fda081699571.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Mt. Waddington summit and Combatant Col indicated by the arrow. Photo from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.summitpost.org/mount-waddington/153091&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;summitpost.org&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My colleagues at the University of Washington, Peter Neff (now at University of Minnesota) and Eric Steig, started work at Mt. Waddington for Peter’s M.S. degree (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal-of-glaciology/article/icecore-net-snow-accumulation-and-seasonal-snow-chemistry-at-a-temperateglacier-site-mount-waddington-southwest-british-columbia-canada/BFE67E26A16331B73DE8986FE05CBBE2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Neff et al., 2012&lt;/a&gt;).
They were successful in drilling a 141-meter core but were obstructed from drilling any deeper by substantial water within the firn, what has now come to be known as a ‘perennial firn aquifer’ based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/ngeo2043&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;similar features in Greenland&lt;/a&gt;.
Despite not extending as far in time as they had hoped, the results from their ice core are novel and interesting.
Layer thicknesses (for precipitation) and water isotopes (for temperature) are used for local and regional climate interpretation.
They sample black carbon within the core which comes from summertime smoke associated with regional wildfires. One of the interesting aspects of a future ice core will be extending this wildfire record well into the pre-industrial.
They found a drop in lead concentrations in the 1980’s which, while not as interesting from an atmospheric process understanding perspective, demonstrates how effective policymakers can be in altering the atmosphere.
Leaded gasoline was forcibly phased out starting with the Clean Air Act in 1970 but followed by a series of regulations and an outright ban in 1996.
The firn core at Combatant Col recorded the response beautifully.
These are the types of examples that give me hope in an era of rampant climate despair. Another example would be the CFC regulations in the Montreal Protocol now acting to &lt;a href=&#34;https://csl.noaa.gov/assessments/ozone/2018/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;heal the ozone hole&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-data-from-the-first-ice-core-drilled-in-2010-neff-et-al-2012&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Data from the first ice core drilled in 2010 (Neff et al., 2012).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/waddington/core_data_hu9788511722b77b6da4f0c0bd36ca8dc3_2389218_1bda6488e8f317f7a2610163dcc34bb2.webp 400w,
               /blog/waddington/core_data_hu9788511722b77b6da4f0c0bd36ca8dc3_2389218_4876ba64fd86f43567dbda2ba85f1c1d.webp 760w,
               /blog/waddington/core_data_hu9788511722b77b6da4f0c0bd36ca8dc3_2389218_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/waddington/core_data_hu9788511722b77b6da4f0c0bd36ca8dc3_2389218_1bda6488e8f317f7a2610163dcc34bb2.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;488&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Data from the first ice core drilled in 2010 (Neff et al., 2012).
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our objective in this field season was to more carefully survey the col with geophysical tools in preparation for another (hopefully deeper) ice core to be drilled in summer 2023.
We used two distinct radar systems for two separate purposes.
First, we used a 10-MHz radar to survey the ice thickness, with the idea being that this relatively low frequency wave should be able to propagate through some water in the firn aquifer to create a reflection off the ice-bed interface.
Second, we used a 100-MHz radar to survey the firn aquifer itself. We get a strong reflection off the water table, so it is quite easy to know where there is standing water and its relative depth below the snow surface.
We do not get a good reflection from the bottom of the firn aquifer, so it is harder to know the total volume of water present or how deep the water can infiltrate before all available pore space is closed off as the firn transitions into solid ice.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-pulling-the-deep-sounding-radar-system-on-skis-with-the-second-summit-of-mt-waddington-in-the-background-the-orange-sled-in-the-foreground-holds-the-radar-transmitter-and-a-precision-gps-up-on-the-pole-the-maroon-sled-closer-to-the-skier-holds-the-radar-receiver-and-the-hoses-on-either-side-of-the-sleds-are-the-radar-antennas&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Pulling the deep-sounding radar system on skis with the second summit of Mt. Waddington in the background. The orange sled in the foreground holds the radar transmitter and a precision GPS up on the pole. The maroon sled, closer to the skier, holds the radar receiver, and the hoses on either side of the sleds are the radar antennas.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/waddington/dragging_radar_hud8c5d75f0c55580faccd25ca871cf326_3250552_2c52f3d59242fb9818b8741805c00350.webp 400w,
               /blog/waddington/dragging_radar_hud8c5d75f0c55580faccd25ca871cf326_3250552_5abb8cb575765cedcd3bc6b05b83d1b7.webp 760w,
               /blog/waddington/dragging_radar_hud8c5d75f0c55580faccd25ca871cf326_3250552_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/waddington/dragging_radar_hud8c5d75f0c55580faccd25ca871cf326_3250552_2c52f3d59242fb9818b8741805c00350.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;570&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Pulling the deep-sounding radar system on skis with the second summit of Mt. Waddington in the background. The orange sled in the foreground holds the radar transmitter and a precision GPS up on the pole. The maroon sled, closer to the skier, holds the radar receiver, and the hoses on either side of the sleds are the radar antennas.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-preliminary-results-from-both-shallow-radar-top-and-deep-radar-bottom-the-x-axis-is-the-distance-we-traversed-along-the-surface-and-the-y-axis-is-the-time-between-radar-transmit-and-receive-in-microseconds-and-converted-to-the-corresponding-depth-approximate&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Preliminary results from both shallow radar (top) and deep radar (bottom). The x-axis is the distance we traversed along the surface, and the y-axis is the time between radar transmit and receive (in microseconds) and converted to the corresponding depth (approximate).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/waddington/blog_radar_hueb7496d28b9c0aaf0be5c991dad47c3b_2242778_7ac972fe519ef413093328283df9438a.webp 400w,
               /blog/waddington/blog_radar_hueb7496d28b9c0aaf0be5c991dad47c3b_2242778_65a9abd4a034cd0b8d701be651ea34f6.webp 760w,
               /blog/waddington/blog_radar_hueb7496d28b9c0aaf0be5c991dad47c3b_2242778_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/waddington/blog_radar_hueb7496d28b9c0aaf0be5c991dad47c3b_2242778_7ac972fe519ef413093328283df9438a.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;732&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Preliminary results from both shallow radar (top) and deep radar (bottom). The x-axis is the distance we traversed along the surface, and the y-axis is the time between radar transmit and receive (in microseconds) and converted to the corresponding depth (approximate).
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our deep radar results look quite different from the stereotypical ice-penetrating radar profile which often has beautifully conformal stratigraphy and a glaringly bright bed reflection (see some examples &lt;a href=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/photo/radar/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).
Instead, we see a bit of a garbled mess, with scattering pretty much everywhere.
In the field I found this quite frustrating, especially that we were not getting an obvious bed reflection.
I spent about a day trying to adjust the radar settings to optimize for these wet conditions.
With no significant improvement and a constrained timeline, I eventually decided we would go ahead and do the survey, that the radar instrument itself was working as well as it could be, and hoping that we could pull out a bit more information with careful post-processing.
In the end, this has turned out to be the case. The data are high quality, there is simply so much water in this temperate ice that we see reflections off of &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; through the entire ice column.
We think that the bottom of these messy reflections delineates the boundary between ice and rock (roughly drawn in red on the figure).
The shallow data are as expected, with a clear reflection at the water table in the firn, but also with a not-so-pleasant surprise of some buried crevasses at the edges of our surveyed area.
Fortunately, they are deep and we were also quite careful roping up away from our camp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any field trip, this week in BC came with a few fun mishaps.
We left Seattle early on a Wednesday morning, hoping to make the ~12 hour drive all the way to White Saddle in one day.
Even before crossing into Canada we found ourselves on the side of the road with a car full of glass from Peter&amp;rsquo;s driver&amp;rsquo;s side window.
An oncoming truck had kicked up a rock which shattered their window. Luckily, Peter stayed calm or it could have turned into a bigger accident.
Having trouble scheduling an auto glass shop, Peter and his student Julia stayed at his mom&amp;rsquo;s house for the night (a situation Peter described as &amp;lsquo;his nightmare&amp;rsquo;, bringing his student to his mom&amp;rsquo;s house) while I continued onward.
Even more eventful was our last night up on the col.
I am a heavy sleeper, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t wake up until I heard my tent vestibule vigorously flapping in the wind.
I poked my head out to check that it was still there and was greeted with some hefty gusts.
A few minutes later I hear clashes and clangs from our kitchen tent followed by a series of profanities from Peter&amp;rsquo;s tent.
Peter was up in an instant trying to chase it, but there was no chance, our tent was long gone.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-broken-window-an-hour-into-our-trip&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Broken window an hour into our trip...&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/waddington/broken_window_hu6263fe60296d2f6637cb2d46fd5f6aa4_4760825_aacabac321aa2f6dc299480cbe5a8712.webp 400w,
               /blog/waddington/broken_window_hu6263fe60296d2f6637cb2d46fd5f6aa4_4760825_ced160cbb4f282012a4802f52ed0a4c7.webp 760w,
               /blog/waddington/broken_window_hu6263fe60296d2f6637cb2d46fd5f6aa4_4760825_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/waddington/broken_window_hu6263fe60296d2f6637cb2d46fd5f6aa4_4760825_aacabac321aa2f6dc299480cbe5a8712.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;573&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Broken window an hour into our trip&amp;hellip;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#39;Working remotely&#39; as a polar field scientist</title>
      <link>https://benhills.github.io/blog/remote-fieldwork/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://benhills.github.io/blog/remote-fieldwork/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are wrapping up our fourth* season at Hercules Dome, Antarctica. I use an asterisk because it hasn’t really been the fourth at all. For the first season, in ‘18-’19, we had a 4-person team who was meant to deploy a full field camp for a full month of work on the ground; instead, we spent ~6 weeks at South Pole Station for a handful of day trips commuting back and forth to Hercules Dome. The second season was as expected, ‘19-’20 brought a 7-person team to the field where we did most of the surveying seen in the figure below. The third “season” was not a season at all, Covid halted nearly 100% of Antarctic field work in ‘20-’21. Finally, this current season that is wrapping up now was a small and lightweight team, with only a single scientist on the ground, meant to get in for only a few repeat acquisitions and nothing else. Hercules Dome was originally proposed as a 2-year surveying project and has now been extended to a total of 5 seasons, such is the nature of Antarctic fieldwork during a global pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-map-of-our-ongoing-survey-at-hercules-dome-overlaid-on-the-rema-surface-elevation-solid-lines-show-positions-of-the-profiling-radar-transects-where-we-map-ice-stratigraphy-and-structure-of-the-underlying-bedrock-dots-show-locations-where-we-measure-vertical-ice-motion-with-a-specialized-radar-system-red-circles-show-the-priority-for-repeat-measurements-that-happened-this-season&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A map of our ongoing survey at Hercules Dome overlaid on the REMA surface elevation. Solid lines show positions of the profiling radar transects where we map ice stratigraphy and structure of the underlying bedrock. Dots show locations where we measure vertical ice motion with a specialized radar system. Red circles show the priority for repeat measurements that happened this season.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/HD_map_2122_hu1d4487603f979735dcc191e2140be7c6_1788984_ac925f73060b24f9a63e46b7cb24c29d.webp 400w,
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/HD_map_2122_hu1d4487603f979735dcc191e2140be7c6_1788984_e7a18f8e9ffdb530d5a88f3d1626180f.webp 760w,
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/HD_map_2122_hu1d4487603f979735dcc191e2140be7c6_1788984_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/remote-fieldwork/HD_map_2122_hu1d4487603f979735dcc191e2140be7c6_1788984_ac925f73060b24f9a63e46b7cb24c29d.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;571&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A map of our ongoing survey at Hercules Dome overlaid on the REMA surface elevation. Solid lines show positions of the profiling radar transects where we map ice stratigraphy and structure of the underlying bedrock. Dots show locations where we measure vertical ice motion with a specialized radar system. Red circles show the priority for repeat measurements that happened this season.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was supposed to be the UW scientist on the ground this season, but I failed the physical qualification examination (PQ) due to mild anxiety/depression. I am not particularly bitter about this. We were able to find a fantastic last-minute replacement, Erika Schreiber of Unavco, who successfully made all of our top priority measurements. Moreover, I was able to spend the holidays with my new fiancée and her family. Having said that, I do want to explain what happened and why I think it is problematic.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-my-fiancée-dani-decorating-the-first-christmas-tree-we-have-had-as-our-own-after-being-together-for-9-years&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;My fiancée, Dani, decorating the first Christmas tree we have had as our own after being together for ~9 years.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/tree_hue89a0aa046b09da89068440f8a9c75be_126460_28266a1c1bc72b1dfd2ef3c930812567.webp 400w,
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/tree_hue89a0aa046b09da89068440f8a9c75be_126460_ebf917d9d79ecfc110fb209b8ca701dd.webp 760w,
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/tree_hue89a0aa046b09da89068440f8a9c75be_126460_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/remote-fieldwork/tree_hue89a0aa046b09da89068440f8a9c75be_126460_28266a1c1bc72b1dfd2ef3c930812567.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;472&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      My fiancée, Dani, decorating the first Christmas tree we have had as our own after being together for ~9 years.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In July, I returned from Montana, where I had been riding out the pandemic, to Seattle in order to carry out my PQ. The necessary procedures include dental exams, blood work, as well as a range of other tests depending on the candidate&amp;rsquo;s age and history within the US Antarctic Program. As some examples, in preparation for my first Greenland deployment they made me get an EKG, and this year the doctor insisted that we do a prostate exam because the language on the document did not make it sufficiently clear that this is only necessary for middle-aged men. Like many others, I have a history of mild anxiety/depression for which I have been prescribed an SSRI in the past. This would not normally be an issue for Antarctic fieldwork, I have travelled to Antarctica carrying this medication before. I have even deployed without the medication at a time when I had elected to stop taking it, my doctor being unconcerned. This year was a bit different though. A flag came up during the mental health check on my PQ (who hasn’t been depressed during Covid??) and I learned that once the flag goes up it is very hard to bring it back down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything being in flux, I saw a new doctor for my PQ this season, one who had no context of my medical history. She was rightfully concerned about my mental health going into a solo field deployment, so she checked the box saying “participant will require further evaluation prior to clearance” since she wanted to start me back on the SSRI for a month before clearing me. Note that this was in July and I was due to deploy in November, so there was time for a secondary evaluation. I believe that my doctor saw me as fit to deploy assuming that I took well to the medication; unfortunately, the medical staff who carry out the PQ paperwork did not see it this way and disqualified me before my doctor could do any further evaluation. There is a procedure to waive the disqualification, but it involves my University signing off on a liability agreement which they were ultimately unwilling to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel mostly unaffected by this disruption since we were able to find a replacement, and I was well supported by my academic advisor as well as my friends and family. However, this exposed me to inefficiencies within the PQ process which I feel could be more disruptive to others, especially younger students who have not had as many opportunities for fieldwork (note that this is a critical learning experience for many earth scientists). Mental health concerns are rampant among academics, and there should be a clear pathway toward successful participation in field campaigns for anyone who can safely do so. Moreover, the review procedure should rely more heavily on trained mental health professionals. My counselor said that she would be willing to sign off in approval of my deployment, but unfortunately her voice did not carry much weight in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After much back and forth, the decision was made clear that I would not deploy for this season only a few weeks before the scheduled departure. Luckily for us, Erika agreed to fill in as a replacement on this extremely short notice. While she had significant polar experience prior to this season, she had never deployed to Antarctica and obviously didn’t have direct experience at Hercules Dome. Suffice it to say, she got her fill of Zoom calls with me and my advisor. Not only did we need to explain our scientific priorities and instrument procedures, but we also had numerous favors for other field groups which she graciously took on. Luckily she had time for reading and reviewing during her 2-week quarantine in New Zealand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After numerous layovers Erika finally arrived at South Pole Station on December 7th. From there, she would acclimatize before using the Twin Otter as a flight commuter for day trips to Hercules Dome. As is typical for this type of work, she faced weather delays during which she did instrument tests around the South Pole. We were having regular calls and she would send data back to us so that we could check that the instrument was working properly. I could tell with certainty whether she was making the measurement in the same way we had done in the past because she was reoccupying old field sites and if done properly the radar return would be coherent with prior acquisitions. Finally, on December 17th, we had our first true science day at Hercules Dome. She returned with the data shown below which, as you can see in the bottom panel, nicely reproduce a prior result of the vertical velocity structure.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-top-panel-coherence-represents-how-similar-the-measured-waveforms-are-between-two-acquisitions-middle-panel-the-phase-offset-tells-us-how-far-a-feature-has-moved-updown-within-the-ice-bottom-panel-the-vertical-velocity-is-simply-the-phase-offset-converted-to-units-of-distance-over-time&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Top panel: Coherence represents how similar the measured waveforms are between two acquisitions. Middle panel: The phase offset tells us how far a feature has moved up/down within the ice. Bottom panel: The vertical velocity is simply the phase offset converted to units of distance over time.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/blog_pres_hu29b6964728c3af8ef7372565a95e8991_300189_0f82244d7eea5f05bc65cad67b9a2eb4.webp 400w,
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/blog_pres_hu29b6964728c3af8ef7372565a95e8991_300189_be6231dd76636685ef311e9e3b9c53c0.webp 760w,
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/blog_pres_hu29b6964728c3af8ef7372565a95e8991_300189_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/remote-fieldwork/blog_pres_hu29b6964728c3af8ef7372565a95e8991_300189_0f82244d7eea5f05bc65cad67b9a2eb4.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;633&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Top panel: Coherence represents how similar the measured waveforms are between two acquisitions. Middle panel: The phase offset tells us how far a feature has moved up/down within the ice. Bottom panel: The vertical velocity is simply the phase offset converted to units of distance over time.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside of the scientific priority for the season, a logistical priority was to revisit the cache that we buried in ‘19-’20. Most of what was left there is unimportant, things like food remaining from that season and relatively inexpensive gear such as shovels and sleds. What do need to be recovered are the 30+ drums of fuel we left, most of which is for the airplanes which will now use Hercules Dome as a remote gas station. Erika and the team did not have time to un-dig the cache, so they reflagged it and left the work for next year. Lucky for me, I like digging :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, the upcoming and final season at Hercules Dome will be a full field campaign similar to what we had in ‘19-’20. We need to deploy the field camp in order to fill in the remainder of the survey shown in the top figure. Based partially on new information from the measurements that Erika made this season, we are now focusing wholeheartedly on West Dome as the site at which the ice core will likely be drilled. The ‘22-’23 priority will be to densify our survey around West Dome in order to choose a precise drilling location. Fortunately, the PQ process is renewed on an annual basis, so my disqualification this year has no bearing on future deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Go Back?</title>
      <link>https://benhills.github.io/blog/why-go-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://benhills.github.io/blog/why-go-back/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;They say that the first time you go to Antarctica is for the adventure, the second for the science, and the third because you no longer belong anywhere else. I would hope that it is always for the science, but I do understand how people get attached to the community down here. Life on the ice is mission oriented; whether for science or support, the team knows what needs to get done and works together to accomplish the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you read my writing last year, you will know that we had some logistical issues with our project at Hercules Dome. In a way, we had to come back to even get a real start. Having said that, it is common for field projects to be spread across multiple seasons, and some of our team will be coming down next year as well. I want to give somewhat of an explanation for why any field-based project would need more than one season on the ice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;logistical-reasons-to-return&#34;&gt;Logistical Reasons to Return&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first and perhaps most obvious reason that we come back is that there is simply too much work to do in the short Antarctic summer. The only working months for deep field projects in Antarctica are late-November, December, and January. After accounting for some bad weather days, time on the front and back end to move cargo around and test equipment, and expected flight delays, there is not much time left to do the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Hercules Dome, our original plan was to have two field seasons over which to spread the surveying that we had planned, the ’18-’19 and the ’19-’20 austral summers. For each, we planned ~20-30 dedicated science days with a small team of 6-7 personnel in an isolated field camp. Last year, a decision was made early in the season that the surface conditions were too rough at our field site to land the LC-130-Hercules (‘Herc’) which is the Air National Guard plane that we needed to bring in our cargo. Based on that decision, our contingency was to do day trips from South Pole Station using the Twin Otter (a much smaller aircraft). Our total number of science days at Hercules Dome last year amounted to ~2.5, so we obviously did not get done all of what we were hoping for. Fortunately, NSF agreed to fund us for an additional season (&amp;lsquo;20-&amp;lsquo;21) because of these logistical setbacks.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-our-groomed-skiway-at-hercules-dome-with-the-field-camp-on-the-right-hand-side-note-the-scale-of-the-surface-roughness-these-sastrugi-are-what-prevented-us-from-landing-the-herc-last-year-photo-credit-rodney-fishbrook-our-twin-otter-pilot-for-the-first-half-of-the-season&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Our groomed skiway at Hercules Dome with the field camp on the right-hand side. Note the scale of the surface roughness, these sastrugi are what prevented us from landing the Herc last year. Photo credit: Rodney Fishbrook, our Twin Otter pilot for the first half of the season.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/why-go-back/skiway_hu7d1472b035cfc73c709fc3246cf2351f_610022_0612fcde909166421a5771350a72117b.webp 400w,
               /blog/why-go-back/skiway_hu7d1472b035cfc73c709fc3246cf2351f_610022_ed8b1e68355778645b321d9727586813.webp 760w,
               /blog/why-go-back/skiway_hu7d1472b035cfc73c709fc3246cf2351f_610022_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/why-go-back/skiway_hu7d1472b035cfc73c709fc3246cf2351f_610022_0612fcde909166421a5771350a72117b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;577&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Our groomed skiway at Hercules Dome with the field camp on the right-hand side. Note the scale of the surface roughness, these sastrugi are what prevented us from landing the Herc last year. Photo credit: Rodney Fishbrook, our Twin Otter pilot for the first half of the season.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with our limited success, the radar data that we were able to collect last year were instrumental in starting to understand the dome and in our survey planning for this season. Coming into this season, we were able to place a 4-person ground crew in the field in late November to groom a skiway for the Herc to land on. The grooming equipment is a 500-lb frame with adjustable metal tines that plow the snow. We have been calling it a ‘glorified pneumatic rake’ which is dragged behind a snowmobile, essentially amounting to carving out a patch of the ice sheet with a lawn-mower . On December 22nd, the plane landed with ~13,000 pounds of cargo. Then, on December 26th the remaining crew (including myself) landed at Hercules Dome and our science could begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;scientific-reasons-to-return&#34;&gt;Scientific Reasons to Return&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, our science also necessitates that we return to complete our measurements of ice motion. Ice moves slowly, especially at an ice divide or an ice dome like Hercules Dome, so we need to wait a considerable amount of time before we can return to measure how far it has moved. For horizontal motion, we use precision GPS instruments at the ice surface which give us a static location at one point in time. Leaving a surveying marker in the snow, we can return the following year to repeat the GPS measurement and learn how far it has moved in the horizontal direction. For vertical motion, we use a special phase-coherent radar instrument. This instrument is similar to our other ice-penetrating radar systems, but with a critical difference that it records phase information from the wave alongside the conventional measurement of wave amplitude through time.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-waveform-represented-in-the-complex-plane&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A waveform represented in the complex plane.&#34;
           src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/why-go-back/phase.gif&#34;
           loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A waveform represented in the complex plane.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing why a phase measurement can be useful warrants another short physics lesson. There are three components to any wave, the frequency is how long it takes for a 2-pi period of the wave to pass, the amplitude is a measure of the real ‘strength’ of the signal, and the phase is the time-varying location of the wave within its periodic cycle. The animation above shows a waveform as represented in the complex plane. Looking at the circle, the phase of the waveform is represented by the angle that the rotating line makes with the horizontal; hence, the phase repeats itself every time the moving point completes the circle (i.e. at 2 pi). While the power (i.e. the radius of the circle) remains constant in time, the real component fluctuates. With a conventional radar system, we would only measure the real component of the waveform, so there is no way to know the phase. However, with a phase-coherent radar system, we use information that we know about the transmitted waveform to back out the imaginary component as well and can then know the phase with precision to ~1 degree. With a center frequency of 300 MHz, the 1-degree precision allows us to measure vertical ice motion on the order of mm.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-annika-fixing-one-of-our-radar-systems-while-we-wait-for-the-apres-to-run-being-a-particularly-distant-site-we-had-to-fly-here-in-the-twin-otter-which-can-be-seen-on-the-horizon&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Annika fixing one of our radar systems while we wait for the ApRES to run. Being a particularly distant site, we had to fly here in the Twin Otter which can be seen on the horizon.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/why-go-back/annika-pres_hu13302735ebbf5f45f6b9c1477bda07d6_2075478_4a82c58bd458a6293fd239a127972109.webp 400w,
               /blog/why-go-back/annika-pres_hu13302735ebbf5f45f6b9c1477bda07d6_2075478_5978deff64dbac51f6427972fb3aaf24.webp 760w,
               /blog/why-go-back/annika-pres_hu13302735ebbf5f45f6b9c1477bda07d6_2075478_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/why-go-back/annika-pres_hu13302735ebbf5f45f6b9c1477bda07d6_2075478_4a82c58bd458a6293fd239a127972109.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;457&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Annika fixing one of our radar systems while we wait for the ApRES to run. Being a particularly distant site, we had to fly here in the Twin Otter which can be seen on the horizon.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the field, we are using a newly developed phase-sensitive radar system from the British Antarctic Survey known as the ApRES (Autonomous phase-sensitive Radio Echo Sounder). We use this system to measure vertical motion through the entire ice column using a series of impurity contrasts within the ice that cause reflections that we can observe. Since the impurity contrasts move with the ice, we can observe their movement. We were able to make a few ApRES measurements last year, so we have confirmation with our repeated measurements this year that the instrument is working. Having more time on the ground this season, we were able to collect 50 of these ApRES measurements. In the case that we are able to repeat them all next season, we will have a good idea of vertical motion over much of the dome.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-repeated-apres-measurement-used-to-infer-vertical-ice-motion-the-top-panel-is-the-measured-phase-over-a-sample-window-represented-by-the-moving-line-in-the-bottom-three-panels-the-second-panel-is-the-radar-profile-with-the-strength-of-the-returning-signal-being-diminished-with-depth-until-the-ice-bed-interface-at-2800-m-the-third-panel-is-the-correlation-between-the-year-1-and-year-2-measurements-as-expected-correlation-drops-off-below-1500-m-because-the-signal-is-noisy-for-deep-returns-the-fourth-panel-is-the-inferred-displacement-between-measurements-the-result-is-well-behaved-above-1500-m-where-the-correlation-is-high&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A repeated ApRES measurement used to infer vertical ice motion. The top panel is the measured phase over a sample window represented by the moving line in the bottom three panels. The second panel is the radar profile with the strength of the returning signal being diminished with depth until the ice-bed interface at ~2800 m. The third panel is the correlation between the year 1 and year 2 measurements. As expected, correlation drops off below ~1500 m because the signal is noisy for deep returns. The fourth panel is the inferred displacement between measurements, the result is well behaved above ~1500 m where the correlation is high.&#34;
           src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/why-go-back/pres.gif&#34;
           loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A repeated ApRES measurement used to infer vertical ice motion. The top panel is the measured phase over a sample window represented by the moving line in the bottom three panels. The second panel is the radar profile with the strength of the returning signal being diminished with depth until the ice-bed interface at ~2800 m. The third panel is the correlation between the year 1 and year 2 measurements. As expected, correlation drops off below ~1500 m because the signal is noisy for deep returns. The fourth panel is the inferred displacement between measurements, the result is well behaved above ~1500 m where the correlation is high.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;continuous-delays&#34;&gt;Continuous Delays&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of now, we are still waiting for a plane to take us off continent. The delays have been frustrating this year, not only for us, but for all of the deep field groups. For the most part, these delays have been inevitable. Early in the season, weather in West Antarctica created unsuitable flying conditions through late November and early December which is when most groups are trying to get out into the field. Additionally, we are short on LC-130’s and there was an early mechanical issue with the C-17 that set all the cargo movement behind starting in November. The delays on the way out have been a combination of mechanical and weather-related as well. By far our closest attempt to escape was on Saturday, my birthday. That day, we had a 10-hour trip out to the skifield here in McMurdo to watch the C-17 fly in from Christchurch, load our cargo, and then be told that the plane is now broken and will sit on the ground while wait to get a decision from Boeing on whether or not it can be flown. At around 10pm the no-fly decision was made. Lucky for us, they brought out food to tide us over during our long wait (i.e. hot dogs with no bun, utensils, or condiments…).&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-new-friends-to-greet-me-along-the-returning-journey-the-first-in-mcmurdo-and-the-second-still-waiting-for-me-back-home&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;New friends to greet me along the returning journey, the first in McMurdo and the second still waiting for me back home.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/why-go-back/critters_hu5173823e27f62e392edd7495b108e579_247288_af83d9718be9723d6ee1872fbc9dee20.webp 400w,
               /blog/why-go-back/critters_hu5173823e27f62e392edd7495b108e579_247288_bc3f6ff56f8f6494826428e969d67056.webp 760w,
               /blog/why-go-back/critters_hu5173823e27f62e392edd7495b108e579_247288_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/why-go-back/critters_hu5173823e27f62e392edd7495b108e579_247288_af83d9718be9723d6ee1872fbc9dee20.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;598&#34;
               height=&#34;255&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      New friends to greet me along the returning journey, the first in McMurdo and the second still waiting for me back home.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Glacier Mass Balance at South Cascade</title>
      <link>https://benhills.github.io/blog/mass-balance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://benhills.github.io/blog/mass-balance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I came home from a week-long field trip to South Cascade Glacier in Washington. South Cascade is one of the United States Geological Survey (USGS) benchmark glaciers, along with Gulkana and Wolverine in Alaska as well as Sperry in Glacier National Park, Montana. The benchmark glacier program was set up by the USGS to intensively monitor climate, glacier motion, glacier mass balance, glacier geometry, and stream runoff for these select glaciers which are thought to be representative of their respective region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why monitor glaciers? Aside from the fact that they are a fascinating aspect of the earth system, one reason is because they act as a low-pass filter on changes in climate. While climatic variables such as the air temperature and precipitation change on time scales as short as hours to days to years, ice flows slowly enough that it absorbs all the high-frequency information and responds at more like decadal (alpine glacier) or centennial (polar ice sheet) time scales. Therefore, glacier growth and decay are typically (c.f. tidewater glacier cycle) expressive of the longer term climate trend whether that be a change in temperature, precipitation, or both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a community, we have been measuring glacier change for at least several decades now. The easiest and most obvious way to do so is also the most illustrative for the public, a simple photo. Projects like the Extreme Ice Survey use photo time series to display glacier retreat in a way that needs no explanation. Some studies even use anecdotal evidence and drawings to extend the record further back in time (to 1602 for the Rhone Glacier). In our case at South Cascade, photos display that the terminus has retreated by ~3 kilometers over the past century. In the 1950&amp;rsquo;s and 60&amp;rsquo;s, this glacier terminated in a proglacial lake, but around 1970 the glacier pulled up out of the lake and now the terminus rests a full kilometer further uphill.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-photo-time-series-of-south-cascade-glacier-usgs&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A photo time series of South Cascade Glacier. USGS.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/mass-balance/history_hu6021e390eb012c2a28d2828b2a80ad68_497490_c7a04911d514d956333c96613858b503.webp 400w,
               /blog/mass-balance/history_hu6021e390eb012c2a28d2828b2a80ad68_497490_3f9441f5f04c3aa2d7a035f05f65abc0.webp 760w,
               /blog/mass-balance/history_hu6021e390eb012c2a28d2828b2a80ad68_497490_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/mass-balance/history_hu6021e390eb012c2a28d2828b2a80ad68_497490_c7a04911d514d956333c96613858b503.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;690&#34;
               height=&#34;550&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A photo time series of South Cascade Glacier. USGS.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-south-cascade-glacier-today-note-that-this-photo-was-taken-in-the-spring-so-there-is-considerably-more-snow-but-less-glacier-ice-than-above-photo-credit-gemma-oconnor&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;South Cascade Glacier today. Note that this photo was taken in the spring, so there is considerably more snow (but less glacier ice) than above. Photo credit: Gemma O&amp;#39;Connor.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/mass-balance/scg_hu8d171eafad3e5ec247601b00697c4980_4525133_85e6157b1b402b00aa22c1881da13c88.webp 400w,
               /blog/mass-balance/scg_hu8d171eafad3e5ec247601b00697c4980_4525133_52d7938e7319d4ba27b99bd7077066fb.webp 760w,
               /blog/mass-balance/scg_hu8d171eafad3e5ec247601b00697c4980_4525133_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/mass-balance/scg_hu8d171eafad3e5ec247601b00697c4980_4525133_85e6157b1b402b00aa22c1881da13c88.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      South Cascade Glacier today. Note that this photo was taken in the spring, so there is considerably more snow (but less glacier ice) than above. Photo credit: Gemma O&amp;rsquo;Connor.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mass-balance-methods&#34;&gt;Mass Balance Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While photos are illustrative, as scientists we want a more rigorous and quantitative way to measure glacier change. To do this, we calculate the ‘mass balance’ of the system, much like a water balance for those with experience in hydrology. The idea is what goes in must come out OR be stored in the glacier as ice. For a glacier, the balance input is snow, which through time is compressed into glacier ice, and the balance outputs are meltwater as well as iceberg calving. Hence, a negative mass balance means that there is more summer melting (and/or calving) than winter snow and the glacier therefore has a net loss (i.e. it is shrinking). On the other hand, a positive mass balance would mean net gains and glacier growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As shown in the schematic below, the high elevation areas of a glacier tend to have a positive mass balance because it snows more and melts less. This region is called the &amp;lsquo;accumulation area&amp;rsquo;. At lower elevations, melting dominates the system in the &amp;lsquo;ablation area&amp;rsquo;. The final component of glacier balance is ice flow from the net positive mass balance in the accumulation area to the net negative in the ablation area, keeping the system in a steady state if the glacier is stable.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-schematic-of-glacier-mass-balance-usgs&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A schematic of glacier mass balance. USGS.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/mass-balance/schematic_hu055126dfc99cfe5a0e61e19c9cac8081_138294_e5a1e29aff839d99510b33bf3be19737.webp 400w,
               /blog/mass-balance/schematic_hu055126dfc99cfe5a0e61e19c9cac8081_138294_bb235608989cfa893ad34cc9a9882fcb.webp 760w,
               /blog/mass-balance/schematic_hu055126dfc99cfe5a0e61e19c9cac8081_138294_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/mass-balance/schematic_hu055126dfc99cfe5a0e61e19c9cac8081_138294_e5a1e29aff839d99510b33bf3be19737.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;460&#34;
               height=&#34;322&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A schematic of glacier mass balance. USGS.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measuring glacier mass balance is relatively simple. For inputs, we drill a snow core or dig a snow pit at the end of the winter season and measure the total depth as well as density through the column. Together, depth and density give us an input balance in units of snow water equivalent (SWE). For outputs, we drill a metal stake into the ice at the beginning of summer and observe how quickly it has melted out by the end. Again, this measurement will be in SWE. Then the balance inputs (accumulation) and outputs (ablation) are summed to quantify glacier change. At South Cascade, the average mass balance over the past 50 years has been about -0.5 m/yr over the extent of the glacier&amp;rsquo;s area (Rasmussen and Conway, 2001; fig. 10).&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-gemma-oconnor-measuring-snow-densities-and-erin-whorton-taking-notes&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Gemma O&amp;#39;Connor measuring snow densities and Erin Whorton taking notes.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/mass-balance/pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_c1e50f56893692b0708f8b6d8fe88c7f.webp 400w,
               /blog/mass-balance/pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_950b77fe2f3a2c75513adfb62b78124a.webp 760w,
               /blog/mass-balance/pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/mass-balance/pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_c1e50f56893692b0708f8b6d8fe88c7f.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Gemma O&amp;rsquo;Connor measuring snow densities and Erin Whorton taking notes.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conventional mass balance methods described above are still in use for many glaciers today. Being glacier geophysicists though, we are interested in developing more innovative ways to get at the inputs and outputs for the system. In particular, we are using ice-penetrating radar to get a distributed snow depth measurement at the end of the winter season. The hope is not to abandon the snow coring completely, but to use the two in parallel to build a more robust, and glacier wide, observation for snow inputs to the glacier system. With radar, we can easily see a reflection of the previous summer&amp;rsquo;s surface (giving the total snow depth accumulated over the winter season), but in some areas we can also see deeper reflections from multi-year snow (firn) layers. Firn observations could provide insight into the mechanisms for accumulation in this alpine setting including avalanching and wind-blown snow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-global-perspective&#34;&gt;A Global Perspective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously the USGS are not the only group measuring glacier mass balance; in fact, most of the longer records come from European glaciers such as Storglaciären or Engabreen. Historically, most of the well-monitored glaciers tend to be those that are close to human civilizations. However, at the onset of the earth-observing satellite era (~1970) it became much easier to survey the global glacier network remotely. This includes glaciers in the arctic but also in North and South America, New Zealand, high mountain Asia, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, the global picture looks similar to what we see in our backyard. Mostly everything is melting, and over the past ~50 years the melt rates show an acceleration. Even though mountain glaciers don&amp;rsquo;t have the potential to effect future sea-level rise to the same extent as the polar ice sheets, there is still some contribution to sea-level rise (~mm/yr, see figure below), and the recession of alpine glaciers means a lot for both the surrounding ecological system as well as the communities that depend upon glaciers as a water supply.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-top-glaciers-around-the-globe-bottom-ice-mass-loss-and-mass-loss-rates-for-alpine-glaciers-around-the-world-these-figures-are-taken-from-the-ipcc-fifth-assessment-reporthttpswwwipccchreportar5wg1&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Top) Glaciers around the globe. Bottom) Ice mass loss and mass loss rates for alpine glaciers around the world. These figures are taken from the [IPCC fifth assessment report](https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/mass-balance/global_map_hub96782b94b601335ab68c556cc3b8482_737040_8b9c82d42c4679ee2463cfacf85692b7.webp 400w,
               /blog/mass-balance/global_map_hub96782b94b601335ab68c556cc3b8482_737040_86781388dcc5604d0c832c5890ad333b.webp 760w,
               /blog/mass-balance/global_map_hub96782b94b601335ab68c556cc3b8482_737040_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/mass-balance/global_map_hub96782b94b601335ab68c556cc3b8482_737040_8b9c82d42c4679ee2463cfacf85692b7.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;526&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Top) Glaciers around the globe. Bottom) Ice mass loss and mass loss rates for alpine glaciers around the world. These figures are taken from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IPCC fifth assessment report&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mass balance survey at South Cascade has been ongoing at the USGS since around 1960, and our collaboration with them will continue into future seasons. Stay tuned! Hopefully we will have more interesting (if somewhat sad) insights into this glacier&amp;rsquo;s health.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ice-Penetrating Radar</title>
      <link>https://benhills.github.io/blog/ice-penetrating-radar/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://benhills.github.io/blog/ice-penetrating-radar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We study ice dynamics; namely, how the Greenland and Antarctic ice sheets are moving, how they may have been moving in the past, and how they will move into the future. Ice flows downhill under the force of gravity. As it moves to lower elevation, it eventually either melts or calves and floats away, both contributing mass to the oceans. Thus, the principal importance of our research is to put constraints on future projections of sea-level rise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a geophysics team, the research tools that we use are a suite of geophysical methods including GPS, remote sensing (satellites), ice-penetrating radar, seismics, and physics-based computer models. With GPS and remote sensing methods we measure the elevation and velocity of the ice surface. We get at least cm precision with our GPS (down to mm when using real-time kinematics from a stationary base station). With radar and seismics, on the other hand, we survey the internal structure and intrinsic properties of the ice sheets. The basics of radar (seismic) methods are to transmit a radio (seismic) wave at the ice surface and to look (listen) for the reflections. The radio waves that we transmit are in the high to very-high frequency range (close to the same frequencies that you would use in your car or on a handheld radio). Seismics in glaciological applications are typically active source, using an explosion triggered at the surface. By measuring the time and amplitude of the returning waves (both radar and seismic), we learn what we need to build intuition about the dynamic nature of the ice-sheet system. Finally, we test our intuition using computer models.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-cartoon-illustration-of-ice-penetrating-radar-and-some-example-data-from-the-northeast-greenland-ice-stream&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A cartoon illustration of ice-penetrating radar and some example data from the Northeast Greenland Ice Stream.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ipr_cartoon_hu2dddb388711da89393e7649c08552bc5_475851_6956e7285cc7e35b22f10952a9cdc528.webp 400w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ipr_cartoon_hu2dddb388711da89393e7649c08552bc5_475851_7e0a5ab9ef5cdff4c9610c5315a3014b.webp 760w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ipr_cartoon_hu2dddb388711da89393e7649c08552bc5_475851_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ipr_cartoon_hu2dddb388711da89393e7649c08552bc5_475851_6956e7285cc7e35b22f10952a9cdc528.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;749&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A cartoon illustration of ice-penetrating radar and some example data from the Northeast Greenland Ice Stream.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I want to focus on radar methods for a couple of reasons. First, they are the primary focus of my personal research. In fact, I have never been on a seismic campaign. Second, our current field season at Herc Dome is a radar campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the fact that radio waves penetrate ice was discovered not by a glaciologist, but by an atmospheric physicist. In the 1960’s, a man named Piggott had an ionosonde stationed on the Brunt Ice Shelf, looking for radio-wave reflections off of the ionosphere. Curious about the consistently absent signal at a regularly-spaced interval, he proposed that reflections from below (off of the ice-water interface at the bottom of the floating ice shelf) were interfering with his primary reflections from the ionosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, we now know that Piggott was correct and have since developed theory as to why radio waves move so easily through crystalline ice. Most of the electromagnetic spectrum is absorbed by ice (making it opaque), although at different rates and by different mechanisms depending on frequency. High-energy photons (microwaves to visible light and higher) are absorbed and converted to either lattice vibrations (heat) or electronic transitions (electron jumps to a higher shell). Low-energy photons (~kHz radio waves) are absorbed by Debye Relaxation (molecular rotations). This leaves an absorption gap for the ~MHz frequency range that we use in our research. Therefore, radio waves at these frequencies can easily image ice that is 3-4 km thick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In using ice-penetrating radar to image the ice sheets, by far the strongest reflection comes from the ice-bedrock interface. This interface represents a permittivity contrast (i.e. that the radio wave travels faster through ice than it does through bedrock). Here it is useful to recall an illustrative demonstration on wave reflections from freshman physics. Take two ropes of unequal weight and tie them together. When a wave traveling through the lighter rope hits the knot between the two, some of the energy propagates forward as a wave in the heavier rope (although at a slower speed); however, the remaining energy is reflected back into the lighter rope in the direction from which it came. The idea in our ice-penetrating radar case is the same, with the knot in the rope being analogous to the ice-bedrock interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having ~50 years of experience behind us, we are building progressively better radar systems with which we can see not only the extremely bright bed reflector, but also the dimmer internal reflectors from within the ice column. Similarly to the bed, these are permittivity contrasts which are typically a result of variations in the impurity content of the ice. The visible stratigraphy of the ice mapped by these internal reflectors leads to the somewhat obvious geometric interpretations of radar data, but we are also starting to use the information in the amplitude of the measured waveform for additional insight. For example, if the ice-bedrock interface is melted the reflection is brighter, so we can use the strength of a bed reflection to say something about the nature of the bed.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-theradar-shelter-containing-the-computer-a-gps-on-top-and-the-leading-red-as-well-as-trailing-black-antennae-the-shelter-is-a-nice-break-from-the-wind-but-it-is-still-not-warm-in-here&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The radar shelter containing the computer, a GPS on top, and the leading (red) as well as trailing (black) antennae. The shelter is a nice break from the wind, but it is still not warm in here.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/radar-shelter_hud91ee38fd9ecc041d795446f233bb91a_266073_66676853e8ea18f6769d7024b64192a6.webp 400w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/radar-shelter_hud91ee38fd9ecc041d795446f233bb91a_266073_3367372f29d6aeb218d763d531d7712d.webp 760w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/radar-shelter_hud91ee38fd9ecc041d795446f233bb91a_266073_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/ice-penetrating-radar/radar-shelter_hud91ee38fd9ecc041d795446f233bb91a_266073_66676853e8ea18f6769d7024b64192a6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;571&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The radar shelter containing the computer, a GPS on top, and the leading (red) as well as trailing (black) antennae. The shelter is a nice break from the wind, but it is still not warm in here.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-apres-radar-with-the-data-logger-in-the-center-next-to-the-gps-and-the-two-antennae-stretched-out-on-either-side&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The ApRES radar with the data logger in the center next to the GPS and the two antennae stretched out on either side.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/apres_hubb6e1558ebe2ad9a2005af4a458250be_1936637_53b5f59b7fc7b2a226742ec8ac294236.webp 400w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/apres_hubb6e1558ebe2ad9a2005af4a458250be_1936637_0b1b7098f02f6eff063a1f79d1f0f7dd.webp 760w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/apres_hubb6e1558ebe2ad9a2005af4a458250be_1936637_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/ice-penetrating-radar/apres_hubb6e1558ebe2ad9a2005af4a458250be_1936637_53b5f59b7fc7b2a226742ec8ac294236.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;306&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The ApRES radar with the data logger in the center next to the GPS and the two antennae stretched out on either side.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Herc Dome we are using 3 radars. The first is a high frequency system (3 MHz) with which we can see to the bed of the ice sheet. Unfortunately though, there is a tradeoff between range and resolution, the 3 MHz antennae give us data that can be vertically resolved only to the scale of ~meters. For this reason, we also use a very-high frequency system (500 MHz) which gives us more like cm-scale resolution although its signal is fully attenuated by about 20 m below the surface. The third system is a phase-coherent radar called the ApRES (autonomous phase-sensitive radio-echo sounder). This system is a bit more complicated so I will not get into the details, but it essentially uses the additional phase information in the waveform to allow incredibly high precision for changes in time. Hence, we can use the ApRES to measure layer motion on the order of mm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary goal of this and following seasons (hopefully two more in 2019-21) are to survey Herc Dome in order to provide guidance for ice-core drilling at this location. We are looking for signs of stability and hopefully a frozen bed. The dream result would be to find a feature called a ‘Raymond Bump’ which forms in the case of a steady divide location for at least a few tens of thousands of years. The bump would indicate a good drilling site because it demonstrates that the ice is not melting at the bed in that location, we would know that the seasonal layers have been well-preserved within the ice, and it implies stability close to the last interglacial which is the time period we are interested in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our day-to-day in the field is mostly spent on a snowmobile or in the radar shelter where we keep the computer while it logs incoming data. All day, we drive around in the flat white expanse. In a way, traversing the ice-sheet surface feels like navigating the sea; there is nothing to be seen except H2O in any direction, and we even use marine GPS. The sastrugi feel like waves and could make one a bit ‘sled sick’ from the sled-rocking motion. We work long days when we are out, but once we get the radar system going it is not exactly strenuous work. The hope is that we sit back and watch the data come in. Of course, when instruments break our lives get a bit more complicated, and this is somewhat inevitable when it is -30°C and we have a bumpy route over sastrugi.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-me-climbing-into-the-radar-shelter-the-twin-otter-that-we-use-for-our-15-hour-commute-from-the-south-pole-is-in-the-background&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Me climbing into the radar shelter. The Twin Otter that we use for our 1.5 hour commute from the South Pole is in the background.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ben_at_hd_hue4873627a0a19c356457209492e55d2d_1040915_203c068a2b3f02e34ddf4262f35e6bdc.webp 400w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ben_at_hd_hue4873627a0a19c356457209492e55d2d_1040915_ab435430a56bfe16bac5525997c6dcd5.webp 760w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ben_at_hd_hue4873627a0a19c356457209492e55d2d_1040915_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ben_at_hd_hue4873627a0a19c356457209492e55d2d_1040915_203c068a2b3f02e34ddf4262f35e6bdc.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;497&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Me climbing into the radar shelter. The Twin Otter that we use for our 1.5 hour commute from the South Pole is in the background.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pole</title>
      <link>https://benhills.github.io/blog/the-pole/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://benhills.github.io/blog/the-pole/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We made it to South Pole Station. It turns out that getting around this continent necessitates a bit of patience. We spent nearly a week in Christchurch, NZ, waiting for the weather to clear so that we could fly to McMurdo (the primary American station). During that week, we had two boomerang flights in which we took off and flew for ~5 hours down over the Southern Ocean only to get turned around back to New Zealand because the pilots did not feel comfortable landing on the McMurdo Ice Shelf. When the weather finally cleared, we landed in McMurdo and I was greeted by the rest of my science team who had been waiting there for three weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McMurdo is an interesting place. In many ways it reminds me of Kangerlussuaq, the center for US science operations in Greenland. The town sits on the McMurdo Sound, across which are the Royal Society Range which tower to 13000&amp;rsquo; from sea level. Being on the coast also means that there is marine wildlife. In the short time that I was there, we saw seals and emperor penguins, but when the icebreaker comes in and breaks the sea ice later in the summer whales, penguins, and seals will surely have a stronger presence. The culture in town in somewhat divided between the contractors and the scientists. They call us &amp;lsquo;beakers&amp;rsquo;, which, although somewhat condescending, is more endearing than the myriad nicknames I was given in high school.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-shuttle-to-our-plane-on-the-mcmurdo-ice-shelf-with-mt-erebus-in-the-background&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Shuttle to our plane on the McMurdo Ice Shelf with Mt. Erebus in the background.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/the-pole/Delta_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_3358740_56b4657c64a4dc423fcd04896ebe8b89.webp 400w,
               /blog/the-pole/Delta_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_3358740_d595c8ecf2c5a823ac3cddc20a14d5d5.webp 760w,
               /blog/the-pole/Delta_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_3358740_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/the-pole/Delta_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_3358740_56b4657c64a4dc423fcd04896ebe8b89.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Shuttle to our plane on the McMurdo Ice Shelf with Mt. Erebus in the background.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, on Saturday the 22nd, we flew to the South Pole which will be our home for the next six weeks or so. Using the station as a home base was not our original plan. We had some logistical problems finding a C-130 landing site at Herc Dome meaning that we will be taking day trips in the smaller Twin Otter. Unfortunately, day trips will not be nearly as productive as staying out at Herc Dome for a full month, but the NSF has generously offered us an additional field season (now we will be coming down the next two years) because the logistical problems were out of our control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flight from McMurdo to Pole is over the Transantarctic Mountains. These mountains mark the boundary between East Antarctica, a stable craton, and West Antarctica, an active rift. We commonly consider the East and West Antarctic Ice Sheets as two seperate systems even though the ice is continuous between them. The East Antarctic Ice Sheet is high and cold; it is considered mostly stable. Ice flows down from East Antarctica through the mountains and into the West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS) which is lower and relatively warm. The bed of WAIS is below sea level which is the root of its susceptibility for collapse, something that has been very apparent for at least 40 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty of the Transantarctic Mountains made it clear to me why ice-sheet landscapes are uniquely attractive. Natural beauty seems to fall into two classifications. The first is the most obvious, being dramatic landscapes such as the Alps or Patagonia. In those settings, sharp contrasts and strong lines highlight features that are striking to our eye. The second is more subtle. The rolling hills of Vermont or even the wide open plains of the Midwest are beautiful because diffusive processes smooth the landscape. These places inspire a feeling of quiet and comfort. Ice-sheet landscapes are unmatched in that they seamlessly coalesce both aspects of natural beauty. Ice flows and diffusively spreads into a smooth surface. Ice far from the mountains is completely flat and white. Only after adjusting one’s perception can the subtle surface slopes be noticed. On the other hand, in mountainous areas nunataks jut straight through the ice, with glacial erosion encouraging steep and dramatic profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-flying-over-the-transantarctic-mountains&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Flying over the Transantarctic Mountains.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/the-pole/transantarctics_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_2874254_9c67154b36ff9b5806a16ec8010cdac6.webp 400w,
               /blog/the-pole/transantarctics_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_2874254_b9ec316632265894b32182f1ce864afd.webp 760w,
               /blog/the-pole/transantarctics_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_2874254_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/the-pole/transantarctics_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_2874254_9c67154b36ff9b5806a16ec8010cdac6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Flying over the Transantarctic Mountains.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antarctica is stunning, but we are ultimately here for the science. The diversity of interesting science is what makes South Pole Station an exciting place. In the ‘dark sector’ there is the IceCube Neutrino Observatory, which is a 1 km3 network of Cherenkov detectors buried in the ice, and the South Pole Telescope, which measures cosmic microwaves with the objective of gaining insight about the origins of our universe. SuperDARN is a radio antenna, and a part of a worldwide network used to study the aurora. In the ‘clean-air sector’ there are automated weather stations, and UV measurements to study the ozone hole. There are also field projects based out of the station including our own, but also another University of Washington project on ice and firn dynamics upstream of the South Pole Ice Core (SPICE core).&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-maintenance-work-on-the-south-pole-telescope&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Maintenance work on the South Pole Telescope.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/the-pole/SPT_hu0a4ff54ba61226b25c17514fab2365d0_348343_dcb2375f70b7c15199dd92cc5d3b0c91.webp 400w,
               /blog/the-pole/SPT_hu0a4ff54ba61226b25c17514fab2365d0_348343_e6dbc22fb3297710d65ec4ee09685cb3.webp 760w,
               /blog/the-pole/SPT_hu0a4ff54ba61226b25c17514fab2365d0_348343_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/the-pole/SPT_hu0a4ff54ba61226b25c17514fab2365d0_348343_dcb2375f70b7c15199dd92cc5d3b0c91.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;506&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Maintenance work on the South Pole Telescope.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The station feels as if it were designed by a science fiction writer. Perhaps science fiction ideas have been based on facilities such as this one. Eric Steig, one of our team members, made a comment that this is the closest any of us will ever get to space. At first I thought it was a funny comment; however, after getting here I do feel like that, being in a remote and isolated environment in which all the personnel are either directly or indirectly doing work to support scientific objectives. Even maintaining the facility is a tremendous effort. Several tractors are moving snow out from under the station all summer to keep it from being buried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few quirky aspects of living on station. First, and most obvious, we have 24 hours of daylight. I found this quite entertaining at first, but am getting frustrated to wake up with the feeling that I am late only to realize that it is still 2am. Thorough hand washing on station is a must because viruses circulate quickly. Even with these difficulties, the community here does a lot to keep each other sane. For the first few days after we got here, we were encouraged to relax so that our bodies could properly acclimatize. Since then, we have been working to prepare our science experiments, but have had some down time to explore the station which includes a gym, a green house, a quiet reading room, and the South Pole Store. We even had a nice dinner and there was a foot race ‘around the world’ on Christmas day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going South</title>
      <link>https://benhills.github.io/blog/going-south/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://benhills.github.io/blog/going-south/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am in the process of deploying to Hercules Dome, Antarctica (‘Herc Dome’, named after the airplane above) and will be in the field for at least a month, likely longer. This research trip came as a surprise to me because, in an emergency, an extra field personnel was needed. Two weeks ago, I was putting together a poster for the American Geophysical Union Fall Meeting in Washington D.C. and making Christmas plans with my girlfriend’s family. In the time since I was informed that I would be needed in Antarctica on Tuesday, November 27, I had to renew my passport, pass a rigorous physical examination (including full blood work, a tuberculosis test, a dental examination, etc.), purchase and pack gear for my first trip to the southern continent, write and print my science poster for a friend to hang up at the conference I would be missing, and finish my schoolwork for the quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mental preparation thrust me into a vortex of emotions. Obviously, I am both excited and nervous about the trip itself, but I also sporadically feel sad, isolated, exhausted, proud, hopeful, and even nostalgic as we pass through Christchurch, New Zealand, where I lived as a 20-year-old student. In the days and weeks to come I will have more trainings and preparations to do at both the McMurdo and South Pole stations. Although being dragged through this emotional landscape is somewhat inevitable, I am hoping for a mental shift toward sharpening my focus on our scientific objectives. After all, that is my reason for being here.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-map-of-ice-core-drilling-sites-in-antarctica-with-herc-dome-shown-in-red-borrowed-from-tj-fudgehttpsantarcticfudgesicleswordpresscom20181117hercules-dome-antarctica&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A map of ice core drilling sites in Antarctica with Herc Dome shown in red (borrowed from [T.J. Fudge](https://antarcticfudgesicles.wordpress.com/2018/11/17/hercules-dome-antarctica/)).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/going-south/hd-map_hue72b89f81990392c5429058996f26f48_43647_71f23b853006c34e2591dfde485d40f1.webp 400w,
               /blog/going-south/hd-map_hue72b89f81990392c5429058996f26f48_43647_a4546e1554ad45056d28353bcf19bed3.webp 760w,
               /blog/going-south/hd-map_hue72b89f81990392c5429058996f26f48_43647_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/going-south/hd-map_hue72b89f81990392c5429058996f26f48_43647_71f23b853006c34e2591dfde485d40f1.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;484&#34;
               height=&#34;417&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A map of ice core drilling sites in Antarctica with Herc Dome shown in red (borrowed from &lt;a href=&#34;https://antarcticfudgesicles.wordpress.com/2018/11/17/hercules-dome-antarctica/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;T.J. Fudge&lt;/a&gt;).
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our project at Herc Dome is tangent to my primary dissertation topic. I first learned about it when I started my PhD approximately 18 months ago because T.J. Fudge gave a talk at the 2017 West Antarctic Ice Sheet Workshop. T.J. and Eric Steig, another faculty in our department at the University of Washington, are interested in Herc Dome as the next drilling site for the US Ice Drilling Program. At the time of T.J.’s talk, this project had no secured funding line, but their ideas were maturing. I have since learned that ice core locations are intensely debated and that Herc Dome has been a highly endorsed candidate for over a decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice cores are useful for learning about past climate. Many have been drilled throughout both the Greenland and Antarctic ice sheets, but each serves a separate purpose. The first few cores to be drilled, like those at Dome C and Lake Vostock, gave us a baseline for atmospheric isotopes up to 800 thousand years ago. Consistent oscillations in those data confirm the existence of past climate cycles and are strongly linked to oscillations in the Earth&amp;rsquo;s orbit called Milankovitch cycles. Some of the more recent ice cores, like the West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS) Divide ice core, were drilled with the intention of obtaining high resolution information about the atmosphere in the most recent glacial/interglacial cycle (since the Eemian warm period ~120 thousand years ago). Learning how the ice sheets changed, and particularly the extent of  collapse, during the Eemian would give us valuable information about what the future’s warming climate will have in store for polar ice. Unfortunately, no Eemian ice was found at WAIS Divide because that location is melting at its bed, something that wasn&amp;rsquo;t known for certain before drilling started. While the WAIS Divide core was a valuable contribution in that it produced the highest resolution isotope data to date, the record only extends to 68 thousand years ago and therefore provides no information about possible collapse of West Antarctica during the Eemian.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-paleoclimate-data-from-three-ice-cores-and-an-oceanic-record-used-as-a-proxy-for-sea-level-change-taken-from-a-climate-review-paperhttpswwwclim-pastnet925252013&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Paleoclimate data from three ice cores and an oceanic record used as a proxy for sea-level change (taken from a [climate review paper](https://www.clim-past.net/9/2525/2013/))&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/going-south/IceCoreData_hu0803a4af1784c1df74d0ceb908763193_79889_9b44b828102dfe0850a6ae58535edf58.webp 400w,
               /blog/going-south/IceCoreData_hu0803a4af1784c1df74d0ceb908763193_79889_93ee3c3f2fab8bcbd1cf4e8dca55f99f.webp 760w,
               /blog/going-south/IceCoreData_hu0803a4af1784c1df74d0ceb908763193_79889_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/going-south/IceCoreData_hu0803a4af1784c1df74d0ceb908763193_79889_9b44b828102dfe0850a6ae58535edf58.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;640&#34;
               height=&#34;450&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Paleoclimate data from three ice cores and an oceanic record used as a proxy for sea-level change (taken from a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.clim-past.net/9/2525/2013/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;climate review paper&lt;/a&gt;)
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our ultimate objective for Herc Dome is to drill a new ice core which will hopefully extend through the Eemian and more rigorously address the nature of the West Antarctic Ice Sheet at that time. This site is at a critical location on an ice divide but between East and West Antarctica, which means that it will likely hold valuable information about flow between the two ice sheets especially in times of WAIS collapse. In preparation, this upcoming season is a pre-drilling geophysics campaign led by my advisor, Knut Christianson. We will use ice-penetrating radar to learn about the bed topography (among other things) and use that information to choose the exact location for the core, whether that be at the top of the dome or not. But how do we know what a ‘good’ ice-core location looks like from the radar data? We are looking for a place where the bottom of the ice sheet is cold (i.e. that it is not melting) because we want the old ice to be preserved. We also want a location where the internal reflectors are consistently flat so that we know the ice flow is relatively simple and has been consistent through time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only a handful of people have ever been to Herc Dome. As far as I know, none of the original explorers came through this way. Scott, Shackleton, and Amundsen all came from the Ross Sea sector but moved through the Transantarctic Mountains further north and ended up significantly east of Herc Dome. One previous science mission did come over the dome as a part of the ITASE traverse from Byrd Station to the South Pole. It was during this traverse that the scientific importance of Herc Dome was established. Bob Jacobel and his team (including Eric Steig) recognized what they thought might be a &amp;lsquo;Raymond Arch&amp;rsquo; within their radar data which would indicate that it is a good location for drilling. However, having only a few isolated transects, their evidence is not strong enough to say for certain what this feature is. That is a big part of the reason why we need to go back.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-getting-my-gear-ready-at-the-clothing-distribution-center-in-christchurch-new-zealand&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Getting my gear ready at the clothing distribution center in Christchurch, New Zealand.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/going-south/clothes_hu8ece794870e2fd8521c3b43a5cefa654_498152_1b186ac16a8b48d494d904b147185bde.webp 400w,
               /blog/going-south/clothes_hu8ece794870e2fd8521c3b43a5cefa654_498152_f3fe9be054356959a3f8db76b709758e.webp 760w,
               /blog/going-south/clothes_hu8ece794870e2fd8521c3b43a5cefa654_498152_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/going-south/clothes_hu8ece794870e2fd8521c3b43a5cefa654_498152_1b186ac16a8b48d494d904b147185bde.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;697&#34;
               height=&#34;695&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Getting my gear ready at the clothing distribution center in Christchurch, New Zealand.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said goodbye to friends and family, they unsurprisingly asked questions about what I have in store. Since this is my first trip South, I don’t feel entirely equipped to answer (hence my looming anxiety). Having said that, I have had extensive conversations with my advisor, helping him buy tools and equipment in preparation for the season, as well as many from the glaciology community at the University of Washington. Herc Dome is at 86.5°S, and 2610 m (8563 ft) elevation. This means that we will have sunlight at all times and that the air temperature is… well it is cold. The mean air temperature is -40°C, but these are the summer months so it will normally be a bit warmer. Antarctica is a huge desert, but the precipitation at Herc Dome is relatively high at 10 cm/yr ice equivalent (~1 m of snow). Even if it is not snowing often, wind and blowing snow will be common. Luckily, the awesome team at the US Antarctic Program issue us sufficient gear to stay cozy in the cold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will surely be busy doing science (or just as likely getting frustrated waiting for flights and trying to fix things that are broken) over the next couple months, but I will try to write a few of my thoughts down when I get the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greenland Ice Sheet Ablation Zone</title>
      <link>https://benhills.github.io/blog/ablation-zone/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://benhills.github.io/blog/ablation-zone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From 2015 to 2017 I was a graduate student at the University of Montana. While there, my research focused on heat transfer in Greenland&amp;rsquo;s ablation zone. I was fortunate in getting to experience this place, which up to now has been the most awe inspiring and the most intellectually fascinating place I have ever been. Spending approximately a month of time on the ice (over two separate summers) I learned how to work in such an environment, and specifically how to extract information from one of the most influential natural systems on our planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ice-sheet-basics&#34;&gt;Ice Sheet Basics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice forms on the Earth&amp;rsquo;s surface in places where more snow falls in the winter than melts in the summer. Typically, this means at either high elevation or high latitude, both of which are landscapes generally void of dense human populations. While it is easy for most of us to think of these as abstract places having no impact on our daily lives, as early as the 1960s scientists were warning of the potential for global influence by the Earth&amp;rsquo;s ice sheets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we appreciate the scale for the importance of the Earth&amp;rsquo;s cryosphere, we are investing more time and energy into researching these environments. We are learning that the large ice systems are a sort of barometer for the climate system. When the climate is stable, the ice sheets will conserve mass, with equal flux in at the top to flux out at the bottom. The flux in comes from precipitation at high elevation and compaction of snow into ice. Eventually, that ice flows downhill and either the warm air temperatures melt the ice or it meets the ocean and &amp;lsquo;calves&amp;rsquo;, floating away as an iceberg (both melting and calving are outward fluxes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This dichotomy of inward and outward fluxes is described in terms of accumulation of mass and ablation (melting). The conceptual model of an ice sheet (below) has an accumulation zone where more ice is formed from precipitation than is melted, and the ablation zone where more ice is lost to melting than is formed. Assessing this mass balance of an ice sheet has become a staple in the science of glaciology and provides a lot of information, not only about the health of an individual glacier or ice sheet, but about the global climate system.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-in-the-accumulation-zone-more-ice-accumulates-from-snowfall-than-melts-alternatively-in-the-ablation-zone-the-entire-winter-snowpack-as-well-as-some-amount-of-ice-all-melts-during-the-summer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;In the accumulation zone, more ice accumulates from snowfall than melts. Alternatively, in the ablation zone, the entire winter snowpack as well as some amount of ice all melts during the summer.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ablation-zone/accabl_hua021b37d7b32ea2a52939f9d359e088c_26655654_38277dd4e9fae0d15b54a8b4d033e791.webp 400w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/accabl_hua021b37d7b32ea2a52939f9d359e088c_26655654_a6a06fe01ee718d50ea14dc27d65dff7.webp 760w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/accabl_hua021b37d7b32ea2a52939f9d359e088c_26655654_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/ablation-zone/accabl_hua021b37d7b32ea2a52939f9d359e088c_26655654_38277dd4e9fae0d15b54a8b4d033e791.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;253&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      In the accumulation zone, more ice accumulates from snowfall than melts. Alternatively, in the ablation zone, the entire winter snowpack as well as some amount of ice all melts during the summer.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two ice sheets on this planet, Greenland and Antarctica, are unique in several ways. Importantly, these ice sheets are at different latitudes, the Antarctic being considerably further from the equator, and as a consequence much colder and larger. The Antarctic Ice Sheet contains approximately 30 million cubic meters (60 m sea level equivalent), while the Greenland Ice Sheet is only about one tenth of that. Because the Antarctic Ice Sheet is in a colder environment, it does not lose mass to melting, only to calving, and it therefore has no ablation zone. Greenland, on the other hand, has a rather large ablation zone, meaning that a significant portion of its mass loss can be attributed to surface melting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-project-in-the-ablation-zone&#34;&gt;Our Project in the Ablation Zone&lt;/h2&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-location-of-our-field-area-in-southwest-greenland&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The location of our field area in southwest Greenland.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ablation-zone/isunninset_hu7494ad9600d4a9895c52f1b8717378bc_752443_afa3cb44f4c4f908cbb825e90c092a06.webp 400w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/isunninset_hu7494ad9600d4a9895c52f1b8717378bc_752443_5c1008b66f404d21b9edf919b4b5bdd5.webp 760w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/isunninset_hu7494ad9600d4a9895c52f1b8717378bc_752443_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/ablation-zone/isunninset_hu7494ad9600d4a9895c52f1b8717378bc_752443_afa3cb44f4c4f908cbb825e90c092a06.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;537&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The location of our field area in southwest Greenland.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland&amp;rsquo;s ablation zone is important because the ice sheet is rapidly losing ice from increased melting. Unfortunately, this area has not been intensely studied because only Greenland, and not Antarctica, has an ablation zone. Hence, we have a somewhat novice understanding of what makes the ablation zone unique, that being primarily the presence of liquid water. When ice melts at the surface, the meltwater flows downhill and forms a branching network of streams. Those streams eventually terminate in either a supraglacial lake, resting on the ice surface, or a moulin, which is a large shaft that brings water from the surface to the base of the ice sheet. Recent work in the ablation zone has shown that this meltwater influences the way in which ice flows, both through warming the ice and through lubricating the bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The science project that brought me to Greenland was focused on these alterations to flow in the ablation zone. Our primary objective was to drill hot-water boreholes into the ice sheet, in order to measure internal properties of the ice including temperature, shear strain, water pressure at the bed, etc. Using this data, we would partition the flow of the ice sheet into its two main constituents, viscous deformation and pure shear (sliding over the bedrock substrate). I should note that this project was already fully developed by the time I joined and never would happened without the hard work of many individuals at both the University of Montana and the University of Wyoming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-primer-on-hot-water-drilling&#34;&gt;A Primer on Hot-Water Drilling&lt;/h2&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-our-research-team-getting-the-hot-water-drill-started-on-the-morning-of-a-drilling-day&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Our research team getting the hot-water drill started on the morning of a drilling day.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ablation-zone/hot-water_hud56757ca3a027ba70972e9f698a2c263_207670_c997d1f069c56f21f27885347a87d914.webp 400w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/hot-water_hud56757ca3a027ba70972e9f698a2c263_207670_c0f26f802120b22e054689e4d069d56a.webp 760w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/hot-water_hud56757ca3a027ba70972e9f698a2c263_207670_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/ablation-zone/hot-water_hud56757ca3a027ba70972e9f698a2c263_207670_c997d1f069c56f21f27885347a87d914.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;712&#34;
               height=&#34;474&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Our research team getting the hot-water drill started on the morning of a drilling day.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two main approaches to drilling in ice. Typically, when I tell people that my research involves drilling boreholes in Greenland, they assume that I am drilling &amp;lsquo;mechanical&amp;rsquo; holes in order to extract ice cores. In fact, our methodology is quite the opposite. A hot-water drill melts a hole in the ice, leaving space so that we can put things into the ice sheet. One can think of a hot-water drill as a hose, which sprays very hot (~80ºC) and highly pressurized (~1100 psi) water. With this hose, we can drill through the thickness of the ice sheet, ~500-1000 m, in less than a day. In total, we drilled something like 35 holes to the bed of the ice sheet in the ablation zone, instrumenting each one with electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-open-borehole-with-cables-for-our-electronics-descending-into-the-ice-sheet&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The open borehole with cables for our electronics descending into the ice sheet.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ablation-zone/hole_hu5ca122fbc12e048477b3e4e646571db0_126123_785a87c751b34a323d9b826a7587b75a.webp 400w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/hole_hu5ca122fbc12e048477b3e4e646571db0_126123_f161110c9794a3eb44143a32d56b43e3.webp 760w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/hole_hu5ca122fbc12e048477b3e4e646571db0_126123_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://benhills.github.io/blog/ablation-zone/hole_hu5ca122fbc12e048477b3e4e646571db0_126123_785a87c751b34a323d9b826a7587b75a.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;708&#34;
               height=&#34;471&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The open borehole with cables for our electronics descending into the ice sheet.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data&#34;&gt;Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The focus of our measurements is to understand the physical behavior of ice in this area. We want to know how the ice is moving and what is forcing it to move in the way that it does. Ice motion is subdivided into two categories, and we have measurements that pertain to each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, ice moves through internal deformation, which is facilitated by both inter-crystal and intra-crystal creep. In order to understand this deformation in a bulk sense, we measure the deformation of the ice at different points along a profile from the surface of the ice sheet to the bed. We also measure ice temperature along this profile, which controls how quickly the ice deforms. Secondly, ice moves by sliding over its bed. This is only true in areas where the bed is at the melting point and partially melted, and one such area happens to be Greenland&amp;rsquo;s ablation zone. To constrain this sliding motion, we measure properties at the bed including water pressure and the composition of the subglacial till. Finally, we directly measure the ice velocity using GPS stations installed into the ice at the surface. With these velocity measurements, we place all of our other data into context by correlating speedups to variations in the internal and basal state of the ice sheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-science&#34;&gt;The Science&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our measurements, along with those of others working in the area, have resulted in the development of ice mechanics theory in the ablation zone. We now know that ice motion is primarily by sliding over what we think is a solid bed. We know that the thermal structure of the ice sheet is much more complicated than we originally thought, which could lead to complexities in ice flow. We know that the basal drainage system consists of large conduits near the ice sheet margin, but these likely do not propagate far inward toward regions of thicker ice. Looking to the future, it will be important to continue to research how the ablation zone will change, whether it will grow and promote the melting of more ice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
