<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Benjamin Hills</title>
    <link>https://example.com/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://example.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Benjamin Hills</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://example.com/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Benjamin Hills</title>
      <link>https://example.com/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Radar Polarimetry in Glaciology: Theory, Measurement Techniques, and Scientific Applications for Investigating the Anisotropy of Ice Masses Greenland and Canadian Arctic ice temperature profiles database</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/hills2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/hills2025/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Radar-derived crystal orientation fabric suggests dynamic stability at the summit of Hercules Dome during the last ice-sheet deglaciation</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/hills2024a/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/hills2024a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Entrained Water in Basal Ice Suppresses Radar Bed‐Echo Power at Active Subglacial Lakes</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/hills2024b/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/hills2024b/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effective diffusivity of sulfuric acid in Antarctic ice cores</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/fudge2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/fudge2023/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scars of tectonic extension promote ice-sheet nucleation from Hercules Dome, West Antarctica</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/hoffman2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/hoffman2023/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greenland and Canadian Arctic ice temperature profiles database</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/lokkegaard2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/lokkegaard2023/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antarctic Bedmap data: Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable (FAIR) sharing of 60 years of ice bed, surface, and thickness data</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/fremand2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/fremand2023/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What can the ice-bed interface tell us? Insights into old ice, meltwater, bedrock geology, and ice-sheet history</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/walcott2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/walcott2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Radar attenuation demonstrates advective cooling in the Siple Coast ice streams</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/hills2022b/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/hills2022b/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combatant Col</title>
      <link>https://example.com/blog/waddington/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/blog/waddington/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We typically think of ice cores in the context of global climate.
For instance, Antarctic ice cores demonstrate the link between greenhouse gases and temperature, both through glacial cycles (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature02599&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dome C&lt;/a&gt;) and into the human era (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1029/95JD03410&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Law Dome&lt;/a&gt;).
What many don’t know is that some of the most powerful ice-core interpretation has been for regional climate rather than global. Take &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/362527a0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Richard Alley’s interpretation&lt;/a&gt; of the Younger Dryas from a Greenland ice core, GISP2.
Noticing substantial precipitation changes in Greenland over very short timescales (~decades), he argued for changes in both atmospheric and ocean circulation in the North Atlantic as the Earth was coming out of the last glacial period.
Ultimately, these changes led to a global climate event in the Younger Dryas, but the critical measurement for this inference was local to the North Atlantic around Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, we are focused on climate in the North Pacific and how that can be sampled using alpine ice cores from Southeast Alaska and, in this case specifically, coastal British Columbia.
The North Pacific is dominated by two pressure systems, the Aleutian Low and the North Pacific High.
Seattle-ites will be very familiar with the effects of these pressure systems.
During winter, cold temperatures move the high pressure system to lower latitude and allow the Aleutian Low to grow which brings wet weather to Seattle and the broader Pacific Northwest.
Alpine ice cores preserve the dynamics of this system and how it may have changed over the last ~few hundred years.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-atmospheric-circulation-in-the-north-pacific&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Atmospheric circulation in the North Pacific.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/waddington/aleutian_low_hu8dc042ba89a8cea4a010c46d7b18f6b8_3544519_49765eef5c27a0911645bdc707f9eacc.webp 400w,
               /blog/waddington/aleutian_low_hu8dc042ba89a8cea4a010c46d7b18f6b8_3544519_8930348f6ff4488ce1c722a0dc31b84f.webp 760w,
               /blog/waddington/aleutian_low_hu8dc042ba89a8cea4a010c46d7b18f6b8_3544519_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/waddington/aleutian_low_hu8dc042ba89a8cea4a010c46d7b18f6b8_3544519_49765eef5c27a0911645bdc707f9eacc.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;443&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Atmospheric circulation in the North Pacific.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mt. Waddington is the highest mountain in British Columbia.
As may be expected for such a prominent piece of earth, it obstructs the wet air masses coming in from the Pacific and can get hammered with snow in the winter months.
Our estimates were for ~12 meters of snow to the previous summer&amp;rsquo;s surface or ~7.5 meters water equivalent! Compare this to Seattle where it rains about 1 meter per year.
Combatant Col, where we are looking to drill an ice core, rests between Waddington and its neighbor to the north, Mt. Combatant.
Enough ice accumulates in this mountain saddle to make it a flat and relatively safe space to camp away from the avalanches and mountain debris coming off both peaks.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-mt-waddington-summit-and-combatant-col-indicated-by-the-arrow-photo-from-summitpostorghttpswwwsummitpostorgmount-waddington153091&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Mt. Waddington summit and Combatant Col indicated by the arrow. Photo from [summitpost.org](https://www.summitpost.org/mount-waddington/153091).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/waddington/waddington_summit_hu69822adf3778783218d5352367cfe673_5919218_cc635e196097489ab7d7fda081699571.webp 400w,
               /blog/waddington/waddington_summit_hu69822adf3778783218d5352367cfe673_5919218_95b6c2268b9cbd751eb6450fb64c4e29.webp 760w,
               /blog/waddington/waddington_summit_hu69822adf3778783218d5352367cfe673_5919218_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/waddington/waddington_summit_hu69822adf3778783218d5352367cfe673_5919218_cc635e196097489ab7d7fda081699571.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Mt. Waddington summit and Combatant Col indicated by the arrow. Photo from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.summitpost.org/mount-waddington/153091&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;summitpost.org&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My colleagues at the University of Washington, Peter Neff (now at University of Minnesota) and Eric Steig, started work at Mt. Waddington for Peter’s M.S. degree (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/journal-of-glaciology/article/icecore-net-snow-accumulation-and-seasonal-snow-chemistry-at-a-temperateglacier-site-mount-waddington-southwest-british-columbia-canada/BFE67E26A16331B73DE8986FE05CBBE2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Neff et al., 2012&lt;/a&gt;).
They were successful in drilling a 141-meter core but were obstructed from drilling any deeper by substantial water within the firn, what has now come to be known as a ‘perennial firn aquifer’ based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/ngeo2043&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;similar features in Greenland&lt;/a&gt;.
Despite not extending as far in time as they had hoped, the results from their ice core are novel and interesting.
Layer thicknesses (for precipitation) and water isotopes (for temperature) are used for local and regional climate interpretation.
They sample black carbon within the core which comes from summertime smoke associated with regional wildfires. One of the interesting aspects of a future ice core will be extending this wildfire record well into the pre-industrial.
They found a drop in lead concentrations in the 1980’s which, while not as interesting from an atmospheric process understanding perspective, demonstrates how effective policymakers can be in altering the atmosphere.
Leaded gasoline was forcibly phased out starting with the Clean Air Act in 1970 but followed by a series of regulations and an outright ban in 1996.
The firn core at Combatant Col recorded the response beautifully.
These are the types of examples that give me hope in an era of rampant climate despair. Another example would be the CFC regulations in the Montreal Protocol now acting to &lt;a href=&#34;https://csl.noaa.gov/assessments/ozone/2018/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;heal the ozone hole&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-data-from-the-first-ice-core-drilled-in-2010-neff-et-al-2012&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Data from the first ice core drilled in 2010 (Neff et al., 2012).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/waddington/core_data_hu9788511722b77b6da4f0c0bd36ca8dc3_2389218_1bda6488e8f317f7a2610163dcc34bb2.webp 400w,
               /blog/waddington/core_data_hu9788511722b77b6da4f0c0bd36ca8dc3_2389218_4876ba64fd86f43567dbda2ba85f1c1d.webp 760w,
               /blog/waddington/core_data_hu9788511722b77b6da4f0c0bd36ca8dc3_2389218_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/waddington/core_data_hu9788511722b77b6da4f0c0bd36ca8dc3_2389218_1bda6488e8f317f7a2610163dcc34bb2.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;488&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Data from the first ice core drilled in 2010 (Neff et al., 2012).
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our objective in this field season was to more carefully survey the col with geophysical tools in preparation for another (hopefully deeper) ice core to be drilled in summer 2023.
We used two distinct radar systems for two separate purposes.
First, we used a 10-MHz radar to survey the ice thickness, with the idea being that this relatively low frequency wave should be able to propagate through some water in the firn aquifer to create a reflection off the ice-bed interface.
Second, we used a 100-MHz radar to survey the firn aquifer itself. We get a strong reflection off the water table, so it is quite easy to know where there is standing water and its relative depth below the snow surface.
We do not get a good reflection from the bottom of the firn aquifer, so it is harder to know the total volume of water present or how deep the water can infiltrate before all available pore space is closed off as the firn transitions into solid ice.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-pulling-the-deep-sounding-radar-system-on-skis-with-the-second-summit-of-mt-waddington-in-the-background-the-orange-sled-in-the-foreground-holds-the-radar-transmitter-and-a-precision-gps-up-on-the-pole-the-maroon-sled-closer-to-the-skier-holds-the-radar-receiver-and-the-hoses-on-either-side-of-the-sleds-are-the-radar-antennas&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Pulling the deep-sounding radar system on skis with the second summit of Mt. Waddington in the background. The orange sled in the foreground holds the radar transmitter and a precision GPS up on the pole. The maroon sled, closer to the skier, holds the radar receiver, and the hoses on either side of the sleds are the radar antennas.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/waddington/dragging_radar_hud8c5d75f0c55580faccd25ca871cf326_3250552_2c52f3d59242fb9818b8741805c00350.webp 400w,
               /blog/waddington/dragging_radar_hud8c5d75f0c55580faccd25ca871cf326_3250552_5abb8cb575765cedcd3bc6b05b83d1b7.webp 760w,
               /blog/waddington/dragging_radar_hud8c5d75f0c55580faccd25ca871cf326_3250552_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/waddington/dragging_radar_hud8c5d75f0c55580faccd25ca871cf326_3250552_2c52f3d59242fb9818b8741805c00350.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;570&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Pulling the deep-sounding radar system on skis with the second summit of Mt. Waddington in the background. The orange sled in the foreground holds the radar transmitter and a precision GPS up on the pole. The maroon sled, closer to the skier, holds the radar receiver, and the hoses on either side of the sleds are the radar antennas.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-preliminary-results-from-both-shallow-radar-top-and-deep-radar-bottom-the-x-axis-is-the-distance-we-traversed-along-the-surface-and-the-y-axis-is-the-time-between-radar-transmit-and-receive-in-microseconds-and-converted-to-the-corresponding-depth-approximate&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Preliminary results from both shallow radar (top) and deep radar (bottom). The x-axis is the distance we traversed along the surface, and the y-axis is the time between radar transmit and receive (in microseconds) and converted to the corresponding depth (approximate).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/waddington/blog_radar_hueb7496d28b9c0aaf0be5c991dad47c3b_2242778_7ac972fe519ef413093328283df9438a.webp 400w,
               /blog/waddington/blog_radar_hueb7496d28b9c0aaf0be5c991dad47c3b_2242778_65a9abd4a034cd0b8d701be651ea34f6.webp 760w,
               /blog/waddington/blog_radar_hueb7496d28b9c0aaf0be5c991dad47c3b_2242778_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/waddington/blog_radar_hueb7496d28b9c0aaf0be5c991dad47c3b_2242778_7ac972fe519ef413093328283df9438a.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;732&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Preliminary results from both shallow radar (top) and deep radar (bottom). The x-axis is the distance we traversed along the surface, and the y-axis is the time between radar transmit and receive (in microseconds) and converted to the corresponding depth (approximate).
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our deep radar results look quite different from the stereotypical ice-penetrating radar profile which often has beautifully conformal stratigraphy and a glaringly bright bed reflection (see some examples &lt;a href=&#34;https://example.com/photo/radar/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).
Instead, we see a bit of a garbled mess, with scattering pretty much everywhere.
In the field I found this quite frustrating, especially that we were not getting an obvious bed reflection.
I spent about a day trying to adjust the radar settings to optimize for these wet conditions.
With no significant improvement and a constrained timeline, I eventually decided we would go ahead and do the survey, that the radar instrument itself was working as well as it could be, and hoping that we could pull out a bit more information with careful post-processing.
In the end, this has turned out to be the case. The data are high quality, there is simply so much water in this temperate ice that we see reflections off of &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; through the entire ice column.
We think that the bottom of these messy reflections delineates the boundary between ice and rock (roughly drawn in red on the figure).
The shallow data are as expected, with a clear reflection at the water table in the firn, but also with a not-so-pleasant surprise of some buried crevasses at the edges of our surveyed area.
Fortunately, they are deep and we were also quite careful roping up away from our camp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any field trip, this week in BC came with a few fun mishaps.
We left Seattle early on a Wednesday morning, hoping to make the ~12 hour drive all the way to White Saddle in one day.
Even before crossing into Canada we found ourselves on the side of the road with a car full of glass from Peter&amp;rsquo;s driver&amp;rsquo;s side window.
An oncoming truck had kicked up a rock which shattered their window. Luckily, Peter stayed calm or it could have turned into a bigger accident.
Having trouble scheduling an auto glass shop, Peter and his student Julia stayed at his mom&amp;rsquo;s house for the night (a situation Peter described as &amp;lsquo;his nightmare&amp;rsquo;, bringing his student to his mom&amp;rsquo;s house) while I continued onward.
Even more eventful was our last night up on the col.
I am a heavy sleeper, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t wake up until I heard my tent vestibule vigorously flapping in the wind.
I poked my head out to check that it was still there and was greeted with some hefty gusts.
A few minutes later I hear clashes and clangs from our kitchen tent followed by a series of profanities from Peter&amp;rsquo;s tent.
Peter was up in an instant trying to chase it, but there was no chance, our tent was long gone.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-broken-window-an-hour-into-our-trip&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Broken window an hour into our trip...&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/waddington/broken_window_hu6263fe60296d2f6637cb2d46fd5f6aa4_4760825_aacabac321aa2f6dc299480cbe5a8712.webp 400w,
               /blog/waddington/broken_window_hu6263fe60296d2f6637cb2d46fd5f6aa4_4760825_ced160cbb4f282012a4802f52ed0a4c7.webp 760w,
               /blog/waddington/broken_window_hu6263fe60296d2f6637cb2d46fd5f6aa4_4760825_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/waddington/broken_window_hu6263fe60296d2f6637cb2d46fd5f6aa4_4760825_aacabac321aa2f6dc299480cbe5a8712.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;573&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Broken window an hour into our trip&amp;hellip;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A site for deep ice coring at West Hercules Dome: results from ground-based geophysics and modeling</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/fudge2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/fudge2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jupyter Boot Camp</title>
      <link>https://example.com/teaching/coding-boot-camp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/teaching/coding-boot-camp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geophysics and thermodynamics at South Pole Lake indicate stability and a regionally thawed bed</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/hills2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/hills2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alpine Glaciers</title>
      <link>https://example.com/photo/alpine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/photo/alpine/</guid>
      <description>










&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/baker.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/baker_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_430612_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;baker.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/dragging_radar.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/dragging_radar_hud8c5d75f0c55580faccd25ca871cf326_3250552_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;dragging_radar.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;143&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/DSC_0032.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/DSC_0032_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_930204_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0032.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/DSC_0243.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/DSC_0243_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_431588_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0243.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/DSC_0337.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/DSC_0337_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_422634_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0337.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/DSC_0339.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/DSC_0339_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_567757_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0339.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/DSC_0474.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/DSC_0474_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_480378_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0474.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/Ice%20Cave4.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/Ice%20Cave4_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_375833_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Ice Cave4.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/icefall.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/icefall_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_522987_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;icefall.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/kaskawulsch.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/kaskawulsch_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_688142_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;kaskawulsch.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/mendenhall.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/mendenhall_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_592890_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;mendenhall.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/ogives-2.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/ogives-2_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_788553_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;ogives-2.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/ogives.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/ogives_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_476285_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;ogives.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/PXL_20220722_213743594.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/PXL_20220722_213743594_hu486fe30a257be559e7b46ffb96bff38f_4876110_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;PXL_20220722_213743594.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;143&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/PXL_20220724_034751945.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/PXL_20220724_034751945_hu367b37d2fb232d694ba526a301984f82_3958247_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;PXL_20220724_034751945.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;252&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/PXL_20220724_204905969.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/PXL_20220724_204905969_hue15965abbe985161c4d4551363ed94bb_2588177_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;PXL_20220724_204905969.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;252&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/PXL_20220724_223333997.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/PXL_20220724_223333997_huc2ab666fd16ff2dc17876d4ec2b7f8bd_3350551_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;PXL_20220724_223333997.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;252&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-alpine&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/PXL_20220725_145551185_2.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/alpine/PXL_20220725_145551185_2_huc7a4cb3d836e1460d26daf43ea5af1e8_2080845_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;PXL_20220725_145551185_2.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;277&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antarctica</title>
      <link>https://example.com/photo/antarctica/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/photo/antarctica/</guid>
      <description>










&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/beardmore.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/beardmore_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_320147_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;beardmore.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/delta.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/delta_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_407054_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;delta.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/dorm.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/dorm_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_444127_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;dorm.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0023.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0023_hu855bbe0a9c47ac557e5b09db74fa3b06_959978_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0023.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0031.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0031_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_1397558_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0031.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0050.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0050_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_766531_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0050.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0066.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0066_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_526101_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0066.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0079.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0079_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_314480_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0079.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0108.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0108_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_272922_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0108.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0191.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0191_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_323360_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0191.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0215.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0215_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_579305_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0215.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0274.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0274_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_299003_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0274.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0297.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0297_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_351573_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0297.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0540.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0540_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_223395_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0540.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0564.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0564_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_156514_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0564.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0598.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/DSC_0598_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_519079_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0598.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/erebus-2.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/erebus-2_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_416354_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;erebus-2.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/erebus.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/erebus_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_395611_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;erebus.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/Pole.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/Pole_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_561402_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Pole.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/royal-society.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/royal-society_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_538251_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;royal-society.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-antarctica&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/Xmas_pole.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/antarctica/Xmas_pole_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_753548_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Xmas_pole.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Glacier Thermodynamics</title>
      <link>https://example.com/teaching/thermo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/teaching/thermo/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hercules Dome</title>
      <link>https://example.com/photo/herc-dome/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/photo/herc-dome/</guid>
      <description>










&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-herc-dome&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/19700103_042818.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/19700103_042818_hu3c9b56034fbbcaba96b73160f93e17d8_436340_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;19700103_042818.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;253&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-herc-dome&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/90296730_10158365520016180_3877880986070941696_n.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/90296730_10158365520016180_3877880986070941696_n_hue776a334b902d7828bf5c7a8aa11ccb3_478774_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;90296730_10158365520016180_3877880986070941696_n.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-herc-dome&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/90966299_10158365519386180_6265774758449643520_n.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/90966299_10158365519386180_6265774758449643520_n_hu27f7dc34c9db8fd2b063f3fba6be9864_333834_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;90966299_10158365519386180_6265774758449643520_n.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;142&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-herc-dome&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/annika-pres_hu13302735ebbf5f45f6b9c1477bda07d6_2075478_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/annika-pres_hucf0adf9a1741089d7f632eb07a657bd7_41218_a4ad128147252047a33cee41435ea67b.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;annika-pres_hu13302735ebbf5f45f6b9c1477bda07d6_2075478_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; width=&#34;316&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-herc-dome&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/ben_at_hd_hue4873627a0a19c356457209492e55d2d_1040915_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/ben_at_hd_hu1b9822f4ba902a2b4060f77007e3fc12_63864_b29817913d9b4558292dbe850faafc04.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;ben_at_hd_hue4873627a0a19c356457209492e55d2d_1040915_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; width=&#34;124&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-herc-dome&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/DSC_0232.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/DSC_0232_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_198027_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0232.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-herc-dome&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/DSC_0246.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/DSC_0246_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_475090_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0246.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-herc-dome&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/DSC_0309.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/DSC_0309_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_288494_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0309.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-herc-dome&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/DSC_0489.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/DSC_0489_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_225033_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0489.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-herc-dome&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/DSC_0498.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/DSC_0498_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_232141_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0498.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-herc-dome&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/radar-shelter.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/radar-shelter_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_434786_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;radar-shelter.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-herc-dome&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/tiny-driver.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/herc-dome/tiny-driver_hu7af45c05e7eaab656aeab8d5fe153c59_136084_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;tiny-driver.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;127&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ice Temperature</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/ice-temperature/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/project/ice-temperature/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Temperatures of glacier ice range from ~ -60-0°C, which corresponds to a viscosity range over three orders of magnitude. Ice is generally warmest at the glacier bed, being heated by the energy flux from the solid Earth, and coldest near the glacier surface where ice is in equilibrium with the mean air temperature. Heat moves between those two boundaries through the processes of diffusion (spreading out) and advection (transport by flow of the ice itself). Because the length scale for thermal diffusion in ice is long, deviations in ice temperature can be preserved for thousands of years.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-characteristic-length-scale-of-thermal-diffusion-in-ice-temperature-variations-can-be-persistent-for-hundreds-of-years-in-alpine-glaciers-and-for-thousands-to-even-tens-of-thousands-of-years-in-the-greenland-and-antarctic-ice-sheets&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Characteristic length scale of thermal diffusion in ice. Temperature variations can be persistent for hundreds of years in alpine glaciers and for thousands to even tens of thousands of years in the Greenland and Antarctic Ice Sheets.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/ice-temperature/length-scale_hue1f45e5cc90b3a8e94fc86f455d4a964_22870_beac3cb7e04314905bfd229bb30c6295.webp 400w,
               /project/ice-temperature/length-scale_hue1f45e5cc90b3a8e94fc86f455d4a964_22870_c204d6e1207e3840b8d602147ce60bdd.webp 760w,
               /project/ice-temperature/length-scale_hue1f45e5cc90b3a8e94fc86f455d4a964_22870_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/ice-temperature/length-scale_hue1f45e5cc90b3a8e94fc86f455d4a964_22870_beac3cb7e04314905bfd229bb30c6295.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;50%&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Characteristic length scale of thermal diffusion in ice. Temperature variations can be persistent for hundreds of years in alpine glaciers and for thousands to even tens of thousands of years in the Greenland and Antarctic Ice Sheets.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We measure ice temperature directly by drilling into it, installing in-situ instrumentation, and letting the hole freeze in on the instruments. The heat from drilling dissipates on the order of ~months and thereafter instruments measure the representative temperature. Ice-temperature measurements made at slow-moving, accumulation-dominated, ice divide locations (e.g. Greenland Ice Core Project, WAIS Divide) can be used to infer past air temperatures. The past climate is preserved within the ice because the frequency of those climate changes is within the time scale for thermal diffusion. We also measure temperature deviations within the faster moving ice-stream shear margins (more below) and the melt-dominated ablation zone. In the ablation zone, surface meltwater is plentifully available and transports latent heat when it penetrates into a crevasse or through a moulin to the ice-sheet bed.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-ice-temperature-deviations-measured-in-a-cube-of-greenland-ice&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Ice temperature deviations measured in a cube of Greenland ice.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/ice-temperature/ice-block_hu88810bf04c8ced369e3c62ff4c9f9c8c_2995205_26b6469ab0c4684537525001fa150720.webp 400w,
               /project/ice-temperature/ice-block_hu88810bf04c8ced369e3c62ff4c9f9c8c_2995205_7750f8614013696d646369f2266b5f8e.webp 760w,
               /project/ice-temperature/ice-block_hu88810bf04c8ced369e3c62ff4c9f9c8c_2995205_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/ice-temperature/ice-block_hu88810bf04c8ced369e3c62ff4c9f9c8c_2995205_26b6469ab0c4684537525001fa150720.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Ice temperature deviations measured in a cube of Greenland ice.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In highly dynamic areas, heat is generated within the ice column through friction as the ice defoms. Warmer ice means a lower viscosity, more deformation, and thus more heat production, creating a positive feedback loop. Some studies even argue that much of the ice in an ice-stream shear margin is at the pressure-melting point. We found that this feedback is suppressed by cold ice moving through the system, ice that was source from higher and colder regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;













&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-whillans-ice-stream-drainage-area-downstream-gradients-in-the-parameters-that-effect-ice-temperature&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Whillans Ice Stream drainage area. Downstream gradients in the parameters that effect ice temperature.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/ice-temperature/whillans_drainage_hu5bb213718131f03a3ed25d13a029632c_667865_6aa2b60f4c45dd69d3eca84dc021aa2b.webp 400w,
               /project/ice-temperature/whillans_drainage_hu5bb213718131f03a3ed25d13a029632c_667865_864c74954cf23094136a41a43a2534b8.webp 760w,
               /project/ice-temperature/whillans_drainage_hu5bb213718131f03a3ed25d13a029632c_667865_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/ice-temperature/whillans_drainage_hu5bb213718131f03a3ed25d13a029632c_667865_6aa2b60f4c45dd69d3eca84dc021aa2b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;228&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Whillans Ice Stream drainage area. Downstream gradients in the parameters that effect ice temperature.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-modeled-ice-temperatures-using-gradients-like-those-above&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Modeled ice temperatures using gradients like those above.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/ice-temperature/siple_temps_hu36bf039a3ad77098d34b3fcd6c8adaaa_637575_6b9e0b305d76b6655608848ad5185d75.webp 400w,
               /project/ice-temperature/siple_temps_hu36bf039a3ad77098d34b3fcd6c8adaaa_637575_1cd70c154c5ac692a548edfe5199b10a.webp 760w,
               /project/ice-temperature/siple_temps_hu36bf039a3ad77098d34b3fcd6c8adaaa_637575_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/ice-temperature/siple_temps_hu36bf039a3ad77098d34b3fcd6c8adaaa_637575_6b9e0b305d76b6655608848ad5185d75.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;338&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Modeled ice temperatures using gradients like those above.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;radar-attenuation&#34;&gt;Radar Attenuation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice temperature can theoretically be measured remotely using radar attenuation. Attenuation is the result of energy absorption through electrical conduction which is temperature dependent. The function is in the form of an Arrhenius relation,&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/ice-temperature/proton-conduction_huc8f271ddbbce851b3f8210b343fac367_195467_b816286980811cb7f00d3d12057bf08e.webp 400w,
               /project/ice-temperature/proton-conduction_huc8f271ddbbce851b3f8210b343fac367_195467_71be4f756686cf692167855bcadead6e.webp 760w,
               /project/ice-temperature/proton-conduction_huc8f271ddbbce851b3f8210b343fac367_195467_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/ice-temperature/proton-conduction_huc8f271ddbbce851b3f8210b343fac367_195467_b816286980811cb7f00d3d12057bf08e.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;50%&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empirical results for radar attenuation are generally dependent on the radar system and the empirical method used. Here, I show a result that we found in a single ground-based radar transect that traverses 200 km down the Kamb Ice Stream and up onto Siple Dome. We interpret the reflected power of the wave reflected off the ice-bed interface and calculate attenuation rate as the change in measured bed power with ice thickness. Essentially, if the wave travels through more ice we should measure a weaker return and the rate at which that measured power attenuates is temperature dependent.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Western Greenland</title>
      <link>https://example.com/photo/greenland/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/photo/greenland/</guid>
      <description>










&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/camp.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/camp_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_190819_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;camp.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/cliff.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/cliff_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_629829_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;cliff.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/DSC_0019.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/DSC_0019_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_533166_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0019.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/DSC_0365.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/DSC_0365_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_323814_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0365.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/DSC_0370.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/DSC_0370_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_657991_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0370.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;127&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/DSC_0376.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/DSC_0376_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_609880_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0376.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/DSC_0438.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/DSC_0438_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_1008152_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0438.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/DSC_0457.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/DSC_0457_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_590969_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;DSC_0457.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/helo.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/helo_hu7af45c05e7eaab656aeab8d5fe153c59_99958_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;helo.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;127&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/hot-tub.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/hot-tub_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_252089_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;hot-tub.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/margin.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/margin_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_582966_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;margin.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/polar-bear.jpeg&#34; data-caption=&#34;The Polar Bear, Kanger&amp;amp;rsquo;s one and only restaurant outside the airport.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/polar-bear_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_426551_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;The Polar Bear, Kanger&amp;#39;s one and only restaurant outside the airport.&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/shuttle.jpeg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Shuttling our gear out to the ice-sheet margin.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/shuttle_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_302117_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Shuttling our gear out to the ice-sheet margin.&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/spiral-moulin.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/spiral-moulin_hu7af45c05e7eaab656aeab8d5fe153c59_105125_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;spiral-moulin.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;127&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/surface-hoar.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/surface-hoar_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_702703_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;surface-hoar.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/surface-stream.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/surface-stream_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_263510_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;surface-stream.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-greenland&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/tent.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/greenland/tent_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_418605_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;tent.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;285&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crystal Fabric</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/cof/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/project/cof/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Snow crystals are deposited at random orientation on the glacier surface. In other words, the &amp;lsquo;crystal orientation fabric&amp;rsquo; is initially isotropic (non-directional). As ice flows, crystal c-axes rotate away from the primary extensional axis and toward compression. In places where ice flow is consistent for hundreds or thousands of years, the bulk fabric becomes anisotropic. Single-pole fabrics with upward-pointing c-axes develop at an ice divide where flow is uniform vertical compression and outward extension (new snow continually added at the surface). In this case, the ice hardens in the vertical and preserves old ice near the bed. Horizontal girdle fabrics develop in an ice-stream shear margin where transverse shear dominates.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/cof/Isotropic_hu4c9062721c1f76a735e9cffd3be65213_889627_6eb8cfeb30d53b10291f555e8dfe8b4e.webp 400w,
               /project/cof/Isotropic_hu4c9062721c1f76a735e9cffd3be65213_889627_e6a113d7a12ccaa24db70b963ad9fdb6.webp 760w,
               /project/cof/Isotropic_hu4c9062721c1f76a735e9cffd3be65213_889627_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/cof/Isotropic_hu4c9062721c1f76a735e9cffd3be65213_889627_6eb8cfeb30d53b10291f555e8dfe8b4e.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;75%&#34;
               height=&#34;380&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/cof/cof-time-scales_hu42309d25c01196f27b1ea2f003cb9707_253879_0c3363e589866221ac1a378345a36e65.webp 400w,
               /project/cof/cof-time-scales_hu42309d25c01196f27b1ea2f003cb9707_253879_1a2689c21f8e690fb2f7c86850a2710a.webp 760w,
               /project/cof/cof-time-scales_hu42309d25c01196f27b1ea2f003cb9707_253879_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/cof/cof-time-scales_hu42309d25c01196f27b1ea2f003cb9707_253879_0c3363e589866221ac1a378345a36e65.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;75%&#34;
               height=&#34;617&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deformation of ice is a result of primarily defect propagation along the crystal&amp;rsquo;s basal plane. This process is directional, defects do not propagate as easily in the direction of the crystal c-axis; therefore, ice viscosity is orientation dependent with the softest ice aligned with the basal plane. When a strong crystal fabric develops, the bulk ice viscosity can change by ~2 orders of magnitude. This can lead to a feedback where a consistent strain pattern leads to development of a crystal fabric which softens the ice and leads to additional strain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;radar-polarimetry&#34;&gt;Radar Polarimetry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The electrical properties of ice are also orientation dependent. Radio waves move faster (smaller permittivity, $\epsilon$) when polarized perpendicular to the c-axis than parallel. This makes ice what we call a &amp;lsquo;birefringent&amp;rsquo; material.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/cof/birefringence_hu94561f6dc1dc8bae5944e4dbd07761e5_212590_4386b5fd5861eda014cbe2d66850f597.webp 400w,
               /project/cof/birefringence_hu94561f6dc1dc8bae5944e4dbd07761e5_212590_44e755f961e6a9b8026846f255c7c73a.webp 760w,
               /project/cof/birefringence_hu94561f6dc1dc8bae5944e4dbd07761e5_212590_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/cof/birefringence_hu94561f6dc1dc8bae5944e4dbd07761e5_212590_4386b5fd5861eda014cbe2d66850f597.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;50%&#34;
               height=&#34;668&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can take this material property and use it in a technique to measure the ice fabric remotely (without sampling the ice directly) using radar polarimetry. Repeating radar acquisitions in the same location but with a rotated polarization leads to a measured phase shift associated with the varying wave speed. The fabric strength is directly related to the gradient in measured phase difference between the two polarizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We carried out a radar polarimetry experiment at Hercules Dome in order to constrain past and present ice flow there. The strength and orientation of inferred crystal orientation fabric tells us about the flow paterns in the recent past (~10-20 ka) which we compare to the present day ice dynamics that we can measure directly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Planetary</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/planetary/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/project/planetary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have growing interests in planetary ice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pingos-and-permafrost&#34;&gt;Pingos and Permafrost&lt;/h2&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/planetary/ibyuk_photo_huff484b46316dbbf0ff5b4ea932cd3378_3678507_e46cb14f3190b96dfacf46cdf864f0c0.webp 400w,
               /project/planetary/ibyuk_photo_huff484b46316dbbf0ff5b4ea932cd3378_3678507_abbcd5d19cfd8806f0ab885096272705.webp 760w,
               /project/planetary/ibyuk_photo_huff484b46316dbbf0ff5b4ea932cd3378_3678507_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/planetary/ibyuk_photo_huff484b46316dbbf0ff5b4ea932cd3378_3678507_e46cb14f3190b96dfacf46cdf864f0c0.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;573&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;martian-radar-sounding&#34;&gt;Martian Radar Sounding&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geophysical Tools</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/geophysical-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/project/geophysical-tools/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;impdar&#34;&gt;ImpDAR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ImpDAR (Impulse raDAR) is a suite of processing and interpretation tools for impulse radar sounding, led by Dr. David Lilien. The software (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dlilien/ImpDAR&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;hosted on github&lt;/a&gt;) is targeted for ice-penetrating radar applications but usable for ground-penetrating radar and associated surveying applications as well. The core processing steps and general terminology come from a set of Matlab scripts developed at St. Olaf College under Dr. Robert Jacobel. Here, everything has been re-written in Python and significant improvements to speed, readability, documentation, and interface have been made across the board. Additionally, ImpDAR is intended to be more flexible than other available options. Support is gradually being added for a variety of file formats. Currently, GSSI, PulseEKKO, GPRMax, SEGY, and several custom file formats are supported. Available processing steps include various filtering operations, trivial modifications such as restacking, cropping, or reversing data, geolocation-related operations like interpolating to constant trace spacing, and various migration routines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to processing, ImpDAR can also be used for interpreting radargrams (i.e. picking layers). Picking is generally an interactive process, so there is a GUI for carrying out the semi-automated picking procedure. Each picked layer is saved with variables for both the depth and picked power (i.e. the root-mean-square amplitude). The GUI also allows for basic processing steps, with the updates happening to the plot in real time to aid the picking process. We are also developing an automated picking algorithm that will ideally pick both internal layers and the bed reflector.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/geophysical-tools/layer-interpretation_hube5f12825a8c46f8fd63167a1dbd1ae4_349398_35481a88845e3d15a3f736c9c58b3a8c.webp 400w,
               /project/geophysical-tools/layer-interpretation_hube5f12825a8c46f8fd63167a1dbd1ae4_349398_d10d4dc68ef138846c8f52375b9f1a97.webp 760w,
               /project/geophysical-tools/layer-interpretation_hube5f12825a8c46f8fd63167a1dbd1ae4_349398_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/geophysical-tools/layer-interpretation_hube5f12825a8c46f8fd63167a1dbd1ae4_349398_35481a88845e3d15a3f736c9c58b3a8c.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;750&#34;
               height=&#34;750&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;apdar&#34;&gt;ApDAR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ApRES (Autonomous phase-sensitive Radio Echo Sounder) is a new and popular tool within the glaciology community. It is a pulse-compression radar that transmits a phase-coherent waveform, so repeat acquisitions can be used for interference in order to measure small changes in returned phase. Phase changes are associated either with a difference in the total distance that the wave travels or differences in the wave speed through the medium. We are actively developing an ImpDAR extension for ApRES processing, called &amp;lsquo;ApDAR&amp;rsquo;. We preserve a similar data structure to the impulse data, so users will have some familiarity across the two.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-repeat-apres-acquisition-showing-motion-phase-offset-of-measured-reflectors&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Repeat ApRES acquisition, showing motion (phase offset) of measured reflectors.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/geophysical-tools/pres_hu847edfb215e0444d8ce3ecd2fe00402b_56497_5ca1cae0709d5aa41c41dbaf70d33a25.webp 400w,
               /project/geophysical-tools/pres_hu847edfb215e0444d8ce3ecd2fe00402b_56497_a9789dea67f75c3931103264078511bd.webp 760w,
               /project/geophysical-tools/pres_hu847edfb215e0444d8ce3ecd2fe00402b_56497_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/geophysical-tools/pres_hu847edfb215e0444d8ce3ecd2fe00402b_56497_5ca1cae0709d5aa41c41dbaf70d33a25.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;640&#34;
               height=&#34;480&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Repeat ApRES acquisition, showing motion (phase offset) of measured reflectors.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ApDAR is built to be modular so that various ApRES acquisition techniques can be loaded and processed. One such technique is radar polarimetry, where the antennas are intentionally polarized in one direction or another to pick out differences in the material properties of the ice, namely the ice-crystal orientation fabric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;seidart&#34;&gt;SeiDarT&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SeiDarT (Seismic-Radar Toolbox) is a full-waveform geophysical modeling package meant for both seismic and radar applications (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/UMainedynamics/SeidarT&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;hosted on github&lt;/a&gt;). Again, the majority of the development is with ice in mind as the primary media, but the tool could be used for other materials as well. This package was primarily developed by Steven Bernsen and Christopher Gerbi at the University of Maine.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34;
           src=&#34;https://example.com/project/geophysical-tools/Ex.gif&#34;
           loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable width=&#34;50%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alpine Glaciology</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/alpine-glaciology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/project/alpine-glaciology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Much of the original theory in glaciology came from work on alpine glaciers, mostly in Europe. This is partially because of their relative proximity to human civilizations, but also becuase until recently we thought that the polar ice sheets operated on millenial timescales, too long to be of immenent concern. It was only around the turn of the century that the glaciological community started to recognize key instabilities within the ice sheets that can be triggered much faster, on the order of decades to centuries. While alpine glaciers have since gotten less attention in terms of sea-level focused research publications and grant funding, they are still critical for water supply, temperature, and chemistry, especially in alpine environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ice-dynamics&#34;&gt;Ice Dynamics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We study alpine glacier dynamics using various tools and techniques. As an example, we use a ground-based radar interferometer at the north face of Mt. Baker. We repeatedly scan the mountain face every 2 minutes for several days and by comparing the phase return between scans can tell how objects in the field of view are moving. This is much like the ApRES measurement described in &lt;a href=&#34;https://example.com/project/geophysical-tools/&#34;&gt;Geophysical Tools&lt;/a&gt; but many different reflections from across a range of azimuths.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/alpine-glaciology/baker_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_456965_827fc8f41bf89976f4976ed5e44643c0.webp 400w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/baker_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_456965_a47e3ade094309f58f304ad911e78f18.webp 760w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/baker_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_456965_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/alpine-glaciology/baker_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_456965_827fc8f41bf89976f4976ed5e44643c0.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with Dr. Peter Neff of the University of Minnesota, we are surveying Combatant Col in preparation for an ice core to be drilled there in summer 2023. This is a radar survey which includes not only measurements of the ice geometry, but also repeat measurements to investigate a perennial firn aquifer and to understand how the ice is flowing.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/alpine-glaciology/waddington_surveying_hue0bab21f1beaed078012c0d9ee9e2341_6008249_f715a590510380780e8de29af359a301.webp 400w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/waddington_surveying_hue0bab21f1beaed078012c0d9ee9e2341_6008249_8535491999195f0719e48c6861779ccd.webp 760w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/waddington_surveying_hue0bab21f1beaed078012c0d9ee9e2341_6008249_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/alpine-glaciology/waddington_surveying_hue0bab21f1beaed078012c0d9ee9e2341_6008249_f715a590510380780e8de29af359a301.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;346&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mass-balance&#34;&gt;Mass Balance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States Geological Survey (USGS) has a surveying outpost at four alpine glaciers, Sperry Glacier in Montana, Wolverine and Gulkana Glaciers in Alaska, and South Cascade Glacier in Washington. For decades, they have been tracking the mass balance, the amount of ice added by snow and removed by melting. Understanding how these USGS ‘benchmark’ glaciers are changing over decadal timescales is helping us understand the regional influence of climate change. Our research group at UW works in collaboration with scientists at USGS, including Dr. Caitlyn Florentine and others, doing field campaigns to collect data for surveying these glaciers, especially at our local South Cascade Glacier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measuring glacier mass balance is relatively simple. For inputs, we drill a snow core or dig a snow pit at the end of the winter season and measure the total depth as well as density through the column. Together, depth and density give us an input balance in units of snow water equivalent (SWE). For outputs, we drill a metal stake into the ice at the beginning of summer and observe how much it has melted out by the end. Again, this measurement will be in SWE. Then the balance inputs (accumulation) and outputs (ablation) are summed to quantify glacier change. At South Cascade, the average mass balance over the past 50 years has been about -0.5 m/yr over the extent of the glacier’s area (Rasmussen and Conway, 2001; fig. 10).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;













&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/alpine-glaciology/snow-pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_6b0ea882f61214c227913e302f30bdbd.webp 400w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/snow-pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_5c47e78f58e87dac9c35ebe8f03508e7.webp 760w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/snow-pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/alpine-glaciology/snow-pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_6b0ea882f61214c227913e302f30bdbd.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/alpine-glaciology/density_hu3f7236b7fdca2276b75c71ce23cc382b_207829_ca42cb50c7145ad115977f5be3c47949.webp 400w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/density_hu3f7236b7fdca2276b75c71ce23cc382b_207829_2e41a6b6315ece17bfac126de900ce03.webp 760w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/density_hu3f7236b7fdca2276b75c71ce23cc382b_207829_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/alpine-glaciology/density_hu3f7236b7fdca2276b75c71ce23cc382b_207829_ca42cb50c7145ad115977f5be3c47949.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;574&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conventional mass balance methods described above are still in use for many glaciers today, including a continuing record for South Cascade Glacier. Being glacier geophysicists though, we are interested in developing more innovative ways to measure the inputs and outputs for the system. In particular, we are using ice-penetrating radar to get a distributed snow depth measurement at the end of the winter season. The hope is not to abandon the snow coring completely, but to use the two in parallel to build a more robust, and glacier wide, observation for snow inputs to the glacier system. With radar, we can easily see a reflection of the previous summer’s surface (giving the total snow depth accumulated over the winter season), but in some areas we can also see deeper reflections from multi-year snow (firn) layers. Firn observations could provide insight into the mechanisms for accumulation in this alpine setting including avalanching and wind-blown snow.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/alpine-glaciology/SCG_Panel_Map_hu1c16bbbe2e5dc55abb81abf305f056cd_1802779_0042bc5172d2e3a3539b00c912b00ade.webp 400w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/SCG_Panel_Map_hu1c16bbbe2e5dc55abb81abf305f056cd_1802779_64d5a90e73a7ea91598fea08aedb8a53.webp 760w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/SCG_Panel_Map_hu1c16bbbe2e5dc55abb81abf305f056cd_1802779_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/alpine-glaciology/SCG_Panel_Map_hu1c16bbbe2e5dc55abb81abf305f056cd_1802779_0042bc5172d2e3a3539b00c912b00ade.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;730&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drilling in Ice</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/drilling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/project/drilling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ice-core-drilling&#34;&gt;Ice-Core Drilling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of our work aids in site selection for ice cores. We use geophysical tools to survey the ice geometry and stratigraphy. We can estimate ice age, ice temperature, past flow patterns, etc. With this information, paleoclimatologists are able to make an informed desicion on specifically where to drill an ice core in order to retrieve ice that will answer their pending quesitons about the ancient atmosphere and climate. Hercules Dome is currently our primary project. The site is close enough to West Antarctica that it should record a climate signal in the case of West Antarctic Ice Sheet collapse, but far enough that ice would not have melted during that time.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/drilling/HD_icesheetgeometry_hu5b6464a03c04b7dde544f0b21efeae90_1201275_640226aebd920645c55f1aeb9346228e.webp 400w,
               /project/drilling/HD_icesheetgeometry_hu5b6464a03c04b7dde544f0b21efeae90_1201275_b728b0248b0ee1e1314e0f64d79e302e.webp 760w,
               /project/drilling/HD_icesheetgeometry_hu5b6464a03c04b7dde544f0b21efeae90_1201275_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/drilling/HD_icesheetgeometry_hu5b6464a03c04b7dde544f0b21efeae90_1201275_640226aebd920645c55f1aeb9346228e.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;100%&#34;
               height=&#34;649&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hot-water-drilling&#34;&gt;Hot-Water Drilling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike ice-core drilling, thermal drilling methods such as with hot water are destructive, so the goal is not to retrieve any ice. Instead, hot-water holes are used to install instruments which measure in-situ properties like ice temeprature, stress/strain, subglacial water pressure, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;













&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-organizing-instrumentation-and-cabling-in-preparation-to-deploy-it-down-the-hole&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Organizing instrumentation and cabling in preparation to deploy it down the hole.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/drilling/surface-cables_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_657819_9b14a2a2e64cbbf4be7df05c0acd9c0c.webp 400w,
               /project/drilling/surface-cables_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_657819_332b82a3bf72958c7c347e5851af4ec9.webp 760w,
               /project/drilling/surface-cables_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_657819_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/drilling/surface-cables_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_657819_9b14a2a2e64cbbf4be7df05c0acd9c0c.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;100%&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Organizing instrumentation and cabling in preparation to deploy it down the hole.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-looking-down-an-instrumented-hole&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Looking down an instrumented hole.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/drilling/hole-cables_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_170451_ab400531032e7ad3e223443745b5255b.webp 400w,
               /project/drilling/hole-cables_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_170451_c08be67297c1126089ec8cdef45a4920.webp 760w,
               /project/drilling/hole-cables_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_170451_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/drilling/hole-cables_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_170451_ab400531032e7ad3e223443745b5255b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;100%&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Looking down an instrumented hole.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hot-point-drilling&#34;&gt;Hot-Point Drilling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is another thermal drilling method which uses conduction at the tip of a melt probe rather than hot water. These drills are simpler in design, so were used earlier, and lighter weight so can be deployed more quickly than hot-water drills. In collaboration with Dr. Dale Winebrenner and Dr. Tim Elam at the Applied Physics Laboratory, I wrote a thermal model and ran an ensemble of model experiments to aid in the engineering design of their hot-point drill, &lt;a href=&#34;https://apl.uw.edu/project/project.php?id=ice_diver&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ice Diver&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/drilling/drill-series_hu1d58162c7fc8bccdcf98ffd91112108a_304824_267847a81154252d6e58c84876bf99e8.webp 400w,
               /project/drilling/drill-series_hu1d58162c7fc8bccdcf98ffd91112108a_304824_652b6a1d09add1d3f13b12dfa4f9a24b.webp 760w,
               /project/drilling/drill-series_hu1d58162c7fc8bccdcf98ffd91112108a_304824_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/drilling/drill-series_hu1d58162c7fc8bccdcf98ffd91112108a_304824_267847a81154252d6e58c84876bf99e8.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;428&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ImpDAR Tutorials</title>
      <link>https://example.com/teaching/impdar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/teaching/impdar/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#39;Working remotely&#39; as a polar field scientist</title>
      <link>https://example.com/blog/remote-fieldwork/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/blog/remote-fieldwork/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are wrapping up our fourth* season at Hercules Dome, Antarctica. I use an asterisk because it hasn’t really been the fourth at all. For the first season, in ‘18-’19, we had a 4-person team who was meant to deploy a full field camp for a full month of work on the ground; instead, we spent ~6 weeks at South Pole Station for a handful of day trips commuting back and forth to Hercules Dome. The second season was as expected, ‘19-’20 brought a 7-person team to the field where we did most of the surveying seen in the figure below. The third “season” was not a season at all, Covid halted nearly 100% of Antarctic field work in ‘20-’21. Finally, this current season that is wrapping up now was a small and lightweight team, with only a single scientist on the ground, meant to get in for only a few repeat acquisitions and nothing else. Hercules Dome was originally proposed as a 2-year surveying project and has now been extended to a total of 5 seasons, such is the nature of Antarctic fieldwork during a global pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-map-of-our-ongoing-survey-at-hercules-dome-overlaid-on-the-rema-surface-elevation-solid-lines-show-positions-of-the-profiling-radar-transects-where-we-map-ice-stratigraphy-and-structure-of-the-underlying-bedrock-dots-show-locations-where-we-measure-vertical-ice-motion-with-a-specialized-radar-system-red-circles-show-the-priority-for-repeat-measurements-that-happened-this-season&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A map of our ongoing survey at Hercules Dome overlaid on the REMA surface elevation. Solid lines show positions of the profiling radar transects where we map ice stratigraphy and structure of the underlying bedrock. Dots show locations where we measure vertical ice motion with a specialized radar system. Red circles show the priority for repeat measurements that happened this season.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/HD_map_2122_hu1d4487603f979735dcc191e2140be7c6_1788984_ac925f73060b24f9a63e46b7cb24c29d.webp 400w,
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/HD_map_2122_hu1d4487603f979735dcc191e2140be7c6_1788984_e7a18f8e9ffdb530d5a88f3d1626180f.webp 760w,
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/HD_map_2122_hu1d4487603f979735dcc191e2140be7c6_1788984_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/remote-fieldwork/HD_map_2122_hu1d4487603f979735dcc191e2140be7c6_1788984_ac925f73060b24f9a63e46b7cb24c29d.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;571&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A map of our ongoing survey at Hercules Dome overlaid on the REMA surface elevation. Solid lines show positions of the profiling radar transects where we map ice stratigraphy and structure of the underlying bedrock. Dots show locations where we measure vertical ice motion with a specialized radar system. Red circles show the priority for repeat measurements that happened this season.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was supposed to be the UW scientist on the ground this season, but I failed the physical qualification examination (PQ) due to mild anxiety/depression. I am not particularly bitter about this. We were able to find a fantastic last-minute replacement, Erika Schreiber of Unavco, who successfully made all of our top priority measurements. Moreover, I was able to spend the holidays with my new fiancée and her family. Having said that, I do want to explain what happened and why I think it is problematic.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-my-fiancée-dani-decorating-the-first-christmas-tree-we-have-had-as-our-own-after-being-together-for-9-years&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;My fiancée, Dani, decorating the first Christmas tree we have had as our own after being together for ~9 years.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/tree_hue89a0aa046b09da89068440f8a9c75be_126460_28266a1c1bc72b1dfd2ef3c930812567.webp 400w,
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/tree_hue89a0aa046b09da89068440f8a9c75be_126460_ebf917d9d79ecfc110fb209b8ca701dd.webp 760w,
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/tree_hue89a0aa046b09da89068440f8a9c75be_126460_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/remote-fieldwork/tree_hue89a0aa046b09da89068440f8a9c75be_126460_28266a1c1bc72b1dfd2ef3c930812567.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;472&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      My fiancée, Dani, decorating the first Christmas tree we have had as our own after being together for ~9 years.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In July, I returned from Montana, where I had been riding out the pandemic, to Seattle in order to carry out my PQ. The necessary procedures include dental exams, blood work, as well as a range of other tests depending on the candidate&amp;rsquo;s age and history within the US Antarctic Program. As some examples, in preparation for my first Greenland deployment they made me get an EKG, and this year the doctor insisted that we do a prostate exam because the language on the document did not make it sufficiently clear that this is only necessary for middle-aged men. Like many others, I have a history of mild anxiety/depression for which I have been prescribed an SSRI in the past. This would not normally be an issue for Antarctic fieldwork, I have travelled to Antarctica carrying this medication before. I have even deployed without the medication at a time when I had elected to stop taking it, my doctor being unconcerned. This year was a bit different though. A flag came up during the mental health check on my PQ (who hasn’t been depressed during Covid??) and I learned that once the flag goes up it is very hard to bring it back down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything being in flux, I saw a new doctor for my PQ this season, one who had no context of my medical history. She was rightfully concerned about my mental health going into a solo field deployment, so she checked the box saying “participant will require further evaluation prior to clearance” since she wanted to start me back on the SSRI for a month before clearing me. Note that this was in July and I was due to deploy in November, so there was time for a secondary evaluation. I believe that my doctor saw me as fit to deploy assuming that I took well to the medication; unfortunately, the medical staff who carry out the PQ paperwork did not see it this way and disqualified me before my doctor could do any further evaluation. There is a procedure to waive the disqualification, but it involves my University signing off on a liability agreement which they were ultimately unwilling to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel mostly unaffected by this disruption since we were able to find a replacement, and I was well supported by my academic advisor as well as my friends and family. However, this exposed me to inefficiencies within the PQ process which I feel could be more disruptive to others, especially younger students who have not had as many opportunities for fieldwork (note that this is a critical learning experience for many earth scientists). Mental health concerns are rampant among academics, and there should be a clear pathway toward successful participation in field campaigns for anyone who can safely do so. Moreover, the review procedure should rely more heavily on trained mental health professionals. My counselor said that she would be willing to sign off in approval of my deployment, but unfortunately her voice did not carry much weight in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After much back and forth, the decision was made clear that I would not deploy for this season only a few weeks before the scheduled departure. Luckily for us, Erika agreed to fill in as a replacement on this extremely short notice. While she had significant polar experience prior to this season, she had never deployed to Antarctica and obviously didn’t have direct experience at Hercules Dome. Suffice it to say, she got her fill of Zoom calls with me and my advisor. Not only did we need to explain our scientific priorities and instrument procedures, but we also had numerous favors for other field groups which she graciously took on. Luckily she had time for reading and reviewing during her 2-week quarantine in New Zealand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After numerous layovers Erika finally arrived at South Pole Station on December 7th. From there, she would acclimatize before using the Twin Otter as a flight commuter for day trips to Hercules Dome. As is typical for this type of work, she faced weather delays during which she did instrument tests around the South Pole. We were having regular calls and she would send data back to us so that we could check that the instrument was working properly. I could tell with certainty whether she was making the measurement in the same way we had done in the past because she was reoccupying old field sites and if done properly the radar return would be coherent with prior acquisitions. Finally, on December 17th, we had our first true science day at Hercules Dome. She returned with the data shown below which, as you can see in the bottom panel, nicely reproduce a prior result of the vertical velocity structure.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-top-panel-coherence-represents-how-similar-the-measured-waveforms-are-between-two-acquisitions-middle-panel-the-phase-offset-tells-us-how-far-a-feature-has-moved-updown-within-the-ice-bottom-panel-the-vertical-velocity-is-simply-the-phase-offset-converted-to-units-of-distance-over-time&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Top panel: Coherence represents how similar the measured waveforms are between two acquisitions. Middle panel: The phase offset tells us how far a feature has moved up/down within the ice. Bottom panel: The vertical velocity is simply the phase offset converted to units of distance over time.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/blog_pres_hu29b6964728c3af8ef7372565a95e8991_300189_0f82244d7eea5f05bc65cad67b9a2eb4.webp 400w,
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/blog_pres_hu29b6964728c3af8ef7372565a95e8991_300189_be6231dd76636685ef311e9e3b9c53c0.webp 760w,
               /blog/remote-fieldwork/blog_pres_hu29b6964728c3af8ef7372565a95e8991_300189_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/remote-fieldwork/blog_pres_hu29b6964728c3af8ef7372565a95e8991_300189_0f82244d7eea5f05bc65cad67b9a2eb4.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;633&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Top panel: Coherence represents how similar the measured waveforms are between two acquisitions. Middle panel: The phase offset tells us how far a feature has moved up/down within the ice. Bottom panel: The vertical velocity is simply the phase offset converted to units of distance over time.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside of the scientific priority for the season, a logistical priority was to revisit the cache that we buried in ‘19-’20. Most of what was left there is unimportant, things like food remaining from that season and relatively inexpensive gear such as shovels and sleds. What do need to be recovered are the 30+ drums of fuel we left, most of which is for the airplanes which will now use Hercules Dome as a remote gas station. Erika and the team did not have time to un-dig the cache, so they reflagged it and left the work for next year. Lucky for me, I like digging :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, the upcoming and final season at Hercules Dome will be a full field campaign similar to what we had in ‘19-’20. We need to deploy the field camp in order to fill in the remainder of the survey shown in the top figure. Based partially on new information from the measurements that Erika made this season, we are now focusing wholeheartedly on West Dome as the site at which the ice core will likely be drilled. The ‘22-’23 priority will be to densify our survey around West Dome in order to choose a precise drilling location. Fortunately, the PQ process is renewed on an annual basis, so my disqualification this year has no bearing on future deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tokenized Thought</title>
      <link>https://example.com/blog/open-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/blog/open-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you to Jocelynn Pearl for reviewing a preliminary version of this article and to Dani Bergey for figure design.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Utility of the NFT expands far beyond fine art and collectibles. Today’s mania does not reflect the more holistic vision and ubiquitous tokenization that is about to take hold. This includes physical assets like the deed to a house and the title to a car, capital assets like stocks and bonds, and as I will argue here, intellectual assets like patents and publications. Intellectual property as a digital object written to the blockchain will change the way we think about publishing science, opening the process to be more transparent and realigning incentives within academic communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-past-and-future-of-scientific-publication&#34;&gt;The Past and Future of Scientific Publication&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we think of today as ‘science’ formed around a culture of natural philosophy, where a small group of thinkers shared ideas through both spoken and written word. As time progressed and groups of thinkers got bigger, individuals wanted to benchmark ideas as their own. The first official patents were developed through the Venetian Patent Statute in 1474. Eventually, patenting inventions alone was not enough, thinkers wanted to document their understanding of the universe, and the first scientific journal was published in 1665 by the Royal Society. This exclusive group initially consisted of only 40 members. Finally, in the late 19th Century, many more subscription and/or for-profit journals began publishing scientific articles. Notably, Science and Nature magazines were both started at this time. While much of the science during this era was published as somewhat informal letters between authors, it is also when the peer-review process was formalized and publishing became what it is today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many academics likely get the feeling of decentralization even now, especially with the myriad open science tools like Python, Github, etc.; unfortunately, the reality is that a few publishers control the space and that a few critical data centers hold most of the publicly accessible data. The majority of prominent journals still institute a paywall, publishing can be prohibitively expensive, and data products are often concealed well after the associated manuscript is published. Throughout history, unexpected events where the state seized control of information flow, like book burnings, have shown us that centralized powers can quickly and unilaterally manipulate free thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a next logical step forward in the history of science and intellectual property, we can imagine publishing thoughts and inventions as NFTs on a dedicated Ethereum rollup. In this way, scientific information and the scientific process reach beyond a singular elite to become a public good. The landscape of blockchain-based science will include but strengthen all of the scientific platforms that we already use today. As open science builds upon the subscription journals that we have used for hundreds of years, so too will the future of blockchain publishing take advantage of the open science tools that we have been building in the last decade. The critical piece that will enable truly ‘open’ science is trustless ownership on the blockchain. Scientists will rest assured that a digital book burning is not possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blockchain-based publishing will be an improvement to the user experience as well. Any person will be able to benchmark their idea from any place and at any time. Since the blockchain cannot be edited, there will forever be evidence that the person had their idea at the time it was published. This takes power away from publishers, whose sole purpose is to act as an intermediary between the idea creators and the idea consumers. Then, with a less restrictive publication process, scientists will tend to publish more incremental progress and more continuously. Continuous publication will slow down the rush of publishing a written manuscript to avoid getting ‘scooped’, and it will give credibility in publishing investigations that do not result in a peer-reviewed manuscript or those that give an ambiguous result. Today, those efforts generally go uncredited. Instead, scientists will focus on incremental publications like software updates through git (which can currently be thought of as a private and centralized blockchain), data-sharing through a decentralized database (IPFS), and of course written articles through blockchain-based journals.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./timeline.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;academic-coordination-through-daos&#34;&gt;Academic Coordination through DAOs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic communities will coordinate through Decentralized Autonomous Organizations (DAOs). Members of a given DAO will share common interests, they will coordinate to progress understanding in their given field. As an example, I will use a community to which I personally belong, the American Geophysical Union (AGU). As a DAO, the AGU would control a small treasury to fund annual meetings, workshops, etc. The AGU DAO would publish several distinct journals, as it does today, and would pay journal editors, reviewers, etc. from the treasury as well. The DAO would be governed by its community, and those who contribute the most would earn the largest portion of the voting rights. While geophysicists coordinate around the AGU DAO, chemists will have slightly different priorities and perspectives; they will form a distinct DAO around the American Chemical Society (sorry for the America-centrism, in reality these will be mostly international groups). The same goes for biologists, mathematicians, you get the point. DAOs are a global coordination tool, and who needs to leverage global coordination more than a dispersed group of thinkers trying to debate the nature of the universe?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;token-based-incentivization&#34;&gt;Token-Based Incentivization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideas and inventions will be published on the blockchain as intellectual property, this much is clear. Further though, I envision the complete tokenization of academic achievement. Digital tokens will be used to represent not only publications but educational achievement, teaching performance, citation metrics, and effectiveness as a peer reviewer. Taken together, these tokens will be a continuous record of one’s performance. Hence, they will act as a public and ever-evolving CV. While the scientist of today is often fixated on boosting their h-index, a measure of citation count only, the scientist of tomorrow should be incentivized to continue learning, they should be more rigorously assessed on their teaching effort, they should be adequately compensated for their peer review. Each of these achievements will be tokenized as either fungible or non-fungible tokens. None of the tokens will have any monetary value or be tradeable at all. They will be desirable for the same reason that a high h-index is desirable, because they are a public display of one’s scientific status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take the example shown below. Scientists A and B publish a series of scientific work, some of which is reviewed by scientist C, and is eventually cited by scientist D. First, scientist A writes the software for their model and publishes that on her own, receiving an NFT representing her ownership. Scientist B, meanwhile, collects data to test their model and publishes that as a separate NFT. To benchmark their progress they then work together to create a figure illustrating their work so far. They publish this with the code from A and the data from B both contained as objects within the hash of the figure’s NFT. Because the figure directly uses work from both A and B, each is included automatically as an author of the figure as well as the subsequent manuscript. NFTs for those publications have two copies, one held by each author. This continuation of authorship down the publication chain remains true no matter how long the chain becomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, D publishes a new manuscript which cites the original written by A and B. As soon as the citing manuscript is published as an NFT, citation tokens are awarded to the authors of the cited manuscript, A and B, signaling that their work was used in a new project. If D went on to update their manuscript, no additional citation tokens would be provided, only one citation per chain of scientific products. Citation tokens will be fungible, so authors accumulate them in the same way they accumulate citations through Google Scholar or any other centralized platform today. Citation tokens will also be divisible and rewards will be weighted based on the type of publication. For instance, a peer-reviewed manuscript would earn more tokens per citation than a standalone figure or data product.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-flow-diagram-for-publication-review-and-citation-tokens-large-circles-represent-individual-scientists-rectangles-represent-published-products-and-small-yellow-circles-represent-tokens-the-black-icon-of-glasses-and-a-hat-represents-a-private-transaction-or-token-arrows-coming-from-an-individual-represent-their-signature-on-the-associated-item-being-published&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./publication-flowmap.png&#34; alt=&#34;Flow diagram for publication, review, and citation tokens. Large circles represent individual scientists, rectangles represent published products, and small yellow circles represent tokens. The black icon of glasses and a hat represents a private transaction or token. Arrows coming from an individual represent their signature on the associated item being published.&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Flow diagram for publication, review, and citation tokens. Large circles represent individual scientists, rectangles represent published products, and small yellow circles represent tokens. The black icon of glasses and a hat represents a private transaction or token. Arrows coming from an individual represent their signature on the associated item being published.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;incentivized-peer-review&#34;&gt;Incentivized Peer Review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists are currently expected to act as peer reviewers on a purely voluntary basis. There are no requirements from journals that enforce a specific quantity or quality of peer review. Instead, the blockchain and DAO-centered journal model will offer additional tokens for peer reviewers. In the example provided, scientist C acts as the reviewer for the manuscript submitted by A and B. The review is initiated as a smart contract which enforces that upon completion of the review and acceptance by the editor: 1) the reviewed product will be republished as a new NFT with the reviewer’s signature proving that the review was done, and 2) the reviewer will be rewarded a separate NFT representing their association with the object. Upon citation of the reviewed object, citation tokens are also awarded to the reviewer, C, in order to incentivize a strong review. Of course, the review is less valuable than the work itself, so the rewards will be weighted appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often peer reviewers wish to remain anonymous. In general, the blockchain model for intellectual property would be open and public; however, it is important to maintain the option for private review so that critiques can be honest and the reviewers do not face direct scrutiny. If a reviewer chooses to remain anonymous, their NFT will be held in a private wallet, and any citation tokens will accumulate through private transactions using zk-proof technology. Citation tokens will appear in the reviewers public wallet, so the fact that they acted as a reviewer on some scientific document that got cited would be public information. The same would be true if an individual wanted to publish an article anonymously but still get credit for the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;distributed-data-storage&#34;&gt;Distributed Data Storage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storage and sharing of scientific knowledge including data products, articles, software, etc., will be on a distributed database built on IPFS (e.g. filecoin). In essence, volunteers from the community rent storage space on their computers which are then used to store the complete archive of scientific information, and those volunteers are incentivised to do so. Because the network is decentralized, access to this information cannot be restricted from anyone or at any time. Protocols that are currently running decentralized storage networks use rational proof-of-storage algorithms to maintain that the data do in fact exist in the state in which they were sent. This distributed database will run in parallel to the publication blockchain discussed above where object hashes are stored. Therefore, when a scientist has a new idea to publish, the network will require them to upload the associated data, manuscript, etc. to this distributed database before they are rewarded their publication token. Thus, all published data will be free and publicly available. The hash for the published object will forever be attached to the publisher&amp;rsquo;s signature and will therefore be provably theirs. That author will then be attributed whenever that data or idea is cited in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;distributed-funding-mechanisms&#34;&gt;Distributed Funding Mechanisms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funds for scientific research are generally distributed through government programs, either at the federal, state, or local level. There are some exceptions including privately funded grants as well as crowd-sourced funding; these are generally looked down upon because the science can proceed without peer review. An alternative would be to use smart contracts similar to Gitcoin’s funding mechanism. Here, both private and crowd-sourced funds could be matched to public funds within the context of a conventional peer review. Private donors would choose a proposal that suits them and submit funds to a smart contract. This contract would hold the community funds until a peer-review decision is made on that proposal. If the peer review is successful, those funds would be contributed to the funded grant; if not, those funds would be returned to the donor. In some cases it may be appropriate to use a government-funded matching pool and quadratic funding allocation based on the number of donors, as in Gitcoin’s funding model.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./funding.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital ownership is not true ownership unless it is represented in a trustless way on a public blockchain. If not, digital objects can be copied and redistributed or worse, they can be transformed and distorted. Intellectual property is perhaps the most valuable form of ownership and is no exception. In the current academic system, ownership and scientific incentives are undervalued and taken advantage of by centralized and archaic publishing regimes. Blockchain - and its overhaul of the art market in particular - give insight for an academic future with more fair incentives, self-custody of intellectual property by the thinker themself, and generally a more distributed scientific field which levels the playing field for its participants. Significant work has already been done toward this effort. Proposals have already been laid out for smart-contract-based peer review. Organizations like Bloxberg, ResearchHub, and Planck Manuscripts are already working on implementing similar incentivization mechanisms to that described above. Research fundraising is being coordinated around decentralized groups like VitaDAO. Eventually, all the work that is being done now to secure financial infrastructure on Ethereum will also be used to secure intellectual property and academic infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Avoiding slush for hot-point drilling of glacier boreholes</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/hills2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/hills2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Radar Stratigraphy</title>
      <link>https://example.com/photo/radar/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/photo/radar/</guid>
      <description>










&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-radar&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/hd_mcords.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/hd_mcords_hue9649e47bef86d7f3505baafe3e6f9da_8706783_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;hd_mcords.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;274&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-radar&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/hd_x45loop.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/hd_x45loop_hu5d9649754fe17c6a2298f2d419c32151_17015163_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;hd_x45loop.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;274&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-radar&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/hd_x53.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/hd_x53_hu120f39e4cc541dd5c6994e4fac8e8abd_14333123_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;hd_x53.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;274&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-radar&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/kamb.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/kamb_hu120f39e4cc541dd5c6994e4fac8e8abd_17621084_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;kamb.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;274&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-radar&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/quadpol.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/quadpol_hu5a24dcec77158565d9e6a393e8399813_8905349_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;quadpol.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;274&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-radar&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/spl.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/spl_huabe10ef0bbe0a6a80f40c9a46fbae55a_15353506_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;spl.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;274&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-radar&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/thwaites_1.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/thwaites_1_hu98c4132014a44fede2241dae56395275_187705_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;thwaites_1.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;273&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-radar&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/thwaites_2.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/thwaites_2_hu3615af93a7df5fd9e95412db25f1ed03_176428_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;thwaites_2.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;274&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-radar&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/thwaites_3.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/thwaites_3_hub32ae36db18b32f02383de16dba2ace3_183265_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;thwaites_3.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;273&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-radar&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/wgz.jpeg&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/radar/wgz_hu120f39e4cc541dd5c6994e4fac8e8abd_14635531_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;wgz.jpeg&#34; width=&#34;274&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Radar Polarimetry</title>
      <link>https://example.com/photo/polarimetry/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/photo/polarimetry/</guid>
      <description>










&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-polarimetry&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/a0r5.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/a0r5_hued5a7f3760577101dfe67d78743cf977_282366_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;a0r5.png&#34; width=&#34;190&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-polarimetry&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/e0s40000.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/e0s40000_hu782053e962a469b0362ba04d96d7ad41_275351_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;e0s40000.png&#34; width=&#34;190&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-polarimetry&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/e0s50000.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/e0s50000_hu33eb5f49f409f93e86873a168f82ac9d_214703_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;e0s50000.png&#34; width=&#34;190&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-polarimetry&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x135n2000.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x135n2000_hud1cd5047a6291957f9c2f3350b4a3087_240520_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;x135n2000.png&#34; width=&#34;190&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-polarimetry&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x135n5000.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x135n5000_hua9eb2feb5e1c748aa9eefb4c98b5f94e_197412_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;x135n5000.png&#34; width=&#34;190&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-polarimetry&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x135s5000.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x135s5000_hufd1875550d8d4681533f1390a770b605_239220_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;x135s5000.png&#34; width=&#34;190&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-polarimetry&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x55n0.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x55n0_hu609a9867890ddda98a76e7d3dc1145e7_252889_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;x55n0.png&#34; width=&#34;190&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-polarimetry&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x95n0.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x95n0_hu510f6303bd4eb4df6e790451f90b3930_231731_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;x95n0.png&#34; width=&#34;190&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-polarimetry&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x95n2000.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x95n2000_hu38a9fdcaac7c5e8a628b75ec23c4a2db_229637_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;x95n2000.png&#34; width=&#34;190&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-polarimetry&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x95s1000.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x95s1000_hue893927b4bf3654ad006a4ebd7f1ed09_272477_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;x95s1000.png&#34; width=&#34;190&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-polarimetry&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x95s2000.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x95s2000_hu29cdd7655d2e61270c697a5befd65300_259406_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;x95s2000.png&#34; width=&#34;190&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-polarimetry&#34; href=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x95s5000.png&#34; &gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://example.com/media/albums/polarimetry/x95s5000_hua018d0abf65e0ff9c9627452c9dd28eb_323602_0x190_resize_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;x95s5000.png&#34; width=&#34;190&#34; height=&#34;190&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ImpDAR: an open-source impulse radar processor</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/lilien2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/lilien2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A framework for attenuation method selection evaluated with ice-penetrating radar data at South Pole Lake</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/hills2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/hills2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Go Back?</title>
      <link>https://example.com/blog/why-go-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/blog/why-go-back/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;They say that the first time you go to Antarctica is for the adventure, the second for the science, and the third because you no longer belong anywhere else. I would hope that it is always for the science, but I do understand how people get attached to the community down here. Life on the ice is mission oriented; whether for science or support, the team knows what needs to get done and works together to accomplish the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you read my writing last year, you will know that we had some logistical issues with our project at Hercules Dome. In a way, we had to come back to even get a real start. Having said that, it is common for field projects to be spread across multiple seasons, and some of our team will be coming down next year as well. I want to give somewhat of an explanation for why any field-based project would need more than one season on the ice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;logistical-reasons-to-return&#34;&gt;Logistical Reasons to Return&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first and perhaps most obvious reason that we come back is that there is simply too much work to do in the short Antarctic summer. The only working months for deep field projects in Antarctica are late-November, December, and January. After accounting for some bad weather days, time on the front and back end to move cargo around and test equipment, and expected flight delays, there is not much time left to do the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Hercules Dome, our original plan was to have two field seasons over which to spread the surveying that we had planned, the ’18-’19 and the ’19-’20 austral summers. For each, we planned ~20-30 dedicated science days with a small team of 6-7 personnel in an isolated field camp. Last year, a decision was made early in the season that the surface conditions were too rough at our field site to land the LC-130-Hercules (‘Herc’) which is the Air National Guard plane that we needed to bring in our cargo. Based on that decision, our contingency was to do day trips from South Pole Station using the Twin Otter (a much smaller aircraft). Our total number of science days at Hercules Dome last year amounted to ~2.5, so we obviously did not get done all of what we were hoping for. Fortunately, NSF agreed to fund us for an additional season (&amp;lsquo;20-&amp;lsquo;21) because of these logistical setbacks.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-our-groomed-skiway-at-hercules-dome-with-the-field-camp-on-the-right-hand-side-note-the-scale-of-the-surface-roughness-these-sastrugi-are-what-prevented-us-from-landing-the-herc-last-year-photo-credit-rodney-fishbrook-our-twin-otter-pilot-for-the-first-half-of-the-season&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Our groomed skiway at Hercules Dome with the field camp on the right-hand side. Note the scale of the surface roughness, these sastrugi are what prevented us from landing the Herc last year. Photo credit: Rodney Fishbrook, our Twin Otter pilot for the first half of the season.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/why-go-back/skiway_hu7d1472b035cfc73c709fc3246cf2351f_610022_0612fcde909166421a5771350a72117b.webp 400w,
               /blog/why-go-back/skiway_hu7d1472b035cfc73c709fc3246cf2351f_610022_ed8b1e68355778645b321d9727586813.webp 760w,
               /blog/why-go-back/skiway_hu7d1472b035cfc73c709fc3246cf2351f_610022_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/why-go-back/skiway_hu7d1472b035cfc73c709fc3246cf2351f_610022_0612fcde909166421a5771350a72117b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;577&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Our groomed skiway at Hercules Dome with the field camp on the right-hand side. Note the scale of the surface roughness, these sastrugi are what prevented us from landing the Herc last year. Photo credit: Rodney Fishbrook, our Twin Otter pilot for the first half of the season.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with our limited success, the radar data that we were able to collect last year were instrumental in starting to understand the dome and in our survey planning for this season. Coming into this season, we were able to place a 4-person ground crew in the field in late November to groom a skiway for the Herc to land on. The grooming equipment is a 500-lb frame with adjustable metal tines that plow the snow. We have been calling it a ‘glorified pneumatic rake’ which is dragged behind a snowmobile, essentially amounting to carving out a patch of the ice sheet with a lawn-mower . On December 22nd, the plane landed with ~13,000 pounds of cargo. Then, on December 26th the remaining crew (including myself) landed at Hercules Dome and our science could begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;scientific-reasons-to-return&#34;&gt;Scientific Reasons to Return&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, our science also necessitates that we return to complete our measurements of ice motion. Ice moves slowly, especially at an ice divide or an ice dome like Hercules Dome, so we need to wait a considerable amount of time before we can return to measure how far it has moved. For horizontal motion, we use precision GPS instruments at the ice surface which give us a static location at one point in time. Leaving a surveying marker in the snow, we can return the following year to repeat the GPS measurement and learn how far it has moved in the horizontal direction. For vertical motion, we use a special phase-coherent radar instrument. This instrument is similar to our other ice-penetrating radar systems, but with a critical difference that it records phase information from the wave alongside the conventional measurement of wave amplitude through time.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-waveform-represented-in-the-complex-plane&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A waveform represented in the complex plane.&#34;
           src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/why-go-back/phase.gif&#34;
           loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A waveform represented in the complex plane.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing why a phase measurement can be useful warrants another short physics lesson. There are three components to any wave, the frequency is how long it takes for a 2-pi period of the wave to pass, the amplitude is a measure of the real ‘strength’ of the signal, and the phase is the time-varying location of the wave within its periodic cycle. The animation above shows a waveform as represented in the complex plane. Looking at the circle, the phase of the waveform is represented by the angle that the rotating line makes with the horizontal; hence, the phase repeats itself every time the moving point completes the circle (i.e. at 2 pi). While the power (i.e. the radius of the circle) remains constant in time, the real component fluctuates. With a conventional radar system, we would only measure the real component of the waveform, so there is no way to know the phase. However, with a phase-coherent radar system, we use information that we know about the transmitted waveform to back out the imaginary component as well and can then know the phase with precision to ~1 degree. With a center frequency of 300 MHz, the 1-degree precision allows us to measure vertical ice motion on the order of mm.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-annika-fixing-one-of-our-radar-systems-while-we-wait-for-the-apres-to-run-being-a-particularly-distant-site-we-had-to-fly-here-in-the-twin-otter-which-can-be-seen-on-the-horizon&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Annika fixing one of our radar systems while we wait for the ApRES to run. Being a particularly distant site, we had to fly here in the Twin Otter which can be seen on the horizon.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/why-go-back/annika-pres_hu13302735ebbf5f45f6b9c1477bda07d6_2075478_4a82c58bd458a6293fd239a127972109.webp 400w,
               /blog/why-go-back/annika-pres_hu13302735ebbf5f45f6b9c1477bda07d6_2075478_5978deff64dbac51f6427972fb3aaf24.webp 760w,
               /blog/why-go-back/annika-pres_hu13302735ebbf5f45f6b9c1477bda07d6_2075478_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/why-go-back/annika-pres_hu13302735ebbf5f45f6b9c1477bda07d6_2075478_4a82c58bd458a6293fd239a127972109.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;457&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Annika fixing one of our radar systems while we wait for the ApRES to run. Being a particularly distant site, we had to fly here in the Twin Otter which can be seen on the horizon.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the field, we are using a newly developed phase-sensitive radar system from the British Antarctic Survey known as the ApRES (Autonomous phase-sensitive Radio Echo Sounder). We use this system to measure vertical motion through the entire ice column using a series of impurity contrasts within the ice that cause reflections that we can observe. Since the impurity contrasts move with the ice, we can observe their movement. We were able to make a few ApRES measurements last year, so we have confirmation with our repeated measurements this year that the instrument is working. Having more time on the ground this season, we were able to collect 50 of these ApRES measurements. In the case that we are able to repeat them all next season, we will have a good idea of vertical motion over much of the dome.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-repeated-apres-measurement-used-to-infer-vertical-ice-motion-the-top-panel-is-the-measured-phase-over-a-sample-window-represented-by-the-moving-line-in-the-bottom-three-panels-the-second-panel-is-the-radar-profile-with-the-strength-of-the-returning-signal-being-diminished-with-depth-until-the-ice-bed-interface-at-2800-m-the-third-panel-is-the-correlation-between-the-year-1-and-year-2-measurements-as-expected-correlation-drops-off-below-1500-m-because-the-signal-is-noisy-for-deep-returns-the-fourth-panel-is-the-inferred-displacement-between-measurements-the-result-is-well-behaved-above-1500-m-where-the-correlation-is-high&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A repeated ApRES measurement used to infer vertical ice motion. The top panel is the measured phase over a sample window represented by the moving line in the bottom three panels. The second panel is the radar profile with the strength of the returning signal being diminished with depth until the ice-bed interface at ~2800 m. The third panel is the correlation between the year 1 and year 2 measurements. As expected, correlation drops off below ~1500 m because the signal is noisy for deep returns. The fourth panel is the inferred displacement between measurements, the result is well behaved above ~1500 m where the correlation is high.&#34;
           src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/why-go-back/pres.gif&#34;
           loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A repeated ApRES measurement used to infer vertical ice motion. The top panel is the measured phase over a sample window represented by the moving line in the bottom three panels. The second panel is the radar profile with the strength of the returning signal being diminished with depth until the ice-bed interface at ~2800 m. The third panel is the correlation between the year 1 and year 2 measurements. As expected, correlation drops off below ~1500 m because the signal is noisy for deep returns. The fourth panel is the inferred displacement between measurements, the result is well behaved above ~1500 m where the correlation is high.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;continuous-delays&#34;&gt;Continuous Delays&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of now, we are still waiting for a plane to take us off continent. The delays have been frustrating this year, not only for us, but for all of the deep field groups. For the most part, these delays have been inevitable. Early in the season, weather in West Antarctica created unsuitable flying conditions through late November and early December which is when most groups are trying to get out into the field. Additionally, we are short on LC-130’s and there was an early mechanical issue with the C-17 that set all the cargo movement behind starting in November. The delays on the way out have been a combination of mechanical and weather-related as well. By far our closest attempt to escape was on Saturday, my birthday. That day, we had a 10-hour trip out to the skifield here in McMurdo to watch the C-17 fly in from Christchurch, load our cargo, and then be told that the plane is now broken and will sit on the ground while wait to get a decision from Boeing on whether or not it can be flown. At around 10pm the no-fly decision was made. Lucky for us, they brought out food to tide us over during our long wait (i.e. hot dogs with no bun, utensils, or condiments…).&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-new-friends-to-greet-me-along-the-returning-journey-the-first-in-mcmurdo-and-the-second-still-waiting-for-me-back-home&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;New friends to greet me along the returning journey, the first in McMurdo and the second still waiting for me back home.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/why-go-back/critters_hu5173823e27f62e392edd7495b108e579_247288_af83d9718be9723d6ee1872fbc9dee20.webp 400w,
               /blog/why-go-back/critters_hu5173823e27f62e392edd7495b108e579_247288_bc3f6ff56f8f6494826428e969d67056.webp 760w,
               /blog/why-go-back/critters_hu5173823e27f62e392edd7495b108e579_247288_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/why-go-back/critters_hu5173823e27f62e392edd7495b108e579_247288_af83d9718be9723d6ee1872fbc9dee20.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;598&#34;
               height=&#34;255&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      New friends to greet me along the returning journey, the first in McMurdo and the second still waiting for me back home.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Glacier Mass Balance at South Cascade</title>
      <link>https://example.com/blog/mass-balance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/blog/mass-balance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I came home from a week-long field trip to South Cascade Glacier in Washington. South Cascade is one of the United States Geological Survey (USGS) benchmark glaciers, along with Gulkana and Wolverine in Alaska as well as Sperry in Glacier National Park, Montana. The benchmark glacier program was set up by the USGS to intensively monitor climate, glacier motion, glacier mass balance, glacier geometry, and stream runoff for these select glaciers which are thought to be representative of their respective region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why monitor glaciers? Aside from the fact that they are a fascinating aspect of the earth system, one reason is because they act as a low-pass filter on changes in climate. While climatic variables such as the air temperature and precipitation change on time scales as short as hours to days to years, ice flows slowly enough that it absorbs all the high-frequency information and responds at more like decadal (alpine glacier) or centennial (polar ice sheet) time scales. Therefore, glacier growth and decay are typically (c.f. tidewater glacier cycle) expressive of the longer term climate trend whether that be a change in temperature, precipitation, or both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a community, we have been measuring glacier change for at least several decades now. The easiest and most obvious way to do so is also the most illustrative for the public, a simple photo. Projects like the Extreme Ice Survey use photo time series to display glacier retreat in a way that needs no explanation. Some studies even use anecdotal evidence and drawings to extend the record further back in time (to 1602 for the Rhone Glacier). In our case at South Cascade, photos display that the terminus has retreated by ~3 kilometers over the past century. In the 1950&amp;rsquo;s and 60&amp;rsquo;s, this glacier terminated in a proglacial lake, but around 1970 the glacier pulled up out of the lake and now the terminus rests a full kilometer further uphill.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-photo-time-series-of-south-cascade-glacier-usgs&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A photo time series of South Cascade Glacier. USGS.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/mass-balance/history_hu6021e390eb012c2a28d2828b2a80ad68_497490_c7a04911d514d956333c96613858b503.webp 400w,
               /blog/mass-balance/history_hu6021e390eb012c2a28d2828b2a80ad68_497490_3f9441f5f04c3aa2d7a035f05f65abc0.webp 760w,
               /blog/mass-balance/history_hu6021e390eb012c2a28d2828b2a80ad68_497490_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/mass-balance/history_hu6021e390eb012c2a28d2828b2a80ad68_497490_c7a04911d514d956333c96613858b503.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;690&#34;
               height=&#34;550&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A photo time series of South Cascade Glacier. USGS.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-south-cascade-glacier-today-note-that-this-photo-was-taken-in-the-spring-so-there-is-considerably-more-snow-but-less-glacier-ice-than-above-photo-credit-gemma-oconnor&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;South Cascade Glacier today. Note that this photo was taken in the spring, so there is considerably more snow (but less glacier ice) than above. Photo credit: Gemma O&amp;#39;Connor.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/mass-balance/scg_hu8d171eafad3e5ec247601b00697c4980_4525133_85e6157b1b402b00aa22c1881da13c88.webp 400w,
               /blog/mass-balance/scg_hu8d171eafad3e5ec247601b00697c4980_4525133_52d7938e7319d4ba27b99bd7077066fb.webp 760w,
               /blog/mass-balance/scg_hu8d171eafad3e5ec247601b00697c4980_4525133_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/mass-balance/scg_hu8d171eafad3e5ec247601b00697c4980_4525133_85e6157b1b402b00aa22c1881da13c88.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      South Cascade Glacier today. Note that this photo was taken in the spring, so there is considerably more snow (but less glacier ice) than above. Photo credit: Gemma O&amp;rsquo;Connor.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mass-balance-methods&#34;&gt;Mass Balance Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While photos are illustrative, as scientists we want a more rigorous and quantitative way to measure glacier change. To do this, we calculate the ‘mass balance’ of the system, much like a water balance for those with experience in hydrology. The idea is what goes in must come out OR be stored in the glacier as ice. For a glacier, the balance input is snow, which through time is compressed into glacier ice, and the balance outputs are meltwater as well as iceberg calving. Hence, a negative mass balance means that there is more summer melting (and/or calving) than winter snow and the glacier therefore has a net loss (i.e. it is shrinking). On the other hand, a positive mass balance would mean net gains and glacier growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As shown in the schematic below, the high elevation areas of a glacier tend to have a positive mass balance because it snows more and melts less. This region is called the &amp;lsquo;accumulation area&amp;rsquo;. At lower elevations, melting dominates the system in the &amp;lsquo;ablation area&amp;rsquo;. The final component of glacier balance is ice flow from the net positive mass balance in the accumulation area to the net negative in the ablation area, keeping the system in a steady state if the glacier is stable.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-schematic-of-glacier-mass-balance-usgs&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A schematic of glacier mass balance. USGS.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/mass-balance/schematic_hu055126dfc99cfe5a0e61e19c9cac8081_138294_e5a1e29aff839d99510b33bf3be19737.webp 400w,
               /blog/mass-balance/schematic_hu055126dfc99cfe5a0e61e19c9cac8081_138294_bb235608989cfa893ad34cc9a9882fcb.webp 760w,
               /blog/mass-balance/schematic_hu055126dfc99cfe5a0e61e19c9cac8081_138294_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/mass-balance/schematic_hu055126dfc99cfe5a0e61e19c9cac8081_138294_e5a1e29aff839d99510b33bf3be19737.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;460&#34;
               height=&#34;322&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A schematic of glacier mass balance. USGS.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measuring glacier mass balance is relatively simple. For inputs, we drill a snow core or dig a snow pit at the end of the winter season and measure the total depth as well as density through the column. Together, depth and density give us an input balance in units of snow water equivalent (SWE). For outputs, we drill a metal stake into the ice at the beginning of summer and observe how quickly it has melted out by the end. Again, this measurement will be in SWE. Then the balance inputs (accumulation) and outputs (ablation) are summed to quantify glacier change. At South Cascade, the average mass balance over the past 50 years has been about -0.5 m/yr over the extent of the glacier&amp;rsquo;s area (Rasmussen and Conway, 2001; fig. 10).&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-gemma-oconnor-measuring-snow-densities-and-erin-whorton-taking-notes&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Gemma O&amp;#39;Connor measuring snow densities and Erin Whorton taking notes.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/mass-balance/pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_c1e50f56893692b0708f8b6d8fe88c7f.webp 400w,
               /blog/mass-balance/pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_950b77fe2f3a2c75513adfb62b78124a.webp 760w,
               /blog/mass-balance/pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/mass-balance/pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_c1e50f56893692b0708f8b6d8fe88c7f.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Gemma O&amp;rsquo;Connor measuring snow densities and Erin Whorton taking notes.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conventional mass balance methods described above are still in use for many glaciers today. Being glacier geophysicists though, we are interested in developing more innovative ways to get at the inputs and outputs for the system. In particular, we are using ice-penetrating radar to get a distributed snow depth measurement at the end of the winter season. The hope is not to abandon the snow coring completely, but to use the two in parallel to build a more robust, and glacier wide, observation for snow inputs to the glacier system. With radar, we can easily see a reflection of the previous summer&amp;rsquo;s surface (giving the total snow depth accumulated over the winter season), but in some areas we can also see deeper reflections from multi-year snow (firn) layers. Firn observations could provide insight into the mechanisms for accumulation in this alpine setting including avalanching and wind-blown snow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-global-perspective&#34;&gt;A Global Perspective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously the USGS are not the only group measuring glacier mass balance; in fact, most of the longer records come from European glaciers such as Storglaciären or Engabreen. Historically, most of the well-monitored glaciers tend to be those that are close to human civilizations. However, at the onset of the earth-observing satellite era (~1970) it became much easier to survey the global glacier network remotely. This includes glaciers in the arctic but also in North and South America, New Zealand, high mountain Asia, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, the global picture looks similar to what we see in our backyard. Mostly everything is melting, and over the past ~50 years the melt rates show an acceleration. Even though mountain glaciers don&amp;rsquo;t have the potential to effect future sea-level rise to the same extent as the polar ice sheets, there is still some contribution to sea-level rise (~mm/yr, see figure below), and the recession of alpine glaciers means a lot for both the surrounding ecological system as well as the communities that depend upon glaciers as a water supply.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-top-glaciers-around-the-globe-bottom-ice-mass-loss-and-mass-loss-rates-for-alpine-glaciers-around-the-world-these-figures-are-taken-from-the-ipcc-fifth-assessment-reporthttpswwwipccchreportar5wg1&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Top) Glaciers around the globe. Bottom) Ice mass loss and mass loss rates for alpine glaciers around the world. These figures are taken from the [IPCC fifth assessment report](https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/mass-balance/global_map_hub96782b94b601335ab68c556cc3b8482_737040_8b9c82d42c4679ee2463cfacf85692b7.webp 400w,
               /blog/mass-balance/global_map_hub96782b94b601335ab68c556cc3b8482_737040_86781388dcc5604d0c832c5890ad333b.webp 760w,
               /blog/mass-balance/global_map_hub96782b94b601335ab68c556cc3b8482_737040_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/mass-balance/global_map_hub96782b94b601335ab68c556cc3b8482_737040_8b9c82d42c4679ee2463cfacf85692b7.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;526&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Top) Glaciers around the globe. Bottom) Ice mass loss and mass loss rates for alpine glaciers around the world. These figures are taken from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IPCC fifth assessment report&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mass balance survey at South Cascade has been ongoing at the USGS since around 1960, and our collaboration with them will continue into future seasons. Stay tuned! Hopefully we will have more interesting (if somewhat sad) insights into this glacier&amp;rsquo;s health.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides</title>
      <link>https://example.com/slides/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/slides/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;create-slides-in-markdown-with-wowchemy&#34;&gt;Create slides in Markdown with Wowchemy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wowchemy&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&#34;https://owchemy.com/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficiently write slides in Markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3-in-1: Create, Present, and Publish your slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supports speaker notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mobile friendly slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;controls&#34;&gt;Controls&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next: &lt;code&gt;Right Arrow&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;Space&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Previous: &lt;code&gt;Left Arrow&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start: &lt;code&gt;Home&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish: &lt;code&gt;End&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overview: &lt;code&gt;Esc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaker notes: &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fullscreen: &lt;code&gt;F&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zoom: &lt;code&gt;Alt + Click&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hakimel/reveal.js#pdf-export&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PDF Export&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;code&gt;E&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-highlighting&#34;&gt;Code Highlighting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inline code: &lt;code&gt;variable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code block:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;porridge = &amp;quot;blueberry&amp;quot;
if porridge == &amp;quot;blueberry&amp;quot;:
    print(&amp;quot;Eating...&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;math&#34;&gt;Math&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In-line math: $x + y = z$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Block math:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
f\left( x \right) = ;\frac{{2\left( {x + 4} \right)\left( {x - 4} \right)}}{{\left( {x + 4} \right)\left( {x + 1} \right)}}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;fragments&#34;&gt;Fragments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make content appear incrementally&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{{% fragment %}} One {{% /fragment %}}
{{% fragment %}} **Two** {{% /fragment %}}
{{% fragment %}} Three {{% /fragment %}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;Space&lt;/code&gt; to play!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
   One 
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
   **Two** 
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
   Three 
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fragment can accept two optional parameters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;class&lt;/code&gt;: use a custom style (requires definition in custom CSS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;weight&lt;/code&gt;: sets the order in which a fragment appears&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;speaker-notes&#34;&gt;Speaker Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add speaker notes to your presentation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;{{% speaker_note %}}
- Only the speaker can read these notes
- Press `S` key to view
{{% /speaker_note %}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Press the &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; key to view the speaker notes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only the speaker can read these notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; key to view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;themes&#34;&gt;Themes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;black: Black background, white text, blue links (default)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;white: White background, black text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;league: Gray background, white text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;beige: Beige background, dark text, brown links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sky: Blue background, thin dark text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;night: Black background, thick white text, orange links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;serif: Cappuccino background, gray text, brown links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;simple: White background, black text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;solarized: Cream-colored background, dark green text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;section data-noprocess data-shortcode-slide
  
      
      data-background-image=&#34;/media/boards.jpg&#34;
  &gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;custom-slide&#34;&gt;Custom Slide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customize the slide style and background&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;{{&amp;lt; slide background-image=&amp;quot;/media/boards.jpg&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
{{&amp;lt; slide background-color=&amp;quot;#0000FF&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
{{&amp;lt; slide class=&amp;quot;my-style&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;custom-css-example&#34;&gt;Custom CSS Example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s make headers navy colored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create &lt;code&gt;assets/css/reveal_custom.css&lt;/code&gt; with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-css&#34;&gt;.reveal section h1,
.reveal section h2,
.reveal section h3 {
  color: navy;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/wowchemy/wowchemy-hugo-modules/discussions&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wowchemy.com/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ice-Penetrating Radar</title>
      <link>https://example.com/blog/ice-penetrating-radar/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/blog/ice-penetrating-radar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We study ice dynamics; namely, how the Greenland and Antarctic ice sheets are moving, how they may have been moving in the past, and how they will move into the future. Ice flows downhill under the force of gravity. As it moves to lower elevation, it eventually either melts or calves and floats away, both contributing mass to the oceans. Thus, the principal importance of our research is to put constraints on future projections of sea-level rise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a geophysics team, the research tools that we use are a suite of geophysical methods including GPS, remote sensing (satellites), ice-penetrating radar, seismics, and physics-based computer models. With GPS and remote sensing methods we measure the elevation and velocity of the ice surface. We get at least cm precision with our GPS (down to mm when using real-time kinematics from a stationary base station). With radar and seismics, on the other hand, we survey the internal structure and intrinsic properties of the ice sheets. The basics of radar (seismic) methods are to transmit a radio (seismic) wave at the ice surface and to look (listen) for the reflections. The radio waves that we transmit are in the high to very-high frequency range (close to the same frequencies that you would use in your car or on a handheld radio). Seismics in glaciological applications are typically active source, using an explosion triggered at the surface. By measuring the time and amplitude of the returning waves (both radar and seismic), we learn what we need to build intuition about the dynamic nature of the ice-sheet system. Finally, we test our intuition using computer models.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-cartoon-illustration-of-ice-penetrating-radar-and-some-example-data-from-the-northeast-greenland-ice-stream&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A cartoon illustration of ice-penetrating radar and some example data from the Northeast Greenland Ice Stream.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ipr_cartoon_hu2dddb388711da89393e7649c08552bc5_475851_6956e7285cc7e35b22f10952a9cdc528.webp 400w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ipr_cartoon_hu2dddb388711da89393e7649c08552bc5_475851_7e0a5ab9ef5cdff4c9610c5315a3014b.webp 760w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ipr_cartoon_hu2dddb388711da89393e7649c08552bc5_475851_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ipr_cartoon_hu2dddb388711da89393e7649c08552bc5_475851_6956e7285cc7e35b22f10952a9cdc528.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;749&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A cartoon illustration of ice-penetrating radar and some example data from the Northeast Greenland Ice Stream.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I want to focus on radar methods for a couple of reasons. First, they are the primary focus of my personal research. In fact, I have never been on a seismic campaign. Second, our current field season at Herc Dome is a radar campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the fact that radio waves penetrate ice was discovered not by a glaciologist, but by an atmospheric physicist. In the 1960’s, a man named Piggott had an ionosonde stationed on the Brunt Ice Shelf, looking for radio-wave reflections off of the ionosphere. Curious about the consistently absent signal at a regularly-spaced interval, he proposed that reflections from below (off of the ice-water interface at the bottom of the floating ice shelf) were interfering with his primary reflections from the ionosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, we now know that Piggott was correct and have since developed theory as to why radio waves move so easily through crystalline ice. Most of the electromagnetic spectrum is absorbed by ice (making it opaque), although at different rates and by different mechanisms depending on frequency. High-energy photons (microwaves to visible light and higher) are absorbed and converted to either lattice vibrations (heat) or electronic transitions (electron jumps to a higher shell). Low-energy photons (~kHz radio waves) are absorbed by Debye Relaxation (molecular rotations). This leaves an absorption gap for the ~MHz frequency range that we use in our research. Therefore, radio waves at these frequencies can easily image ice that is 3-4 km thick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In using ice-penetrating radar to image the ice sheets, by far the strongest reflection comes from the ice-bedrock interface. This interface represents a permittivity contrast (i.e. that the radio wave travels faster through ice than it does through bedrock). Here it is useful to recall an illustrative demonstration on wave reflections from freshman physics. Take two ropes of unequal weight and tie them together. When a wave traveling through the lighter rope hits the knot between the two, some of the energy propagates forward as a wave in the heavier rope (although at a slower speed); however, the remaining energy is reflected back into the lighter rope in the direction from which it came. The idea in our ice-penetrating radar case is the same, with the knot in the rope being analogous to the ice-bedrock interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having ~50 years of experience behind us, we are building progressively better radar systems with which we can see not only the extremely bright bed reflector, but also the dimmer internal reflectors from within the ice column. Similarly to the bed, these are permittivity contrasts which are typically a result of variations in the impurity content of the ice. The visible stratigraphy of the ice mapped by these internal reflectors leads to the somewhat obvious geometric interpretations of radar data, but we are also starting to use the information in the amplitude of the measured waveform for additional insight. For example, if the ice-bedrock interface is melted the reflection is brighter, so we can use the strength of a bed reflection to say something about the nature of the bed.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-theradar-shelter-containing-the-computer-a-gps-on-top-and-the-leading-red-as-well-as-trailing-black-antennae-the-shelter-is-a-nice-break-from-the-wind-but-it-is-still-not-warm-in-here&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The radar shelter containing the computer, a GPS on top, and the leading (red) as well as trailing (black) antennae. The shelter is a nice break from the wind, but it is still not warm in here.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/radar-shelter_hud91ee38fd9ecc041d795446f233bb91a_266073_66676853e8ea18f6769d7024b64192a6.webp 400w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/radar-shelter_hud91ee38fd9ecc041d795446f233bb91a_266073_3367372f29d6aeb218d763d531d7712d.webp 760w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/radar-shelter_hud91ee38fd9ecc041d795446f233bb91a_266073_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/ice-penetrating-radar/radar-shelter_hud91ee38fd9ecc041d795446f233bb91a_266073_66676853e8ea18f6769d7024b64192a6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;571&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The radar shelter containing the computer, a GPS on top, and the leading (red) as well as trailing (black) antennae. The shelter is a nice break from the wind, but it is still not warm in here.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-apres-radar-with-the-data-logger-in-the-center-next-to-the-gps-and-the-two-antennae-stretched-out-on-either-side&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The ApRES radar with the data logger in the center next to the GPS and the two antennae stretched out on either side.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/apres_hubb6e1558ebe2ad9a2005af4a458250be_1936637_53b5f59b7fc7b2a226742ec8ac294236.webp 400w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/apres_hubb6e1558ebe2ad9a2005af4a458250be_1936637_0b1b7098f02f6eff063a1f79d1f0f7dd.webp 760w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/apres_hubb6e1558ebe2ad9a2005af4a458250be_1936637_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/ice-penetrating-radar/apres_hubb6e1558ebe2ad9a2005af4a458250be_1936637_53b5f59b7fc7b2a226742ec8ac294236.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;306&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The ApRES radar with the data logger in the center next to the GPS and the two antennae stretched out on either side.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Herc Dome we are using 3 radars. The first is a high frequency system (3 MHz) with which we can see to the bed of the ice sheet. Unfortunately though, there is a tradeoff between range and resolution, the 3 MHz antennae give us data that can be vertically resolved only to the scale of ~meters. For this reason, we also use a very-high frequency system (500 MHz) which gives us more like cm-scale resolution although its signal is fully attenuated by about 20 m below the surface. The third system is a phase-coherent radar called the ApRES (autonomous phase-sensitive radio-echo sounder). This system is a bit more complicated so I will not get into the details, but it essentially uses the additional phase information in the waveform to allow incredibly high precision for changes in time. Hence, we can use the ApRES to measure layer motion on the order of mm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary goal of this and following seasons (hopefully two more in 2019-21) are to survey Herc Dome in order to provide guidance for ice-core drilling at this location. We are looking for signs of stability and hopefully a frozen bed. The dream result would be to find a feature called a ‘Raymond Bump’ which forms in the case of a steady divide location for at least a few tens of thousands of years. The bump would indicate a good drilling site because it demonstrates that the ice is not melting at the bed in that location, we would know that the seasonal layers have been well-preserved within the ice, and it implies stability close to the last interglacial which is the time period we are interested in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our day-to-day in the field is mostly spent on a snowmobile or in the radar shelter where we keep the computer while it logs incoming data. All day, we drive around in the flat white expanse. In a way, traversing the ice-sheet surface feels like navigating the sea; there is nothing to be seen except H2O in any direction, and we even use marine GPS. The sastrugi feel like waves and could make one a bit ‘sled sick’ from the sled-rocking motion. We work long days when we are out, but once we get the radar system going it is not exactly strenuous work. The hope is that we sit back and watch the data come in. Of course, when instruments break our lives get a bit more complicated, and this is somewhat inevitable when it is -30°C and we have a bumpy route over sastrugi.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-me-climbing-into-the-radar-shelter-the-twin-otter-that-we-use-for-our-15-hour-commute-from-the-south-pole-is-in-the-background&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Me climbing into the radar shelter. The Twin Otter that we use for our 1.5 hour commute from the South Pole is in the background.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ben_at_hd_hue4873627a0a19c356457209492e55d2d_1040915_203c068a2b3f02e34ddf4262f35e6bdc.webp 400w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ben_at_hd_hue4873627a0a19c356457209492e55d2d_1040915_ab435430a56bfe16bac5525997c6dcd5.webp 760w,
               /blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ben_at_hd_hue4873627a0a19c356457209492e55d2d_1040915_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/ice-penetrating-radar/ben_at_hd_hue4873627a0a19c356457209492e55d2d_1040915_203c068a2b3f02e34ddf4262f35e6bdc.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;497&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Me climbing into the radar shelter. The Twin Otter that we use for our 1.5 hour commute from the South Pole is in the background.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pole</title>
      <link>https://example.com/blog/the-pole/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/blog/the-pole/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We made it to South Pole Station. It turns out that getting around this continent necessitates a bit of patience. We spent nearly a week in Christchurch, NZ, waiting for the weather to clear so that we could fly to McMurdo (the primary American station). During that week, we had two boomerang flights in which we took off and flew for ~5 hours down over the Southern Ocean only to get turned around back to New Zealand because the pilots did not feel comfortable landing on the McMurdo Ice Shelf. When the weather finally cleared, we landed in McMurdo and I was greeted by the rest of my science team who had been waiting there for three weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McMurdo is an interesting place. In many ways it reminds me of Kangerlussuaq, the center for US science operations in Greenland. The town sits on the McMurdo Sound, across which are the Royal Society Range which tower to 13000&amp;rsquo; from sea level. Being on the coast also means that there is marine wildlife. In the short time that I was there, we saw seals and emperor penguins, but when the icebreaker comes in and breaks the sea ice later in the summer whales, penguins, and seals will surely have a stronger presence. The culture in town in somewhat divided between the contractors and the scientists. They call us &amp;lsquo;beakers&amp;rsquo;, which, although somewhat condescending, is more endearing than the myriad nicknames I was given in high school.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-shuttle-to-our-plane-on-the-mcmurdo-ice-shelf-with-mt-erebus-in-the-background&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Shuttle to our plane on the McMurdo Ice Shelf with Mt. Erebus in the background.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/the-pole/Delta_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_3358740_56b4657c64a4dc423fcd04896ebe8b89.webp 400w,
               /blog/the-pole/Delta_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_3358740_d595c8ecf2c5a823ac3cddc20a14d5d5.webp 760w,
               /blog/the-pole/Delta_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_3358740_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/the-pole/Delta_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_3358740_56b4657c64a4dc423fcd04896ebe8b89.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Shuttle to our plane on the McMurdo Ice Shelf with Mt. Erebus in the background.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, on Saturday the 22nd, we flew to the South Pole which will be our home for the next six weeks or so. Using the station as a home base was not our original plan. We had some logistical problems finding a C-130 landing site at Herc Dome meaning that we will be taking day trips in the smaller Twin Otter. Unfortunately, day trips will not be nearly as productive as staying out at Herc Dome for a full month, but the NSF has generously offered us an additional field season (now we will be coming down the next two years) because the logistical problems were out of our control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flight from McMurdo to Pole is over the Transantarctic Mountains. These mountains mark the boundary between East Antarctica, a stable craton, and West Antarctica, an active rift. We commonly consider the East and West Antarctic Ice Sheets as two seperate systems even though the ice is continuous between them. The East Antarctic Ice Sheet is high and cold; it is considered mostly stable. Ice flows down from East Antarctica through the mountains and into the West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS) which is lower and relatively warm. The bed of WAIS is below sea level which is the root of its susceptibility for collapse, something that has been very apparent for at least 40 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty of the Transantarctic Mountains made it clear to me why ice-sheet landscapes are uniquely attractive. Natural beauty seems to fall into two classifications. The first is the most obvious, being dramatic landscapes such as the Alps or Patagonia. In those settings, sharp contrasts and strong lines highlight features that are striking to our eye. The second is more subtle. The rolling hills of Vermont or even the wide open plains of the Midwest are beautiful because diffusive processes smooth the landscape. These places inspire a feeling of quiet and comfort. Ice-sheet landscapes are unmatched in that they seamlessly coalesce both aspects of natural beauty. Ice flows and diffusively spreads into a smooth surface. Ice far from the mountains is completely flat and white. Only after adjusting one’s perception can the subtle surface slopes be noticed. On the other hand, in mountainous areas nunataks jut straight through the ice, with glacial erosion encouraging steep and dramatic profiles.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-flying-over-the-transantarctic-mountains&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Flying over the Transantarctic Mountains.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/the-pole/transantarctics_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_2874254_9c67154b36ff9b5806a16ec8010cdac6.webp 400w,
               /blog/the-pole/transantarctics_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_2874254_b9ec316632265894b32182f1ce864afd.webp 760w,
               /blog/the-pole/transantarctics_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_2874254_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/the-pole/transantarctics_hu722106d66d2a50f4000fa5df1234233d_2874254_9c67154b36ff9b5806a16ec8010cdac6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Flying over the Transantarctic Mountains.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antarctica is stunning, but we are ultimately here for the science. The diversity of interesting science is what makes South Pole Station an exciting place. In the ‘dark sector’ there is the IceCube Neutrino Observatory, which is a 1 km3 network of Cherenkov detectors buried in the ice, and the South Pole Telescope, which measures cosmic microwaves with the objective of gaining insight about the origins of our universe. SuperDARN is a radio antenna, and a part of a worldwide network used to study the aurora. In the ‘clean-air sector’ there are automated weather stations, and UV measurements to study the ozone hole. There are also field projects based out of the station including our own, but also another University of Washington project on ice and firn dynamics upstream of the South Pole Ice Core (SPICE core).&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-maintenance-work-on-the-south-pole-telescope&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Maintenance work on the South Pole Telescope.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/the-pole/SPT_hu0a4ff54ba61226b25c17514fab2365d0_348343_dcb2375f70b7c15199dd92cc5d3b0c91.webp 400w,
               /blog/the-pole/SPT_hu0a4ff54ba61226b25c17514fab2365d0_348343_e6dbc22fb3297710d65ec4ee09685cb3.webp 760w,
               /blog/the-pole/SPT_hu0a4ff54ba61226b25c17514fab2365d0_348343_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/the-pole/SPT_hu0a4ff54ba61226b25c17514fab2365d0_348343_dcb2375f70b7c15199dd92cc5d3b0c91.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;506&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Maintenance work on the South Pole Telescope.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The station feels as if it were designed by a science fiction writer. Perhaps science fiction ideas have been based on facilities such as this one. Eric Steig, one of our team members, made a comment that this is the closest any of us will ever get to space. At first I thought it was a funny comment; however, after getting here I do feel like that, being in a remote and isolated environment in which all the personnel are either directly or indirectly doing work to support scientific objectives. Even maintaining the facility is a tremendous effort. Several tractors are moving snow out from under the station all summer to keep it from being buried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few quirky aspects of living on station. First, and most obvious, we have 24 hours of daylight. I found this quite entertaining at first, but am getting frustrated to wake up with the feeling that I am late only to realize that it is still 2am. Thorough hand washing on station is a must because viruses circulate quickly. Even with these difficulties, the community here does a lot to keep each other sane. For the first few days after we got here, we were encouraged to relax so that our bodies could properly acclimatize. Since then, we have been working to prepare our science experiments, but have had some down time to explore the station which includes a gym, a green house, a quiet reading room, and the South Pole Store. We even had a nice dinner and there was a foot race ‘around the world’ on Christmas day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going South</title>
      <link>https://example.com/blog/going-south/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/blog/going-south/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am in the process of deploying to Hercules Dome, Antarctica (‘Herc Dome’, named after the airplane above) and will be in the field for at least a month, likely longer. This research trip came as a surprise to me because, in an emergency, an extra field personnel was needed. Two weeks ago, I was putting together a poster for the American Geophysical Union Fall Meeting in Washington D.C. and making Christmas plans with my girlfriend’s family. In the time since I was informed that I would be needed in Antarctica on Tuesday, November 27, I had to renew my passport, pass a rigorous physical examination (including full blood work, a tuberculosis test, a dental examination, etc.), purchase and pack gear for my first trip to the southern continent, write and print my science poster for a friend to hang up at the conference I would be missing, and finish my schoolwork for the quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mental preparation thrust me into a vortex of emotions. Obviously, I am both excited and nervous about the trip itself, but I also sporadically feel sad, isolated, exhausted, proud, hopeful, and even nostalgic as we pass through Christchurch, New Zealand, where I lived as a 20-year-old student. In the days and weeks to come I will have more trainings and preparations to do at both the McMurdo and South Pole stations. Although being dragged through this emotional landscape is somewhat inevitable, I am hoping for a mental shift toward sharpening my focus on our scientific objectives. After all, that is my reason for being here.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-map-of-ice-core-drilling-sites-in-antarctica-with-herc-dome-shown-in-red-borrowed-from-tj-fudgehttpsantarcticfudgesicleswordpresscom20181117hercules-dome-antarctica&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A map of ice core drilling sites in Antarctica with Herc Dome shown in red (borrowed from [T.J. Fudge](https://antarcticfudgesicles.wordpress.com/2018/11/17/hercules-dome-antarctica/)).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/going-south/hd-map_hue72b89f81990392c5429058996f26f48_43647_71f23b853006c34e2591dfde485d40f1.webp 400w,
               /blog/going-south/hd-map_hue72b89f81990392c5429058996f26f48_43647_a4546e1554ad45056d28353bcf19bed3.webp 760w,
               /blog/going-south/hd-map_hue72b89f81990392c5429058996f26f48_43647_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/going-south/hd-map_hue72b89f81990392c5429058996f26f48_43647_71f23b853006c34e2591dfde485d40f1.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;484&#34;
               height=&#34;417&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A map of ice core drilling sites in Antarctica with Herc Dome shown in red (borrowed from &lt;a href=&#34;https://antarcticfudgesicles.wordpress.com/2018/11/17/hercules-dome-antarctica/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;T.J. Fudge&lt;/a&gt;).
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our project at Herc Dome is tangent to my primary dissertation topic. I first learned about it when I started my PhD approximately 18 months ago because T.J. Fudge gave a talk at the 2017 West Antarctic Ice Sheet Workshop. T.J. and Eric Steig, another faculty in our department at the University of Washington, are interested in Herc Dome as the next drilling site for the US Ice Drilling Program. At the time of T.J.’s talk, this project had no secured funding line, but their ideas were maturing. I have since learned that ice core locations are intensely debated and that Herc Dome has been a highly endorsed candidate for over a decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice cores are useful for learning about past climate. Many have been drilled throughout both the Greenland and Antarctic ice sheets, but each serves a separate purpose. The first few cores to be drilled, like those at Dome C and Lake Vostock, gave us a baseline for atmospheric isotopes up to 800 thousand years ago. Consistent oscillations in those data confirm the existence of past climate cycles and are strongly linked to oscillations in the Earth&amp;rsquo;s orbit called Milankovitch cycles. Some of the more recent ice cores, like the West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS) Divide ice core, were drilled with the intention of obtaining high resolution information about the atmosphere in the most recent glacial/interglacial cycle (since the Eemian warm period ~120 thousand years ago). Learning how the ice sheets changed, and particularly the extent of  collapse, during the Eemian would give us valuable information about what the future’s warming climate will have in store for polar ice. Unfortunately, no Eemian ice was found at WAIS Divide because that location is melting at its bed, something that wasn&amp;rsquo;t known for certain before drilling started. While the WAIS Divide core was a valuable contribution in that it produced the highest resolution isotope data to date, the record only extends to 68 thousand years ago and therefore provides no information about possible collapse of West Antarctica during the Eemian.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-paleoclimate-data-from-three-ice-cores-and-an-oceanic-record-used-as-a-proxy-for-sea-level-change-taken-from-a-climate-review-paperhttpswwwclim-pastnet925252013&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Paleoclimate data from three ice cores and an oceanic record used as a proxy for sea-level change (taken from a [climate review paper](https://www.clim-past.net/9/2525/2013/))&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/going-south/IceCoreData_hu0803a4af1784c1df74d0ceb908763193_79889_9b44b828102dfe0850a6ae58535edf58.webp 400w,
               /blog/going-south/IceCoreData_hu0803a4af1784c1df74d0ceb908763193_79889_93ee3c3f2fab8bcbd1cf4e8dca55f99f.webp 760w,
               /blog/going-south/IceCoreData_hu0803a4af1784c1df74d0ceb908763193_79889_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/going-south/IceCoreData_hu0803a4af1784c1df74d0ceb908763193_79889_9b44b828102dfe0850a6ae58535edf58.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;640&#34;
               height=&#34;450&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Paleoclimate data from three ice cores and an oceanic record used as a proxy for sea-level change (taken from a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.clim-past.net/9/2525/2013/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;climate review paper&lt;/a&gt;)
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our ultimate objective for Herc Dome is to drill a new ice core which will hopefully extend through the Eemian and more rigorously address the nature of the West Antarctic Ice Sheet at that time. This site is at a critical location on an ice divide but between East and West Antarctica, which means that it will likely hold valuable information about flow between the two ice sheets especially in times of WAIS collapse. In preparation, this upcoming season is a pre-drilling geophysics campaign led by my advisor, Knut Christianson. We will use ice-penetrating radar to learn about the bed topography (among other things) and use that information to choose the exact location for the core, whether that be at the top of the dome or not. But how do we know what a ‘good’ ice-core location looks like from the radar data? We are looking for a place where the bottom of the ice sheet is cold (i.e. that it is not melting) because we want the old ice to be preserved. We also want a location where the internal reflectors are consistently flat so that we know the ice flow is relatively simple and has been consistent through time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only a handful of people have ever been to Herc Dome. As far as I know, none of the original explorers came through this way. Scott, Shackleton, and Amundsen all came from the Ross Sea sector but moved through the Transantarctic Mountains further north and ended up significantly east of Herc Dome. One previous science mission did come over the dome as a part of the ITASE traverse from Byrd Station to the South Pole. It was during this traverse that the scientific importance of Herc Dome was established. Bob Jacobel and his team (including Eric Steig) recognized what they thought might be a &amp;lsquo;Raymond Arch&amp;rsquo; within their radar data which would indicate that it is a good location for drilling. However, having only a few isolated transects, their evidence is not strong enough to say for certain what this feature is. That is a big part of the reason why we need to go back.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-getting-my-gear-ready-at-the-clothing-distribution-center-in-christchurch-new-zealand&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Getting my gear ready at the clothing distribution center in Christchurch, New Zealand.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/going-south/clothes_hu8ece794870e2fd8521c3b43a5cefa654_498152_1b186ac16a8b48d494d904b147185bde.webp 400w,
               /blog/going-south/clothes_hu8ece794870e2fd8521c3b43a5cefa654_498152_f3fe9be054356959a3f8db76b709758e.webp 760w,
               /blog/going-south/clothes_hu8ece794870e2fd8521c3b43a5cefa654_498152_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/going-south/clothes_hu8ece794870e2fd8521c3b43a5cefa654_498152_1b186ac16a8b48d494d904b147185bde.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;697&#34;
               height=&#34;695&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Getting my gear ready at the clothing distribution center in Christchurch, New Zealand.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said goodbye to friends and family, they unsurprisingly asked questions about what I have in store. Since this is my first trip South, I don’t feel entirely equipped to answer (hence my looming anxiety). Having said that, I have had extensive conversations with my advisor, helping him buy tools and equipment in preparation for the season, as well as many from the glaciology community at the University of Washington. Herc Dome is at 86.5°S, and 2610 m (8563 ft) elevation. This means that we will have sunlight at all times and that the air temperature is… well it is cold. The mean air temperature is -40°C, but these are the summer months so it will normally be a bit warmer. Antarctica is a huge desert, but the precipitation at Herc Dome is relatively high at 10 cm/yr ice equivalent (~1 m of snow). Even if it is not snowing often, wind and blowing snow will be common. Luckily, the awesome team at the US Antarctic Program issue us sufficient gear to stay cozy in the cold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will surely be busy doing science (or just as likely getting frustrated waiting for flights and trying to fix things that are broken) over the next couple months, but I will try to write a few of my thoughts down when I get the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Processes influencing heat transfer in the near-surface ice of Greenland&#39;s ablation zone</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/hills2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/hills2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sea-Level Fingerprinting</title>
      <link>https://example.com/blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Projections of sea-level rise from the International Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) 5th Assessment Report are daunting to say the least. Policy makers are most concerned about the changes coming in the next century, over which we could see up to a full meter of sea-level rise. Even under the best-case scenario, dramatically curbing emissions today, the oceans will rise considerably by year 2100 (see the figure below). Looking beyond that 100-year mark though, the rates of sea-level rise become much more uncertain. The largest uncertainty in future sea-level projections is that associated with dynamic losses from the West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS). Dynamic losses are those from speedup of the ice sheet, resulting in drawdown of interior ice and more calving into the ocean. Unlike ice melting, which pretty much scales linearly with the global air temperature, these dynamic losses could entirely eliminate an unstable ice sheet on the timescale of decades to centuries rather than millennia.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-historic-and-projected-sea-level-change-from-pre-industrial-1700-future-projections-are-for-shown-for-the-very-high-emission-scenario-red-and-the-very-low-emission-scenario-blueipcc-ar5httpwwwipccchreportar5wg1ulvpnh_ix8e&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Historic and projected sea-level change from pre-industrial (1700). Future projections are for shown for the very high emission scenario (red) and the very low emission scenario (blue). [IPCC AR5](http://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/#.UlvpNH_Ix8E)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/ipcc_ar5_13-27_hue4a9bb055a15b72671004250451c24ae_35173_5856d5a353079dbfde643b99970a308e.webp 400w,
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/ipcc_ar5_13-27_hue4a9bb055a15b72671004250451c24ae_35173_55bdff5ffb534d7a431336680ec5769d.webp 760w,
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/ipcc_ar5_13-27_hue4a9bb055a15b72671004250451c24ae_35173_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/ipcc_ar5_13-27_hue4a9bb055a15b72671004250451c24ae_35173_5856d5a353079dbfde643b99970a308e.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;589&#34;
               height=&#34;556&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Historic and projected sea-level change from pre-industrial (1700). Future projections are for shown for the very high emission scenario (red) and the very low emission scenario (blue). &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/#.UlvpNH_Ix8E&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IPCC AR5&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most simple way to think about the sea level in a non-steady condition is in the analogy with a large pool of water. When extra water is added to the pool, or if the water expands due to an increase in temperature, its average level will come up. This model of the mean, or &amp;rsquo;eustatic,&amp;rsquo; sea level is often termed the &amp;lsquo;bathtub model&amp;rsquo; because it is like thinking of the global oceans as a bathtub and the added water as a turn of the faucet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is useful to conceptualize the bathtub model for preliminary calculations, in reality, sea-level rise does not come in this globally-averaged sense. A visualization from NASA shows that the sea-level change that we have recorded with satellites over the last 23 years is variable throughout the Earth&amp;rsquo;s oceans. The most obvious sources for the regional variations in this visualization include shifts in ocean currents or natural oscillations in climate. There are even localized human influences on regional sea level such as the rapid subsidence of a coastal city like New Orleans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above examples of regional sea-level rise are relatively complicated to fully understand or to project into the future. However, a more systematic sea-level adjustment comes with any change in mass of an ice sheet. Not only does a decrease in ice-sheet mass mean more water into the ocean, and thus a change in the eustatic sea level, but the mass of an ice sheet has a regional control on sea level as well. Each ice sheet having its own unique signature, these regional controls are termed sea-level &amp;lsquo;fingerprints.&amp;rsquo; Sea-level fingerprints are the result of several physical processes acting together, and only recently they were directly measured for the first time using satellites. I briefly explain the physical processes of fingerprinting below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the Earth&amp;rsquo;s ice sheets are massive enough to attract the ocean toward them, much like the moon attracts the ocean to create tides. Therefore, if an ice sheet loses mass, the force with which it attracts the ocean toward it decreases and the local sea level falls nearby the ice sheet. If the ocean is to conserve water though (which it must), a local drop in sea level around the ice sheet means additional rise in sea level far away from the ice sheet. This idea of self-gravitation by the ice sheet mass is drawn out in the figure below.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-self-gravitation-of-an-ice-sheet-national-academies-presshttpswwwnapeduread18373chapter4&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Self-gravitation of an ice sheet. [National Academies Press](https://www.nap.edu/read/18373/chapter/4)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/selfgravitation-e1521560665946_hu59304f0243382091d904558f1d9bf9c5_102749_8b3d2f6100097ef6614a53c3ba5ac1ed.webp 400w,
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/selfgravitation-e1521560665946_hu59304f0243382091d904558f1d9bf9c5_102749_42dbaa00d3d92449c7d082e358921ceb.webp 760w,
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/selfgravitation-e1521560665946_hu59304f0243382091d904558f1d9bf9c5_102749_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/selfgravitation-e1521560665946_hu59304f0243382091d904558f1d9bf9c5_102749_8b3d2f6100097ef6614a53c3ba5ac1ed.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;592&#34;
               height=&#34;451&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Self-gravitation of an ice sheet. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nap.edu/read/18373/chapter/4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;National Academies Press&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the earth under an ice sheet is not completely &amp;lsquo;solid&amp;rsquo; in the sense that it would be unable to deform; on the contrary, the upper mantle flows viscously over long timescales, which permits the motion of tectonic plates. When a mass load (e.g. an ice sheet) is created on the surface of the Earth, the mantle viscously readjusts itself to that new state over the timescales of thousands of years. Likewise, when an ice sheet melts and disappears, the mantle fills in and the overlying crust subsequently rises up to its original elevation from before the presence of that mass load. This concept is called isostasy, and it is also important for relative sea-level rise. Today, previously glaciated regions such as the land around the Hudson Bay in Canada are still rising in elevation, or isostatically rebounding, by up to ~1 cm/yr as we come out of the last ice age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most recently developed in the scientific literature is a third physical process, where alterations in ice masses near the poles can change the manner in which the Earth rotates. We know that the rotation of the earth creates a centrifugal force that pushes more water out at the equator than at the poles. In a similar manner, the rock mass of the Earth itself has an equatorial bulge. However, the axis of rotation and the corresponding equator are not necessarily fixed. If one of the ice sheets melts, the planet will slightly adjust on its axis of rotation in a way that conserves angular momentum. This adjustment would redistribute some amount of water toward the new equator. Even if only adjusted slightly, this shift in rotation would dramatically effect the extent of sea-level rise at low latitudes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above factors add up to describe a different story for future (and past) sea-level rise depending on what the melt source is for water added to the ocean. The characteristics of a global ocean under collapse of the WAIS would look dramatically different from that under collapse of the Greenland Ice Sheet. Research today is using the sea-level fingerprints of each of the ice sheets to make inferences about the nature of ice sheet collapse in geologic history. Namely, that the WAIS most likely collapsed during the last interglacial period based on present-day high stands of corals around the world. Unfortunately, this evidence for historic WAIS collapse is particularly supportive of the potential for rapid dynamic losses in the near-future as mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-relative-sea-level-fingerprints-for-greenland-left-and-west-antarctica-right-the-scale-is-dimensionless-with-1-being-equal-to-the-eustatic-global-mean-sea-level-rise-and-negative-being-a-regional-drop-in-sea-level-hay-et-al-2015httpswwwnaturecomarticlesnature14093&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Relative sea-level fingerprints for Greenland (left) and West Antarctica (right). The scale is dimensionless, with 1 being equal to the eustatic (global mean) sea level rise and negative being a regional drop in sea level  [(Hay et al., 2015)](https://www.nature.com/articles/nature14093).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/fingerprints_hu78f147769a67a20b7fc9070ce9fb86f8_1463218_1eaebf29742993e6bb4fc2da22936160.webp 400w,
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/fingerprints_hu78f147769a67a20b7fc9070ce9fb86f8_1463218_f9d1c6596df1b83ec3d23aee16d10312.webp 760w,
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/fingerprints_hu78f147769a67a20b7fc9070ce9fb86f8_1463218_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/fingerprints_hu78f147769a67a20b7fc9070ce9fb86f8_1463218_1eaebf29742993e6bb4fc2da22936160.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;256&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Relative sea-level fingerprints for Greenland (left) and West Antarctica (right). The scale is dimensionless, with 1 being equal to the eustatic (global mean) sea level rise and negative being a regional drop in sea level  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature14093&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Hay et al., 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall effect of sea-level fingerprinting is sadly not in our favor. The figure above shows that the WAIS, which is the most likely to rapidly collapse in the near-future, could contribute to sea-level rise of greater than the global mean in the most densely populated regions of the world such as North America, Europe, and Eastern Asia. The take home point here is that we should be preparing for sea-level rise in a well educated manner. While city planners are beginning to incorporate a rising ocean into their assessments, they often use the misinformed global mean, whereas local estimates could be quite variable from that eustatic value.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crystalline Ice</title>
      <link>https://example.com/blog/crystalline-ice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/blog/crystalline-ice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Now suppose,&amp;rsquo; chortled Dr. Breed, enjoying himself, &amp;rsquo;that there were many possible ways in which water could crystallize, could freeze. Suppose that the sort of ice we skate upon and put into highballs&amp;ndash;what we might call ice-one&amp;ndash; is only one of several types of ice. Suppose water always froze as ice-one on Earth because it had never had a seed to teach it how to form ice-two, ice-three, ice-four&amp;hellip;? And suppose,&amp;rsquo; he rapped on his desk with his old hand again, &amp;rsquo;that there were one form, which we will call ice-nine&amp;ndash;a crystal as hard as this desk&amp;ndash;with a melting point of, let us say, one-hundred degrees Fahrenheit, or, better still, a melting point of one-hundred-and-thirty degrees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an excerpt from Kurt Vonnegut Jr.&amp;rsquo;s novel, Cat&amp;rsquo;s Cradle, in which he presents &amp;lsquo;ice-nine&amp;rsquo;, a crystalline form of water ice with the potential to destroy the world as we know it. Vonnegut&amp;rsquo;s ice-nine, which I will call ice IX for consistency with the scientific naming convention, is stable at room temperature, and the crystalline structure will propagate from a seed. Hence, when liquid water is brought into contact with an ice IX crystal, it spontaneously freezes as long as it is below the melting point of this crystalline phase, 113ºC. The societal implications for such a crystal are boundless, for if it came into contact with the Earth&amp;rsquo;s water cycle the entire planet would freeze over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The background for Vonnegut&amp;rsquo;s story is interesting. He was brought up in a scientific family, and a certain scientific style often shows through in his writing. The oldest brother, Bernard, was a physical chemist who, at the time, worked at General Electric (he actually helped Kurt get his first job at GE as well). For his work in atmospheric physics, Bernard was credited with discovering silver iodide cloud seeding, a technique that has widespread use today. Having a brother who studied ice nucleation interested Vonnegut in the phases of ice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, this novel was published in 1963 which was a highly contentious time in the history of weapons research. There was an imminent fear of soviet attack, so much scientific research was directed toward our nuclear arsenal and other weapons. Bernard&amp;rsquo;s research on cloud seeding even had military applications. However, many scientists, including Bernard, had ethical issues with working toward such a goal. The ice IX story plays with these ideas, highlighting the danger of global weapons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the ice IX of Cat&amp;rsquo;s Cradle is a fictional crystalline form, there truly are many distinct forms of water ice. In fact, one of the features that makes water unique is that it has nearly 20 crystalline phases that we know of, many more than most crystal-forming compounds. Most of these exist only in the laboratory, and all ice that we interact with on the Earth resides in one familiar crystalline phase called ice Ih.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;water-molecule&#34;&gt;Water Molecule&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to discuss crystal structure for phases of ice, we must first review the properties of the water molecule. Water, H2O, is made up of two hydrogen and one oxygen atom. We know this from, among several other experiments, electrolysis where H2O is split up into its constituents of H2 and O2 gases. In the water molecule, the electronegative oxygen atom shares its electrons with the hydrogen atoms in strong covalent bonds.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-water-molecule-has-two-hydrogen-and-one-oxygen-atom-the-angle-between-covalent-bonds-is-about-1045º-and-the-distance-from-the-oxygen-nucleus-to-hydrogen-is-about-1-angstrom&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The water molecule has two hydrogen and one oxygen atom. The angle between covalent bonds is about 104.5º and the distance from the oxygen nucleus to hydrogen is about 1 angstrom.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/crystalline-ice/watermolecule_hube666d9788fb7101f5181fd87be78acf_998764_93af586cc6f61a2bba9e330a413eacb2.webp 400w,
               /blog/crystalline-ice/watermolecule_hube666d9788fb7101f5181fd87be78acf_998764_cc4a37d413d576881933731fd587d3b8.webp 760w,
               /blog/crystalline-ice/watermolecule_hube666d9788fb7101f5181fd87be78acf_998764_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/crystalline-ice/watermolecule_hube666d9788fb7101f5181fd87be78acf_998764_93af586cc6f61a2bba9e330a413eacb2.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;578&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The water molecule has two hydrogen and one oxygen atom. The angle between covalent bonds is about 104.5º and the distance from the oxygen nucleus to hydrogen is about 1 angstrom.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly to the crystalline structure of ice, the electrons are not shared equally in the covalent bonds. The oxygen atoms hold on more closely to the electrons, which in turn creates an electric dipole for this molecule with the oxygen being the negative end and hydrogens positive. Because each molecule has its own dipole, there is some amount of electromagnetic attraction/repulsion between water molecules which ultimately controls many of the interesting properties that we commonly observe in the water substance. Most critically, the electromagnetic attraction between the negative oxygen and the positive hydrogen promotes hydrogen bonding between molecules. In a lattice, the hydrogen bonds determine the crystalline form of ice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ice-ih&#34;&gt;Ice Ih&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are four hydrogen bonding sites for each water molecule, one at each of the hydrogen atoms, and two additional sites at the &amp;rsquo;lone pairs&amp;rsquo; of electrons which are located on the opposite side of the oxygen atom from the hydrogens. The four bonding sites promote a tetrahedral structure for stacking in ice crystals. Because of the angles between bonds in the tetrahedron, ice crystals form as a series of crinkled sheets each as a tessellation of open hexagons. We call these sheets the basal planes and they are stacked along the &amp;lsquo;c-axis&amp;rsquo; which is orthogonal to the surface of the basal plane. In the ice crystal that we are familiar with, ice Ih, the sheets stack nicely on top of one another, alternating their crinkled pattern A-B-A-B. In this crystal, the hexagonal form in the basal plane is consistent throughout, creating a hexagonal column in three dimensions, hence the &amp;lsquo;h&amp;rsquo; in ice Ih. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hydrogen atoms within an ice crystal do not always face up along the c-axis, and they do not always stay in the basal plane, they are disordered. Disorder as well as small impurities in the crystal, or &amp;lsquo;dislocations&amp;rsquo;, explain many of the properties of ice, such as its mechanical, thermal, and some of its electrical properties. Considering the disorder in the ice Ih crystal, Nobel laureate Linus Pauling theorized that ice has some amount of residual entropy at zero Kelvin, meaning that the disorder would maintain even to the lowest possible temperature. His theory was later confirmed by calorimetry experiments in which changes in entropy were inferred by applying heat to ice and measuring the temperature change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;alternate-forms&#34;&gt;Alternate Forms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At low pressure there are two other forms of the ice crystal. The first is ice XI which is ordered, meaning that it would in fact have have zero entropy at 0K. If ice Ih were held at a low enough energy state (below 72K) for a long enough time, the water molecules would eventually order themselves into ice XI. The third low-pressure ice crystal is technically in the same category as ice Ih, but it is a cubic crystal rather than hexagonal, so it is termed ice Ic. This crystal does naturally form in the Earth&amp;rsquo;s atmosphere when clouds are very cold (below ~170K or -100ºC).&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-phase-diagram-of-water-over-a-large-range-of-temperatures-and-pressures-sourcehttpswebhomephydukeeduhsg363table-imageswater-phase-diagramhtml&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Phase diagram of water over a large range of temperatures and pressures. [Source](https://webhome.phy.duke.edu/~hsg/363/table-images/water-phase-diagram.html)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/crystalline-ice/phase-diagram_hu36918e10f8af4dbaf69be9e919579f3c_235863_c56671314f618958244f0c7ca94ba0c6.webp 400w,
               /blog/crystalline-ice/phase-diagram_hu36918e10f8af4dbaf69be9e919579f3c_235863_354d8e3074dafe7b6f00ddc555ca4445.webp 760w,
               /blog/crystalline-ice/phase-diagram_hu36918e10f8af4dbaf69be9e919579f3c_235863_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/crystalline-ice/phase-diagram_hu36918e10f8af4dbaf69be9e919579f3c_235863_c56671314f618958244f0c7ca94ba0c6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;510&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Phase diagram of water over a large range of temperatures and pressures. &lt;a href=&#34;https://webhome.phy.duke.edu/~hsg/363/table-images/water-phase-diagram.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remaining ice phases all form at high pressure (on the order of GPa or greater, which is 10,000 times atmospheric pressure). At these high pressures, the bond angles in the water molecule can bend in order to achieve a higher density crystal. These high pressure phases are more dense than ice Ih and would sink in water. While the pressures on the Earth&amp;rsquo;s surface are much too low to achieve any of these crystalline forms, it has been hypothesized that they might exist deep in the Earth where pressures are extremely high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, Vonnegut was somewhat prescient in writing about ice IX, but he never intended to describe a real ice crystal. His ice IX was an analogy for weaponized science during the cold war. While the ice IX that we know today is only stable at very high pressures and low temperatures, the analogy still holds, especially as North Korea continues to push their nuclear agenda forward and President Trump proposes increased military spending.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greenland Ice Sheet Ablation Zone</title>
      <link>https://example.com/blog/ablation-zone/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/blog/ablation-zone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From 2015 to 2017 I was a graduate student at the University of Montana. While there, my research focused on heat transfer in Greenland&amp;rsquo;s ablation zone. I was fortunate in getting to experience this place, which up to now has been the most awe inspiring and the most intellectually fascinating place I have ever been. Spending approximately a month of time on the ice (over two separate summers) I learned how to work in such an environment, and specifically how to extract information from one of the most influential natural systems on our planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ice-sheet-basics&#34;&gt;Ice Sheet Basics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice forms on the Earth&amp;rsquo;s surface in places where more snow falls in the winter than melts in the summer. Typically, this means at either high elevation or high latitude, both of which are landscapes generally void of dense human populations. While it is easy for most of us to think of these as abstract places having no impact on our daily lives, as early as the 1960s scientists were warning of the potential for global influence by the Earth&amp;rsquo;s ice sheets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we appreciate the scale for the importance of the Earth&amp;rsquo;s cryosphere, we are investing more time and energy into researching these environments. We are learning that the large ice systems are a sort of barometer for the climate system. When the climate is stable, the ice sheets will conserve mass, with equal flux in at the top to flux out at the bottom. The flux in comes from precipitation at high elevation and compaction of snow into ice. Eventually, that ice flows downhill and either the warm air temperatures melt the ice or it meets the ocean and &amp;lsquo;calves&amp;rsquo;, floating away as an iceberg (both melting and calving are outward fluxes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This dichotomy of inward and outward fluxes is described in terms of accumulation of mass and ablation (melting). The conceptual model of an ice sheet (below) has an accumulation zone where more ice is formed from precipitation than is melted, and the ablation zone where more ice is lost to melting than is formed. Assessing this mass balance of an ice sheet has become a staple in the science of glaciology and provides a lot of information, not only about the health of an individual glacier or ice sheet, but about the global climate system.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-in-the-accumulation-zone-more-ice-accumulates-from-snowfall-than-melts-alternatively-in-the-ablation-zone-the-entire-winter-snowpack-as-well-as-some-amount-of-ice-all-melts-during-the-summer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;In the accumulation zone, more ice accumulates from snowfall than melts. Alternatively, in the ablation zone, the entire winter snowpack as well as some amount of ice all melts during the summer.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ablation-zone/accabl_hua021b37d7b32ea2a52939f9d359e088c_26655654_38277dd4e9fae0d15b54a8b4d033e791.webp 400w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/accabl_hua021b37d7b32ea2a52939f9d359e088c_26655654_a6a06fe01ee718d50ea14dc27d65dff7.webp 760w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/accabl_hua021b37d7b32ea2a52939f9d359e088c_26655654_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/ablation-zone/accabl_hua021b37d7b32ea2a52939f9d359e088c_26655654_38277dd4e9fae0d15b54a8b4d033e791.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;253&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      In the accumulation zone, more ice accumulates from snowfall than melts. Alternatively, in the ablation zone, the entire winter snowpack as well as some amount of ice all melts during the summer.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two ice sheets on this planet, Greenland and Antarctica, are unique in several ways. Importantly, these ice sheets are at different latitudes, the Antarctic being considerably further from the equator, and as a consequence much colder and larger. The Antarctic Ice Sheet contains approximately 30 million cubic meters (60 m sea level equivalent), while the Greenland Ice Sheet is only about one tenth of that. Because the Antarctic Ice Sheet is in a colder environment, it does not lose mass to melting, only to calving, and it therefore has no ablation zone. Greenland, on the other hand, has a rather large ablation zone, meaning that a significant portion of its mass loss can be attributed to surface melting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-project-in-the-ablation-zone&#34;&gt;Our Project in the Ablation Zone&lt;/h2&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-location-of-our-field-area-in-southwest-greenland&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The location of our field area in southwest Greenland.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ablation-zone/isunninset_hu7494ad9600d4a9895c52f1b8717378bc_752443_afa3cb44f4c4f908cbb825e90c092a06.webp 400w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/isunninset_hu7494ad9600d4a9895c52f1b8717378bc_752443_5c1008b66f404d21b9edf919b4b5bdd5.webp 760w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/isunninset_hu7494ad9600d4a9895c52f1b8717378bc_752443_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/ablation-zone/isunninset_hu7494ad9600d4a9895c52f1b8717378bc_752443_afa3cb44f4c4f908cbb825e90c092a06.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;537&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The location of our field area in southwest Greenland.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland&amp;rsquo;s ablation zone is important because the ice sheet is rapidly losing ice from increased melting. Unfortunately, this area has not been intensely studied because only Greenland, and not Antarctica, has an ablation zone. Hence, we have a somewhat novice understanding of what makes the ablation zone unique, that being primarily the presence of liquid water. When ice melts at the surface, the meltwater flows downhill and forms a branching network of streams. Those streams eventually terminate in either a supraglacial lake, resting on the ice surface, or a moulin, which is a large shaft that brings water from the surface to the base of the ice sheet. Recent work in the ablation zone has shown that this meltwater influences the way in which ice flows, both through warming the ice and through lubricating the bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The science project that brought me to Greenland was focused on these alterations to flow in the ablation zone. Our primary objective was to drill hot-water boreholes into the ice sheet, in order to measure internal properties of the ice including temperature, shear strain, water pressure at the bed, etc. Using this data, we would partition the flow of the ice sheet into its two main constituents, viscous deformation and pure shear (sliding over the bedrock substrate). I should note that this project was already fully developed by the time I joined and never would happened without the hard work of many individuals at both the University of Montana and the University of Wyoming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-primer-on-hot-water-drilling&#34;&gt;A Primer on Hot-Water Drilling&lt;/h2&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-our-research-team-getting-the-hot-water-drill-started-on-the-morning-of-a-drilling-day&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Our research team getting the hot-water drill started on the morning of a drilling day.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ablation-zone/hot-water_hud56757ca3a027ba70972e9f698a2c263_207670_c997d1f069c56f21f27885347a87d914.webp 400w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/hot-water_hud56757ca3a027ba70972e9f698a2c263_207670_c0f26f802120b22e054689e4d069d56a.webp 760w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/hot-water_hud56757ca3a027ba70972e9f698a2c263_207670_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/ablation-zone/hot-water_hud56757ca3a027ba70972e9f698a2c263_207670_c997d1f069c56f21f27885347a87d914.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;712&#34;
               height=&#34;474&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Our research team getting the hot-water drill started on the morning of a drilling day.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two main approaches to drilling in ice. Typically, when I tell people that my research involves drilling boreholes in Greenland, they assume that I am drilling &amp;lsquo;mechanical&amp;rsquo; holes in order to extract ice cores. In fact, our methodology is quite the opposite. A hot-water drill melts a hole in the ice, leaving space so that we can put things into the ice sheet. One can think of a hot-water drill as a hose, which sprays very hot (~80ºC) and highly pressurized (~1100 psi) water. With this hose, we can drill through the thickness of the ice sheet, ~500-1000 m, in less than a day. In total, we drilled something like 35 holes to the bed of the ice sheet in the ablation zone, instrumenting each one with electronics.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-open-borehole-with-cables-for-our-electronics-descending-into-the-ice-sheet&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The open borehole with cables for our electronics descending into the ice sheet.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/ablation-zone/hole_hu5ca122fbc12e048477b3e4e646571db0_126123_785a87c751b34a323d9b826a7587b75a.webp 400w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/hole_hu5ca122fbc12e048477b3e4e646571db0_126123_f161110c9794a3eb44143a32d56b43e3.webp 760w,
               /blog/ablation-zone/hole_hu5ca122fbc12e048477b3e4e646571db0_126123_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/ablation-zone/hole_hu5ca122fbc12e048477b3e4e646571db0_126123_785a87c751b34a323d9b826a7587b75a.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;708&#34;
               height=&#34;471&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The open borehole with cables for our electronics descending into the ice sheet.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data&#34;&gt;Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The focus of our measurements is to understand the physical behavior of ice in this area. We want to know how the ice is moving and what is forcing it to move in the way that it does. Ice motion is subdivided into two categories, and we have measurements that pertain to each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, ice moves through internal deformation, which is facilitated by both inter-crystal and intra-crystal creep. In order to understand this deformation in a bulk sense, we measure the deformation of the ice at different points along a profile from the surface of the ice sheet to the bed. We also measure ice temperature along this profile, which controls how quickly the ice deforms. Secondly, ice moves by sliding over its bed. This is only true in areas where the bed is at the melting point and partially melted, and one such area happens to be Greenland&amp;rsquo;s ablation zone. To constrain this sliding motion, we measure properties at the bed including water pressure and the composition of the subglacial till. Finally, we directly measure the ice velocity using GPS stations installed into the ice at the surface. With these velocity measurements, we place all of our other data into context by correlating speedups to variations in the internal and basal state of the ice sheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-science&#34;&gt;The Science&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our measurements, along with those of others working in the area, have resulted in the development of ice mechanics theory in the ablation zone. We now know that ice motion is primarily by sliding over what we think is a solid bed. We know that the thermal structure of the ice sheet is much more complicated than we originally thought, which could lead to complexities in ice flow. We know that the basal drainage system consists of large conduits near the ice sheet margin, but these likely do not propagate far inward toward regions of thicker ice. Looking to the future, it will be important to continue to research how the ablation zone will change, whether it will grow and promote the melting of more ice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measured horizontal temperature gradients constrain heat transfer mechanisms in Greenland ice</title>
      <link>https://example.com/publication/hills2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/publication/hills2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://example.com/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
