<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Benjamin Hills</title>
    <link>https://example.com/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://example.com/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://example.com/media/icon_hu9514fa0e347f2b799933f532dc1945ad_152873_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cryo Geophysics</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/cryo-geophysics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/project/cryo-geophysics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;impdar&#34;&gt;ImpDAR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ImpDAR (Impulse raDAR) is a suite of processing and interpretation tools for impulse radar sounding. The software (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dlilien/ImpDAR&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;hosted on github&lt;/a&gt;) is targeted for ice-penetrating radar applications but usable for ground-penetrating radar and associated surveying applications as well. The core processing steps and general terminology come from a set of Matlab scripts developed at St. Olaf College under Dr. Robert Jacobel. Here, everything has been re-written in Python and significant improvements to speed, readability, documentation, and interface have been made across the board. Additionally, ImpDAR is intended to be more flexible than other available options. Support is gradually being added for a variety of file formats. Currently, GSSI, PulseEKKO, GPRMax, SEGY, and several custom file formats are supported. Available processing steps include various filtering operations, trivial modifications such as restacking, cropping, or reversing data, geolocation-related operations like interpolating to constant trace spacing, and various migration routines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to processing, ImpDAR can also be used for interpreting radargrams (i.e. picking layers). Picking is generally an interactive process, so there is a GUI for carrying out the semi-automated picking procedure. Each picked layer is saved with variables for both the depth and picked power (i.e. the root-mean-square amplitude). The GUI also allows for basic processing steps, with the updates happening to the plot in real time to aid the picking process. We are also developing an automated picking algorithm that will ideally pick both internal layers and the bed reflector.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/cryo-geophysics/layer-interpretation_hube5f12825a8c46f8fd63167a1dbd1ae4_349398_35481a88845e3d15a3f736c9c58b3a8c.webp 400w,
               /project/cryo-geophysics/layer-interpretation_hube5f12825a8c46f8fd63167a1dbd1ae4_349398_d10d4dc68ef138846c8f52375b9f1a97.webp 760w,
               /project/cryo-geophysics/layer-interpretation_hube5f12825a8c46f8fd63167a1dbd1ae4_349398_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/cryo-geophysics/layer-interpretation_hube5f12825a8c46f8fd63167a1dbd1ae4_349398_35481a88845e3d15a3f736c9c58b3a8c.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;750&#34;
               height=&#34;750&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ApRES (Autonomous phase-sensitive Radio Echo Sounder) is a new and popular tool within the glaciology community. It is a pulse-compression radar that transmits a phase-coherent waveform, so repeat acquisitions can be used for interference in order to measure small changes in returned phase. Phase changes are associated either with a difference in the total distance that the wave travels or differences in the wave speed through the medium. We are actively developing an ImpDAR extension for ApRES processing, called &amp;lsquo;ApDAR&amp;rsquo;. We preserve a similar data structure to the impulse data, so users will have some familiarity across the two.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-repeat-apres-acquisition-showing-motion-phase-offset-of-measured-reflectors&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Repeat ApRES acquisition, showing motion (phase offset) of measured reflectors.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/cryo-geophysics/pres_hu847edfb215e0444d8ce3ecd2fe00402b_56497_5ca1cae0709d5aa41c41dbaf70d33a25.webp 400w,
               /project/cryo-geophysics/pres_hu847edfb215e0444d8ce3ecd2fe00402b_56497_a9789dea67f75c3931103264078511bd.webp 760w,
               /project/cryo-geophysics/pres_hu847edfb215e0444d8ce3ecd2fe00402b_56497_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/cryo-geophysics/pres_hu847edfb215e0444d8ce3ecd2fe00402b_56497_5ca1cae0709d5aa41c41dbaf70d33a25.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;640&#34;
               height=&#34;480&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Repeat ApRES acquisition, showing motion (phase offset) of measured reflectors.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ApDAR is built to be modular so that various ApRES acquisition techniques can be loaded and processed. One such technique is radar polarimetry, where the antennas are intentionally polarized in one direction or another to pick out differences in the material properties of the ice, namely the ice-crystal orientation fabric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;seidart&#34;&gt;SeiDarT&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SeiDarT (Seismic-Radar Toolbox) is a full-waveform geophysical modeling package meant for both seismic and radar applications (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/UMainedynamics/SeidarT&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;hosted on github&lt;/a&gt;). Again, the majority of the development is with ice in mind as the primary media, but the tool could be used for other materials as well. This package was primarily developed by Steven Bernsen and Christopher Gerbi at the University of Maine.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34;
           src=&#34;https://example.com/project/cryo-geophysics/Ex.gif&#34;
           loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable width=&#34;50%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ice Sheet Properties &amp; Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/ice-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/project/ice-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Temperatures of glacier ice range from ~ -60-0°C, which corresponds to a viscosity range over three orders of magnitude. Ice is generally warmest at the glacier bed, being heated by the energy flux from the solid Earth, and coldest near the glacier surface where ice is in equilibrium with the mean air temperature. Heat moves between those two boundaries through the processes of diffusion (spreading out) and advection (transport by flow of the ice itself). Because the length scale for thermal diffusion in ice is long, deviations in ice temperature can be preserved for thousands of years.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-characteristic-length-scale-of-thermal-diffusion-in-ice-temperature-variations-can-be-persistent-for-hundreds-of-years-in-alpine-glaciers-and-for-thousands-to-even-tens-of-thousands-of-years-in-the-greenland-and-antarctic-ice-sheets&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Characteristic length scale of thermal diffusion in ice. Temperature variations can be persistent for hundreds of years in alpine glaciers and for thousands to even tens of thousands of years in the Greenland and Antarctic Ice Sheets.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/ice-dynamics/length-scale_hue1f45e5cc90b3a8e94fc86f455d4a964_22870_beac3cb7e04314905bfd229bb30c6295.webp 400w,
               /project/ice-dynamics/length-scale_hue1f45e5cc90b3a8e94fc86f455d4a964_22870_c204d6e1207e3840b8d602147ce60bdd.webp 760w,
               /project/ice-dynamics/length-scale_hue1f45e5cc90b3a8e94fc86f455d4a964_22870_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/ice-dynamics/length-scale_hue1f45e5cc90b3a8e94fc86f455d4a964_22870_beac3cb7e04314905bfd229bb30c6295.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;50%&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Characteristic length scale of thermal diffusion in ice. Temperature variations can be persistent for hundreds of years in alpine glaciers and for thousands to even tens of thousands of years in the Greenland and Antarctic Ice Sheets.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We measure ice temperature directly by drilling into it, installing in-situ instrumentation, and letting the hole freeze in on the instruments. The heat from drilling dissipates on the order of ~months and thereafter instruments measure the representative temperature. Ice-temperature measurements made at slow-moving, accumulation-dominated, ice divide locations (e.g. Greenland Ice Core Project, WAIS Divide) can be used to infer past air temperatures. The past climate is preserved within the ice because the frequency of those climate changes is within the time scale for thermal diffusion. We also measure temperature deviations within the faster moving ice-stream shear margins (more below) and the melt-dominated ablation zone. In the ablation zone, surface meltwater is plentifully available and transports latent heat when it penetrates into a crevasse or through a moulin to the ice-sheet bed.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-ice-temperature-deviations-measured-in-a-cube-of-greenland-ice&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Ice temperature deviations measured in a cube of Greenland ice.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/ice-dynamics/ice-block_hu88810bf04c8ced369e3c62ff4c9f9c8c_2995205_26b6469ab0c4684537525001fa150720.webp 400w,
               /project/ice-dynamics/ice-block_hu88810bf04c8ced369e3c62ff4c9f9c8c_2995205_7750f8614013696d646369f2266b5f8e.webp 760w,
               /project/ice-dynamics/ice-block_hu88810bf04c8ced369e3c62ff4c9f9c8c_2995205_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/ice-dynamics/ice-block_hu88810bf04c8ced369e3c62ff4c9f9c8c_2995205_26b6469ab0c4684537525001fa150720.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;570&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Ice temperature deviations measured in a cube of Greenland ice.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In highly dynamic areas, heat is generated within the ice column through friction as the ice defoms. Warmer ice means a lower viscosity, more deformation, and thus more heat production, creating a positive feedback loop. Some studies even argue that much of the ice in an ice-stream shear margin is at the pressure-melting point. We found that this feedback is suppressed by cold ice moving through the system, ice that was source from higher and colder regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;













&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-whillans-ice-stream-drainage-area-downstream-gradients-in-the-parameters-that-effect-ice-temperature&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Whillans Ice Stream drainage area. Downstream gradients in the parameters that effect ice temperature.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/ice-dynamics/whillans_drainage_hu5bb213718131f03a3ed25d13a029632c_667865_6aa2b60f4c45dd69d3eca84dc021aa2b.webp 400w,
               /project/ice-dynamics/whillans_drainage_hu5bb213718131f03a3ed25d13a029632c_667865_864c74954cf23094136a41a43a2534b8.webp 760w,
               /project/ice-dynamics/whillans_drainage_hu5bb213718131f03a3ed25d13a029632c_667865_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/ice-dynamics/whillans_drainage_hu5bb213718131f03a3ed25d13a029632c_667865_6aa2b60f4c45dd69d3eca84dc021aa2b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;228&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Whillans Ice Stream drainage area. Downstream gradients in the parameters that effect ice temperature.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-modeled-ice-temperatures-using-gradients-like-those-above&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Modeled ice temperatures using gradients like those above.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/ice-dynamics/siple_temps_hu36bf039a3ad77098d34b3fcd6c8adaaa_637575_6b9e0b305d76b6655608848ad5185d75.webp 400w,
               /project/ice-dynamics/siple_temps_hu36bf039a3ad77098d34b3fcd6c8adaaa_637575_1cd70c154c5ac692a548edfe5199b10a.webp 760w,
               /project/ice-dynamics/siple_temps_hu36bf039a3ad77098d34b3fcd6c8adaaa_637575_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/ice-dynamics/siple_temps_hu36bf039a3ad77098d34b3fcd6c8adaaa_637575_6b9e0b305d76b6655608848ad5185d75.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;338&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Modeled ice temperatures using gradients like those above.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;radar-attenuation&#34;&gt;Radar Attenuation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice temperature can theoretically be measured remotely using radar attenuation. Attenuation is the result of energy absorption through electrical conduction which is temperature dependent. The function is in the form of an Arrhenius relation,&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/ice-dynamics/proton-conduction_huc8f271ddbbce851b3f8210b343fac367_195467_b816286980811cb7f00d3d12057bf08e.webp 400w,
               /project/ice-dynamics/proton-conduction_huc8f271ddbbce851b3f8210b343fac367_195467_71be4f756686cf692167855bcadead6e.webp 760w,
               /project/ice-dynamics/proton-conduction_huc8f271ddbbce851b3f8210b343fac367_195467_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/ice-dynamics/proton-conduction_huc8f271ddbbce851b3f8210b343fac367_195467_b816286980811cb7f00d3d12057bf08e.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;50%&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empirical results for radar attenuation are generally dependent on the radar system and the empirical method used. Here, I show a result that we found in a single ground-based radar transect that traverses 200 km down the Kamb Ice Stream and up onto Siple Dome. We interpret the reflected power of the wave reflected off the ice-bed interface and calculate attenuation rate as the change in measured bed power with ice thickness. Essentially, if the wave travels through more ice we should measure a weaker return and the rate at which that measured power attenuates is temperature dependent.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hydro Geophysics</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/hydro-geophysics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/project/hydro-geophysics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nuclear-magnetic-resonance&#34;&gt;Nuclear Magnetic Resonance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geophysical nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) uses the same technology as a medical MRI. It is the only geophysical method that directly detects water rather than inferring its presence from other properties like electrical conductivity. The technique can either be done non-invasively, by deploying a loop of wire at the ground surface, or through logging of existing wells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The method works by exploiting the magnetic properties of hydrogen nuclei in water molecules. Those nuclei are polarized in a magnetic field (sometimes using the Earth&amp;rsquo;s natural magnetic field), then forced to resonate with a transmitted pulse at a specific radio frequency (the Larmor frequency). The measured NMR signal, decay of that resonance over time, gives information about the in situ water content, pore-size distribution, and other hydrogeological properties such as hydraulic conductivity.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/hydro-geophysics/WSP_ben_gmr_hu313361485b1d7b6a9a58ffc4f9dc468d_315374_a2ba80ef640f6a05fc69c851eb9db2ff.webp 400w,
               /project/hydro-geophysics/WSP_ben_gmr_hu313361485b1d7b6a9a58ffc4f9dc468d_315374_05301423cddb4c39a73716f8210e6e30.webp 760w,
               /project/hydro-geophysics/WSP_ben_gmr_hu313361485b1d7b6a9a58ffc4f9dc468d_315374_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/hydro-geophysics/WSP_ben_gmr_hu313361485b1d7b6a9a58ffc4f9dc468d_315374_a2ba80ef640f6a05fc69c851eb9db2ff.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;100%&#34;
               height=&#34;596&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;electromagnetic-methods&#34;&gt;Electromagnetic Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time-domain electromagnetic (TEM) sounding, also called transient electromagnetic method, is a widely used geophysical technique for mapping subsurface electrical conductivity, which makes it particularly valuable for hydrogeological investigations. The method works by inducing electromagnetic fields in the subsurface and measuring the decay of those fields over time. A transmitter loop laid on the ground surface sends a pulse of electrical current, creating a primary magnetic field. When the current is abruptly shut off, this collapsing magnetic field induces eddy currents in conductive subsurface materials. These eddy currents generate their own secondary magnetic fields that gradually decay. A receiver coil measures this decay signal, and because deeper currents take longer to diffuse and decay, the time-varying response provides information about conductivity at different depths.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/hydro-geophysics/Ky_TEM_hu01c48f652d9f16a64b129975a391b562_633273_04002f3ebc0d7ec5ba2b56c3f1da60c3.webp 400w,
               /project/hydro-geophysics/Ky_TEM_hu01c48f652d9f16a64b129975a391b562_633273_2cd43a9f048d73cd7e06c66a225eff22.webp 760w,
               /project/hydro-geophysics/Ky_TEM_hu01c48f652d9f16a64b129975a391b562_633273_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/hydro-geophysics/Ky_TEM_hu01c48f652d9f16a64b129975a391b562_633273_04002f3ebc0d7ec5ba2b56c3f1da60c3.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;100%&#34;
               height=&#34;572&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Planetary</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/planetary/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/project/planetary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pingos-and-permafrost&#34;&gt;Pingos and Permafrost&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pingo is a large ice-cored hill or mound that forms in permafrost regions, creating distinctive dome-shaped landforms that can reach heights of 3 to 70 meters and diameters of up to several hundred meters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two main types of pingos based on how they form. Hydrostatic (closed-system) pingos, also called Mackenzie-type pingos after their abundance in Canada&amp;rsquo;s Mackenzie Delta, form when lakes drain or shallow water bodies fill in. The ground beneath the former lake refreezes, but a pocket of unfrozen saturated sediment (talik) remains trapped beneath. As permafrost encroaches from all sides, it compresses this trapped water, increasing pore pressure and forcing water upward. This water then freezes, creating an expanding ice core that heaves the surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hydraulic (open-system) pingos, or East Greenland-type, form where groundwater under artesian pressure moves through taliks beneath or within permafrost. When this pressurized water reaches the surface or near-surface, it freezes and accumulates as an ice core. These often form on slopes or valley bottoms where groundwater can flow from higher elevations.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/planetary/ibyuk_photo_huff484b46316dbbf0ff5b4ea932cd3378_3678507_e46cb14f3190b96dfacf46cdf864f0c0.webp 400w,
               /project/planetary/ibyuk_photo_huff484b46316dbbf0ff5b4ea932cd3378_3678507_abbcd5d19cfd8806f0ab885096272705.webp 760w,
               /project/planetary/ibyuk_photo_huff484b46316dbbf0ff5b4ea932cd3378_3678507_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/planetary/ibyuk_photo_huff484b46316dbbf0ff5b4ea932cd3378_3678507_e46cb14f3190b96dfacf46cdf864f0c0.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;573&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Snow, Glaciers, &amp; Alpine Hydrology</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/alpine-glaciology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/project/alpine-glaciology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Much of the original theory in glaciology came from work on alpine glaciers, mostly in Europe. This is partially because of their relative proximity to human civilizations, but also becuase until recently we thought that the polar ice sheets operated on millenial timescales, too long to be of immenent concern. It was only around the turn of the century that the glaciological community started to recognize key instabilities within the ice sheets that can be triggered much faster, on the order of decades to centuries. While alpine glaciers have since gotten less attention in terms of sea-level focused research publications and grant funding, they are still critical for water supply, temperature, and chemistry, especially in alpine environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ice-dynamics&#34;&gt;Ice Dynamics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We study alpine glacier dynamics using various tools and techniques. As an example, we use a ground-based radar interferometer at the north face of Mt. Baker. We repeatedly scan the mountain face every 2 minutes for several days and by comparing the phase return between scans can tell how objects in the field of view are moving. This is much like the ApRES measurement described in &lt;a href=&#34;https://example.com/project/cryo-geophysics/&#34;&gt;Cryo Geophysics&lt;/a&gt; but many different reflections from across a range of azimuths.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/alpine-glaciology/baker_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_456965_827fc8f41bf89976f4976ed5e44643c0.webp 400w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/baker_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_456965_a47e3ade094309f58f304ad911e78f18.webp 760w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/baker_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_456965_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/alpine-glaciology/baker_hu284d939a3cc125d20c5fd77c3e290803_456965_827fc8f41bf89976f4976ed5e44643c0.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with Dr. Peter Neff of the University of Minnesota, we are surveying Combatant Col in preparation for an ice core to be drilled there in summer 2023. This is a radar survey which includes not only measurements of the ice geometry, but also repeat measurements to investigate a perennial firn aquifer and to understand how the ice is flowing.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/alpine-glaciology/waddington_surveying_hue0bab21f1beaed078012c0d9ee9e2341_6008249_f715a590510380780e8de29af359a301.webp 400w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/waddington_surveying_hue0bab21f1beaed078012c0d9ee9e2341_6008249_8535491999195f0719e48c6861779ccd.webp 760w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/waddington_surveying_hue0bab21f1beaed078012c0d9ee9e2341_6008249_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/alpine-glaciology/waddington_surveying_hue0bab21f1beaed078012c0d9ee9e2341_6008249_f715a590510380780e8de29af359a301.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;346&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mass-balance&#34;&gt;Mass Balance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States Geological Survey (USGS) has a surveying outpost at four alpine glaciers, Sperry Glacier in Montana, Wolverine and Gulkana Glaciers in Alaska, and South Cascade Glacier in Washington. For decades, they have been tracking the mass balance, the amount of ice added by snow and removed by melting. Understanding how these USGS ‘benchmark’ glaciers are changing over decadal timescales is helping us understand the regional influence of climate change. Our research group at UW works in collaboration with scientists at USGS, including Dr. Caitlyn Florentine and others, doing field campaigns to collect data for surveying these glaciers, especially at our local South Cascade Glacier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measuring glacier mass balance is relatively simple. For inputs, we drill a snow core or dig a snow pit at the end of the winter season and measure the total depth as well as density through the column. Together, depth and density give us an input balance in units of snow water equivalent (SWE). For outputs, we drill a metal stake into the ice at the beginning of summer and observe how much it has melted out by the end. Again, this measurement will be in SWE. Then the balance inputs (accumulation) and outputs (ablation) are summed to quantify glacier change. At South Cascade, the average mass balance over the past 50 years has been about -0.5 m/yr over the extent of the glacier’s area (Rasmussen and Conway, 2001; fig. 10).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;













&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/alpine-glaciology/snow-pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_6b0ea882f61214c227913e302f30bdbd.webp 400w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/snow-pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_5c47e78f58e87dac9c35ebe8f03508e7.webp 760w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/snow-pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/alpine-glaciology/snow-pit_hufbb8dc8af21203b24f648026c9457cdf_108650_6b0ea882f61214c227913e302f30bdbd.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/alpine-glaciology/density_hu3f7236b7fdca2276b75c71ce23cc382b_207829_ca42cb50c7145ad115977f5be3c47949.webp 400w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/density_hu3f7236b7fdca2276b75c71ce23cc382b_207829_2e41a6b6315ece17bfac126de900ce03.webp 760w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/density_hu3f7236b7fdca2276b75c71ce23cc382b_207829_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/alpine-glaciology/density_hu3f7236b7fdca2276b75c71ce23cc382b_207829_ca42cb50c7145ad115977f5be3c47949.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;574&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conventional mass balance methods described above are still in use for many glaciers today, including a continuing record for South Cascade Glacier. Being glacier geophysicists though, we are interested in developing more innovative ways to measure the inputs and outputs for the system. In particular, we are using ice-penetrating radar to get a distributed snow depth measurement at the end of the winter season. The hope is not to abandon the snow coring completely, but to use the two in parallel to build a more robust, and glacier wide, observation for snow inputs to the glacier system. With radar, we can easily see a reflection of the previous summer’s surface (giving the total snow depth accumulated over the winter season), but in some areas we can also see deeper reflections from multi-year snow (firn) layers. Firn observations could provide insight into the mechanisms for accumulation in this alpine setting including avalanching and wind-blown snow.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/alpine-glaciology/SCG_Panel_Map_hu1c16bbbe2e5dc55abb81abf305f056cd_1802779_0042bc5172d2e3a3539b00c912b00ade.webp 400w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/SCG_Panel_Map_hu1c16bbbe2e5dc55abb81abf305f056cd_1802779_64d5a90e73a7ea91598fea08aedb8a53.webp 760w,
               /project/alpine-glaciology/SCG_Panel_Map_hu1c16bbbe2e5dc55abb81abf305f056cd_1802779_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/alpine-glaciology/SCG_Panel_Map_hu1c16bbbe2e5dc55abb81abf305f056cd_1802779_0042bc5172d2e3a3539b00c912b00ade.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;730&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Subglacial Hydrology</title>
      <link>https://example.com/project/subglacial-hydrology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/project/subglacial-hydrology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;subglacial-hydrology-observation&#34;&gt;Subglacial Hydrology Observation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Radar sounding is one of the predominant geophysical tools used for investigating subglacial lakes. However, lake locations identified with radar have not coincided with lakes identified at the surface with spaceborne lidar methods. We found that volume scattering on small water inclusions in temperate ice directly above the lake lid are suppressing the radar echo from the lake and therefore obscuring the lake from the radar image.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/subglacial-hydrology/SLW_scattering_hu5afa65e98885c05a57a876273a0bfd6f_2026270_706d6da559a65e21ada74f4779e23302.webp 400w,
               /project/subglacial-hydrology/SLW_scattering_hu5afa65e98885c05a57a876273a0bfd6f_2026270_6fa3f05574019a012ae4a6de2f02ef22.webp 760w,
               /project/subglacial-hydrology/SLW_scattering_hu5afa65e98885c05a57a876273a0bfd6f_2026270_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/subglacial-hydrology/SLW_scattering_hu5afa65e98885c05a57a876273a0bfd6f_2026270_706d6da559a65e21ada74f4779e23302.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;378&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;subglacial-hydrology-modeling&#34;&gt;Subglacial Hydrology Modeling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerical models of subglacial hydrologic systems typically distinguish between two end-member drainage systems. Distributed systems include slow drainage through thin water films at the ice-bed interface, flow through porous sediment layers, or linked cavity networks where water occupies cavities on the lee side of bedrock bumps. Channelized systems consist of efficient conduits, often modeled as Röthlisberger channels (R-channels) carved into basal ice or Nye channels incised into bedrock. Real subglacial systems often contain elements of both, and capturing the transition between these states is a key modeling challenge.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/subglacial-hydrology/ConceptualModel_hu8376abf29fdbc3abf8f5685b31e65826_315923_407a1a2a071cfc2121dff15554ae0164.webp 400w,
               /project/subglacial-hydrology/ConceptualModel_hu8376abf29fdbc3abf8f5685b31e65826_315923_30465ef60248613b2618a3525b8800bb.webp 760w,
               /project/subglacial-hydrology/ConceptualModel_hu8376abf29fdbc3abf8f5685b31e65826_315923_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/subglacial-hydrology/ConceptualModel_hu8376abf29fdbc3abf8f5685b31e65826_315923_407a1a2a071cfc2121dff15554ae0164.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;333&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/subglacial-hydrology/MapView_StableVariables_hub27f6db6d612edf8a967883a506b83c0_653509_88781dfc0461a4bdcb05bf83ed8bc1f8.webp 400w,
               /project/subglacial-hydrology/MapView_StableVariables_hub27f6db6d612edf8a967883a506b83c0_653509_218a272fe506df24383e4a344ea4de4c.webp 760w,
               /project/subglacial-hydrology/MapView_StableVariables_hub27f6db6d612edf8a967883a506b83c0_653509_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/project/subglacial-hydrology/MapView_StableVariables_hub27f6db6d612edf8a967883a506b83c0_653509_88781dfc0461a4bdcb05bf83ed8bc1f8.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;380&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
