<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Educational | Benjamin Hills</title>
    <link>https://example.com/category/educational/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://example.com/category/educational/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Educational</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://example.com/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Educational</title>
      <link>https://example.com/category/educational/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sea-Level Fingerprinting</title>
      <link>https://example.com/blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Projections of sea-level rise from the International Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) 5th Assessment Report are daunting to say the least. Policy makers are most concerned about the changes coming in the next century, over which we could see up to a full meter of sea-level rise. Even under the best-case scenario, dramatically curbing emissions today, the oceans will rise considerably by year 2100 (see the figure below). Looking beyond that 100-year mark though, the rates of sea-level rise become much more uncertain. The largest uncertainty in future sea-level projections is that associated with dynamic losses from the West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS). Dynamic losses are those from speedup of the ice sheet, resulting in drawdown of interior ice and more calving into the ocean. Unlike ice melting, which pretty much scales linearly with the global air temperature, these dynamic losses could entirely eliminate an unstable ice sheet on the timescale of decades to centuries rather than millennia.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-historic-and-projected-sea-level-change-from-pre-industrial-1700-future-projections-are-for-shown-for-the-very-high-emission-scenario-red-and-the-very-low-emission-scenario-blueipcc-ar5httpwwwipccchreportar5wg1ulvpnh_ix8e&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Historic and projected sea-level change from pre-industrial (1700). Future projections are for shown for the very high emission scenario (red) and the very low emission scenario (blue). [IPCC AR5](http://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/#.UlvpNH_Ix8E)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/ipcc_ar5_13-27_hue4a9bb055a15b72671004250451c24ae_35173_5856d5a353079dbfde643b99970a308e.webp 400w,
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/ipcc_ar5_13-27_hue4a9bb055a15b72671004250451c24ae_35173_55bdff5ffb534d7a431336680ec5769d.webp 760w,
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/ipcc_ar5_13-27_hue4a9bb055a15b72671004250451c24ae_35173_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/ipcc_ar5_13-27_hue4a9bb055a15b72671004250451c24ae_35173_5856d5a353079dbfde643b99970a308e.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;589&#34;
               height=&#34;556&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Historic and projected sea-level change from pre-industrial (1700). Future projections are for shown for the very high emission scenario (red) and the very low emission scenario (blue). &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/#.UlvpNH_Ix8E&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IPCC AR5&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most simple way to think about the sea level in a non-steady condition is in the analogy with a large pool of water. When extra water is added to the pool, or if the water expands due to an increase in temperature, its average level will come up. This model of the mean, or &amp;rsquo;eustatic,&amp;rsquo; sea level is often termed the &amp;lsquo;bathtub model&amp;rsquo; because it is like thinking of the global oceans as a bathtub and the added water as a turn of the faucet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is useful to conceptualize the bathtub model for preliminary calculations, in reality, sea-level rise does not come in this globally-averaged sense. A visualization from NASA shows that the sea-level change that we have recorded with satellites over the last 23 years is variable throughout the Earth&amp;rsquo;s oceans. The most obvious sources for the regional variations in this visualization include shifts in ocean currents or natural oscillations in climate. There are even localized human influences on regional sea level such as the rapid subsidence of a coastal city like New Orleans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above examples of regional sea-level rise are relatively complicated to fully understand or to project into the future. However, a more systematic sea-level adjustment comes with any change in mass of an ice sheet. Not only does a decrease in ice-sheet mass mean more water into the ocean, and thus a change in the eustatic sea level, but the mass of an ice sheet has a regional control on sea level as well. Each ice sheet having its own unique signature, these regional controls are termed sea-level &amp;lsquo;fingerprints.&amp;rsquo; Sea-level fingerprints are the result of several physical processes acting together, and only recently they were directly measured for the first time using satellites. I briefly explain the physical processes of fingerprinting below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the Earth&amp;rsquo;s ice sheets are massive enough to attract the ocean toward them, much like the moon attracts the ocean to create tides. Therefore, if an ice sheet loses mass, the force with which it attracts the ocean toward it decreases and the local sea level falls nearby the ice sheet. If the ocean is to conserve water though (which it must), a local drop in sea level around the ice sheet means additional rise in sea level far away from the ice sheet. This idea of self-gravitation by the ice sheet mass is drawn out in the figure below.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-self-gravitation-of-an-ice-sheet-national-academies-presshttpswwwnapeduread18373chapter4&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Self-gravitation of an ice sheet. [National Academies Press](https://www.nap.edu/read/18373/chapter/4)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/selfgravitation-e1521560665946_hu59304f0243382091d904558f1d9bf9c5_102749_8b3d2f6100097ef6614a53c3ba5ac1ed.webp 400w,
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/selfgravitation-e1521560665946_hu59304f0243382091d904558f1d9bf9c5_102749_42dbaa00d3d92449c7d082e358921ceb.webp 760w,
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/selfgravitation-e1521560665946_hu59304f0243382091d904558f1d9bf9c5_102749_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/selfgravitation-e1521560665946_hu59304f0243382091d904558f1d9bf9c5_102749_8b3d2f6100097ef6614a53c3ba5ac1ed.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;592&#34;
               height=&#34;451&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Self-gravitation of an ice sheet. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nap.edu/read/18373/chapter/4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;National Academies Press&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the earth under an ice sheet is not completely &amp;lsquo;solid&amp;rsquo; in the sense that it would be unable to deform; on the contrary, the upper mantle flows viscously over long timescales, which permits the motion of tectonic plates. When a mass load (e.g. an ice sheet) is created on the surface of the Earth, the mantle viscously readjusts itself to that new state over the timescales of thousands of years. Likewise, when an ice sheet melts and disappears, the mantle fills in and the overlying crust subsequently rises up to its original elevation from before the presence of that mass load. This concept is called isostasy, and it is also important for relative sea-level rise. Today, previously glaciated regions such as the land around the Hudson Bay in Canada are still rising in elevation, or isostatically rebounding, by up to ~1 cm/yr as we come out of the last ice age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most recently developed in the scientific literature is a third physical process, where alterations in ice masses near the poles can change the manner in which the Earth rotates. We know that the rotation of the earth creates a centrifugal force that pushes more water out at the equator than at the poles. In a similar manner, the rock mass of the Earth itself has an equatorial bulge. However, the axis of rotation and the corresponding equator are not necessarily fixed. If one of the ice sheets melts, the planet will slightly adjust on its axis of rotation in a way that conserves angular momentum. This adjustment would redistribute some amount of water toward the new equator. Even if only adjusted slightly, this shift in rotation would dramatically effect the extent of sea-level rise at low latitudes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above factors add up to describe a different story for future (and past) sea-level rise depending on what the melt source is for water added to the ocean. The characteristics of a global ocean under collapse of the WAIS would look dramatically different from that under collapse of the Greenland Ice Sheet. Research today is using the sea-level fingerprints of each of the ice sheets to make inferences about the nature of ice sheet collapse in geologic history. Namely, that the WAIS most likely collapsed during the last interglacial period based on present-day high stands of corals around the world. Unfortunately, this evidence for historic WAIS collapse is particularly supportive of the potential for rapid dynamic losses in the near-future as mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-relative-sea-level-fingerprints-for-greenland-left-and-west-antarctica-right-the-scale-is-dimensionless-with-1-being-equal-to-the-eustatic-global-mean-sea-level-rise-and-negative-being-a-regional-drop-in-sea-level-hay-et-al-2015httpswwwnaturecomarticlesnature14093&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Relative sea-level fingerprints for Greenland (left) and West Antarctica (right). The scale is dimensionless, with 1 being equal to the eustatic (global mean) sea level rise and negative being a regional drop in sea level  [(Hay et al., 2015)](https://www.nature.com/articles/nature14093).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/fingerprints_hu78f147769a67a20b7fc9070ce9fb86f8_1463218_1eaebf29742993e6bb4fc2da22936160.webp 400w,
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/fingerprints_hu78f147769a67a20b7fc9070ce9fb86f8_1463218_f9d1c6596df1b83ec3d23aee16d10312.webp 760w,
               /blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/fingerprints_hu78f147769a67a20b7fc9070ce9fb86f8_1463218_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/sea-level-fingerprinting/fingerprints_hu78f147769a67a20b7fc9070ce9fb86f8_1463218_1eaebf29742993e6bb4fc2da22936160.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;256&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Relative sea-level fingerprints for Greenland (left) and West Antarctica (right). The scale is dimensionless, with 1 being equal to the eustatic (global mean) sea level rise and negative being a regional drop in sea level  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature14093&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;(Hay et al., 2015)&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall effect of sea-level fingerprinting is sadly not in our favor. The figure above shows that the WAIS, which is the most likely to rapidly collapse in the near-future, could contribute to sea-level rise of greater than the global mean in the most densely populated regions of the world such as North America, Europe, and Eastern Asia. The take home point here is that we should be preparing for sea-level rise in a well educated manner. While city planners are beginning to incorporate a rising ocean into their assessments, they often use the misinformed global mean, whereas local estimates could be quite variable from that eustatic value.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crystalline Ice</title>
      <link>https://example.com/blog/crystalline-ice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.com/blog/crystalline-ice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Now suppose,&amp;rsquo; chortled Dr. Breed, enjoying himself, &amp;rsquo;that there were many possible ways in which water could crystallize, could freeze. Suppose that the sort of ice we skate upon and put into highballs&amp;ndash;what we might call ice-one&amp;ndash; is only one of several types of ice. Suppose water always froze as ice-one on Earth because it had never had a seed to teach it how to form ice-two, ice-three, ice-four&amp;hellip;? And suppose,&amp;rsquo; he rapped on his desk with his old hand again, &amp;rsquo;that there were one form, which we will call ice-nine&amp;ndash;a crystal as hard as this desk&amp;ndash;with a melting point of, let us say, one-hundred degrees Fahrenheit, or, better still, a melting point of one-hundred-and-thirty degrees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an excerpt from Kurt Vonnegut Jr.&amp;rsquo;s novel, Cat&amp;rsquo;s Cradle, in which he presents &amp;lsquo;ice-nine&amp;rsquo;, a crystalline form of water ice with the potential to destroy the world as we know it. Vonnegut&amp;rsquo;s ice-nine, which I will call ice IX for consistency with the scientific naming convention, is stable at room temperature, and the crystalline structure will propagate from a seed. Hence, when liquid water is brought into contact with an ice IX crystal, it spontaneously freezes as long as it is below the melting point of this crystalline phase, 113ºC. The societal implications for such a crystal are boundless, for if it came into contact with the Earth&amp;rsquo;s water cycle the entire planet would freeze over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The background for Vonnegut&amp;rsquo;s story is interesting. He was brought up in a scientific family, and a certain scientific style often shows through in his writing. The oldest brother, Bernard, was a physical chemist who, at the time, worked at General Electric (he actually helped Kurt get his first job at GE as well). For his work in atmospheric physics, Bernard was credited with discovering silver iodide cloud seeding, a technique that has widespread use today. Having a brother who studied ice nucleation interested Vonnegut in the phases of ice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, this novel was published in 1963 which was a highly contentious time in the history of weapons research. There was an imminent fear of soviet attack, so much scientific research was directed toward our nuclear arsenal and other weapons. Bernard&amp;rsquo;s research on cloud seeding even had military applications. However, many scientists, including Bernard, had ethical issues with working toward such a goal. The ice IX story plays with these ideas, highlighting the danger of global weapons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the ice IX of Cat&amp;rsquo;s Cradle is a fictional crystalline form, there truly are many distinct forms of water ice. In fact, one of the features that makes water unique is that it has nearly 20 crystalline phases that we know of, many more than most crystal-forming compounds. Most of these exist only in the laboratory, and all ice that we interact with on the Earth resides in one familiar crystalline phase called ice Ih.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;water-molecule&#34;&gt;Water Molecule&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to discuss crystal structure for phases of ice, we must first review the properties of the water molecule. Water, H2O, is made up of two hydrogen and one oxygen atom. We know this from, among several other experiments, electrolysis where H2O is split up into its constituents of H2 and O2 gases. In the water molecule, the electronegative oxygen atom shares its electrons with the hydrogen atoms in strong covalent bonds.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-water-molecule-has-two-hydrogen-and-one-oxygen-atom-the-angle-between-covalent-bonds-is-about-1045º-and-the-distance-from-the-oxygen-nucleus-to-hydrogen-is-about-1-angstrom&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The water molecule has two hydrogen and one oxygen atom. The angle between covalent bonds is about 104.5º and the distance from the oxygen nucleus to hydrogen is about 1 angstrom.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/crystalline-ice/watermolecule_hube666d9788fb7101f5181fd87be78acf_998764_93af586cc6f61a2bba9e330a413eacb2.webp 400w,
               /blog/crystalline-ice/watermolecule_hube666d9788fb7101f5181fd87be78acf_998764_cc4a37d413d576881933731fd587d3b8.webp 760w,
               /blog/crystalline-ice/watermolecule_hube666d9788fb7101f5181fd87be78acf_998764_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/crystalline-ice/watermolecule_hube666d9788fb7101f5181fd87be78acf_998764_93af586cc6f61a2bba9e330a413eacb2.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;578&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      The water molecule has two hydrogen and one oxygen atom. The angle between covalent bonds is about 104.5º and the distance from the oxygen nucleus to hydrogen is about 1 angstrom.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly to the crystalline structure of ice, the electrons are not shared equally in the covalent bonds. The oxygen atoms hold on more closely to the electrons, which in turn creates an electric dipole for this molecule with the oxygen being the negative end and hydrogens positive. Because each molecule has its own dipole, there is some amount of electromagnetic attraction/repulsion between water molecules which ultimately controls many of the interesting properties that we commonly observe in the water substance. Most critically, the electromagnetic attraction between the negative oxygen and the positive hydrogen promotes hydrogen bonding between molecules. In a lattice, the hydrogen bonds determine the crystalline form of ice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ice-ih&#34;&gt;Ice Ih&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are four hydrogen bonding sites for each water molecule, one at each of the hydrogen atoms, and two additional sites at the &amp;rsquo;lone pairs&amp;rsquo; of electrons which are located on the opposite side of the oxygen atom from the hydrogens. The four bonding sites promote a tetrahedral structure for stacking in ice crystals. Because of the angles between bonds in the tetrahedron, ice crystals form as a series of crinkled sheets each as a tessellation of open hexagons. We call these sheets the basal planes and they are stacked along the &amp;lsquo;c-axis&amp;rsquo; which is orthogonal to the surface of the basal plane. In the ice crystal that we are familiar with, ice Ih, the sheets stack nicely on top of one another, alternating their crinkled pattern A-B-A-B. In this crystal, the hexagonal form in the basal plane is consistent throughout, creating a hexagonal column in three dimensions, hence the &amp;lsquo;h&amp;rsquo; in ice Ih. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hydrogen atoms within an ice crystal do not always face up along the c-axis, and they do not always stay in the basal plane, they are disordered. Disorder as well as small impurities in the crystal, or &amp;lsquo;dislocations&amp;rsquo;, explain many of the properties of ice, such as its mechanical, thermal, and some of its electrical properties. Considering the disorder in the ice Ih crystal, Nobel laureate Linus Pauling theorized that ice has some amount of residual entropy at zero Kelvin, meaning that the disorder would maintain even to the lowest possible temperature. His theory was later confirmed by calorimetry experiments in which changes in entropy were inferred by applying heat to ice and measuring the temperature change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;alternate-forms&#34;&gt;Alternate Forms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At low pressure there are two other forms of the ice crystal. The first is ice XI which is ordered, meaning that it would in fact have have zero entropy at 0K. If ice Ih were held at a low enough energy state (below 72K) for a long enough time, the water molecules would eventually order themselves into ice XI. The third low-pressure ice crystal is technically in the same category as ice Ih, but it is a cubic crystal rather than hexagonal, so it is termed ice Ic. This crystal does naturally form in the Earth&amp;rsquo;s atmosphere when clouds are very cold (below ~170K or -100ºC).&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-phase-diagram-of-water-over-a-large-range-of-temperatures-and-pressures-sourcehttpswebhomephydukeeduhsg363table-imageswater-phase-diagramhtml&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Phase diagram of water over a large range of temperatures and pressures. [Source](https://webhome.phy.duke.edu/~hsg/363/table-images/water-phase-diagram.html)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /blog/crystalline-ice/phase-diagram_hu36918e10f8af4dbaf69be9e919579f3c_235863_c56671314f618958244f0c7ca94ba0c6.webp 400w,
               /blog/crystalline-ice/phase-diagram_hu36918e10f8af4dbaf69be9e919579f3c_235863_354d8e3074dafe7b6f00ddc555ca4445.webp 760w,
               /blog/crystalline-ice/phase-diagram_hu36918e10f8af4dbaf69be9e919579f3c_235863_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://example.com/blog/crystalline-ice/phase-diagram_hu36918e10f8af4dbaf69be9e919579f3c_235863_c56671314f618958244f0c7ca94ba0c6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;510&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Phase diagram of water over a large range of temperatures and pressures. &lt;a href=&#34;https://webhome.phy.duke.edu/~hsg/363/table-images/water-phase-diagram.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remaining ice phases all form at high pressure (on the order of GPa or greater, which is 10,000 times atmospheric pressure). At these high pressures, the bond angles in the water molecule can bend in order to achieve a higher density crystal. These high pressure phases are more dense than ice Ih and would sink in water. While the pressures on the Earth&amp;rsquo;s surface are much too low to achieve any of these crystalline forms, it has been hypothesized that they might exist deep in the Earth where pressures are extremely high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, Vonnegut was somewhat prescient in writing about ice IX, but he never intended to describe a real ice crystal. His ice IX was an analogy for weaponized science during the cold war. While the ice IX that we know today is only stable at very high pressures and low temperatures, the analogy still holds, especially as North Korea continues to push their nuclear agenda forward and President Trump proposes increased military spending.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
